<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Geometry &#8211; Geometric Algebra Explorer</title>
	<atom:link href="/index.php/tag/geometry/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Voyaging the Computational Universe with Geometric Algebra</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 09:15:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.8.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/cropped-GAExplorer-Icon-150x150.jpg</url>
	<title>Geometry &#8211; Geometric Algebra Explorer</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Cybernetics with Transdisciplinary Geometric Algebra</title>
		<link>/index.php/2017/01/27/ga-cybernetics/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 13:23:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ahmad Eid]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[GA Applications]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometric Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interview]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer Vision]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Control]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cybernetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometric Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lie Groups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neural Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Projective Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robotics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://gacomputing.info/?p=2369</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Hard sciences are successful because they deal with the soft problems; soft sciences are struggling because they deal with the hard problems. &#8212; Heinz von Foerster Cyberneticist, or cybernetician, is a person practicing Cybernetics: a&#46;&#46;&#46;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2017/01/27/ga-cybernetics/">Cybernetics with Transdisciplinary Geometric Algebra</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Cybernetics.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-0" title=""><img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2372" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Cybernetics-1024x680.jpg" alt="Cybernetics" width="1024" height="680" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Cybernetics-1024x680.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Cybernetics-300x199.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Cybernetics-768x510.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Cybernetics.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></p>
<blockquote><p>Hard sciences are successful because they deal with the soft problems; soft sciences are struggling because they deal with the hard problems. &#8212; Heinz von Foerster</p></blockquote>
<p><span class="dropcap">A</span> Cyberneticist, or cybernetician, is a person practicing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cybernetics" target="_blank">Cybernetics</a>: a transdisciplinary approach for exploring regulatory systems; their structures, constraints, and possibilities. Professor Eduardo Bayro-Corrochano is one such leading academic who uses Geometric Algebra to handle the diverse fields of theoretical knowledge and practical application he needs. Such fields include Robotics, Neural Computing, Computer Vision, and Lie Algebras. In this post, I interview Prof. Eduardo Bayro who tells us about how using GA in his work can simplify dealing with such diverse fields, and how can GA relate, generalize, and unify ideas from these fields together in his mind and the minds of his students.</p>
<hr />
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Prof.-Eduardo-Bayro.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-1" title=""><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-2380" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Prof.-Eduardo-Bayro-180x300.jpg" alt="Prof. Eduardo Bayro" width="180" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Prof.-Eduardo-Bayro-180x300.jpg 180w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Prof.-Eduardo-Bayro.jpg 409w" sizes="(max-width: 180px) 100vw, 180px" /></a>Professor Eduardo Bayro started working on the applications of GA in the late 1990’s. His work is to stress the application of GA in cybernetics which typically involves Robotics, Neural Computing, Computer Vision, and Lie Algebras. Using GA-based geometric computing he tackled problems related to the building of intelligent machines, particularly Humanoids, to formulate algorithms for dealing with computer graphics curves, spheres, hyperplanes, and simple geometric tasks. Another goal is to build intelligent machines with real devices using geometric control, geometric perception and even quaternion wavelet transform, quaternion spike, or quantum quaternion neurons. Currently, he is preparing a new book series of 3 volumes on these topics. He is laying out the theory of future geometric intelligent robots and machines with powerful FPGA and Nvidia geometric accelerators.</p>
<hr />
<p><span style="color: #003366;"><strong>Tell us about the benefits of using Geometric Algebra in Geometric Computing applications.  </strong></span></p>
<p>Geometric Algebra (GA) is a powerful geometric language for the modeling of the physics of systems. It is a highly intuitive language and provides many algebraic tools very useful to tackle complex equation manipulations. GA allows economical representations of transformations due to the GA multivector representation as opposite to analytic geometry or vector calculus. GA-based representations avoid redundant parameters and elegantly encapsulate the geometry of the problem. As a result due to its economical representations, GA is a well-suited framework for the development of real-time computations.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #003366;"><strong>How can using GA simplify dealing with the diverse fields of interdisciplinary applications you are working on? What about its range of applicability?</strong></span></p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/normal_ams_borro.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-2" title=""><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-2386" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/normal_ams_borro-257x300.jpg" alt="Non-Euclidean Geometry" width="257" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/normal_ams_borro-257x300.jpg 257w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/normal_ams_borro.jpg 400w" sizes="(max-width: 257px) 100vw, 257px" /></a>GA achieves the unification of many domains like multilinear algebra, multivariable analysis, conformal geometry, Lie group and Lie algebras, projective geometry, quantum mechanics and general relativity. GA allows:</p>
<ul>
<li>Extending and completing algebraic operations on vectors and multi-vectors.</li>
<li>Providing unified concepts for geometry and algebra.</li>
<li>Providing explicit interpretation of geometric entities and operations on them in arbitrary dimensions with Euclidean and pseudo-Euclidean metrics.</li>
<li>Acting as an advanced formalism for rotations and in general Lie groups in arbitrary dimensions.</li>
<li>Acting as a metalanguage for high-level reasoning.</li>
</ul>
<p>Because of these features, Geometric Algebra has a wide range of applications: graphics engineering, signal and image processing, computer vision, neural networks and quantum computing, machine learning, and robotics.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #003366;"><strong>Tell us about the recent developments of applying GA in your research activities.</strong></span></p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/jetson-tk1.png" data-rel="lightbox-3" title=""><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-2382" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/jetson-tk1-300x171.png" alt="jetson-tk1" width="300" height="171" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/jetson-tk1-300x171.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/jetson-tk1.png 350w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a>Recent achievements in geometric accelerators using packets like Versor (P. Colapinto) or Gaalop (Geometric Algebra Algorithms Optimizer, D. Hildenbrand) allow us with FPGA or NVidia to accelerate computations even more. In my lab, we develop and build intelligent machines like in medical robotics or humanoids. The development of GA algorithms follows: algorithmic modeling, using our own C++ programs or Versor, then simply the algorithms with Maple or Gaalop and accelerate them with either FPFGA or Nvidia. The results are quite impressive for real time applications and the visualization of computing in higher dimensions which in turn helps us to gain insight and achieve correctness in the prove of theorems and improve the performance of our algorithms. We are working now to develop in the next 3 years a single small chip for geometric computing using GA with a power superior as the <a href="http://www.nvidia.com/object/jetson-tk1-embedded-dev-kit.html" target="_blank">Jetson TK1 Nvidia</a> card.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #003366;"><strong>In your opinion, are there any relations between Neural Learning and Geometric Learning? How do you use GA as a tool for exploring such relations?</strong></span></p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/neurons-1739997_640.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-4" title=""><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-2383" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/neurons-1739997_640-300x214.jpg" alt="Neurons" width="300" height="214" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/neurons-1739997_640-300x214.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/neurons-1739997_640.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a>The tricky question is what should be a true geometric learning? We started by generalizing the McCulloch-Pitts neuron replacing its inner product via the geometric product, so the neural network weights are then multivectors and the learning rules are formulated using the gradient of multivectors as well. Our networks for classification via their kernels map the data using multivectors to a direct product of Hilbert spaces to separate multivector clusters, this helps a lot to find optimal hyperplanes. We have worked on geometric neural computing since 1995, in fact, we have generalized in GA most of the neural networks: i.e. multivector valued [SOM, NeuralGAS, MLP, ART], Clifford SVM and Quaternion Spike neural Network, currently we are developing the quaternion quantum Neural Network. This year we are also focusing on geometric high-order recurrent Neural Networks.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #003366;"><strong>Tell us about your books describing your valuable work and experience with GA, and the new books you are currently preparing.</strong></span></p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Geometric-Computing-Book.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-5" title=""><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-2384" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Geometric-Computing-Book-199x300.jpg" alt="Geometric Computing Book" width="199" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Geometric-Computing-Book-199x300.jpg 199w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Geometric-Computing-Book.jpg 331w" sizes="(max-width: 199px) 100vw, 199px" /></a>I have been teaching since 1997 using the material of my work which was then published in two books:</p>
<ul>
<li>Geometric Computing for Perception Action Systems. Eduardo Bayro-Corrochano, Springer-Verlag, April 2001.</li>
<li>Geometric Computing: for Wavelet Transforms, Robot Vision, Learning, Control, and Action. Eduardo Bayro-Corrochano, Springer-Verlag, 2010.</li>
</ul>
<p>I am preparing a more comprehensive series in three volumes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Vol. I: GA for computer vision and machine learning,</li>
<li>Vol. II: GA for Robotics,</li>
<li>Vol. III: GA for Signal Processing, Filtering, Transforms and Quantum Computing.</li>
</ul>
<p>These three volumes are based on my first two books, of course, while including new exciting results. My books generally differ from many the current books on GA applications because my books cover computer vision, graphics engineering, neural networks, machine learning, robotics, integral transforms, and ultimately the endeavor of building intelligent machines with GA; they present real applications. The other books are more related to the foundations of GA and its restricted use to the develop algorithms in computer science and its sub-fields like computer graphics. That is why my continuous work during all these years is helping to be able to prepare these new three volumes, which I believe will certainly establish the true geometric computing for the future development of intelligent machines.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #003366;"><strong>Tell us about your practical experience teaching applied Geometric Algebra. How do you overcome the challenges you face while using GA in teaching?</strong></span></p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/robocup-400467_640.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-6" title=""><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-2387" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/robocup-400467_640-300x198.jpg" alt="Robocup" width="300" height="198" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/robocup-400467_640-300x198.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/robocup-400467_640.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a>I call for studying and applying GA for future cybernetics in my lectures at different universities in Europe, North America (MIT) and Latin America. I have students with different backgrounds as in physics, mathematics, or engineering; some well prepared for some topics and less for others, so I start as in a fractal approach for conveying knowledge:</p>
<ul>
<li>We study 2D- and 3D-GA to become acquainted with the formulation of the geometric primitives and the use of different Clifford operations.</li>
<li>Then we model the kinematics of points, lines and planes particularly to understand well screw theory and differential kinematics.</li>
<li>Then I explain the basic of differential geometry like the Geometric Laplace-Beltrami Operator for applications in Euclidean and pseudo-Euclidean spaces.</li>
<li>We study in depth Lie Groups and Lie algebras using spinors and versors for Euclidean, Affine, and 2D and 3D projective geometry.</li>
<li>Then I explain projective geometry using Euclidean and Minkowski metrics for the projective plane and spaces and extensions of the projective space in R(3,3).</li>
</ul>
<p>In this manner, the students have learned the most important ingredients to move the Conformal Geometric Algebra and high dimensional geometric algebras like G(6,3) and G(8,2). Thanks to our optimized routines for GA in C++ (with NVidia) and Maple (using the Clifford 14.0 package of R. Ablamowicz), we can prove theorems and develop real-time algorithms for intelligent machines.</p>
<p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=%2Findex.php%2F2017%2F01%2F27%2Fga-cybernetics%2F&amp;linkname=Cybernetics%20with%20Transdisciplinary%20Geometric%20Algebra" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_twitter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/twitter?linkurl=%2Findex.php%2F2017%2F01%2F27%2Fga-cybernetics%2F&amp;linkname=Cybernetics%20with%20Transdisciplinary%20Geometric%20Algebra" title="Twitter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_google_plus" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/google_plus?linkurl=%2Findex.php%2F2017%2F01%2F27%2Fga-cybernetics%2F&amp;linkname=Cybernetics%20with%20Transdisciplinary%20Geometric%20Algebra" title="Google+" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=%2Findex.php%2F2017%2F01%2F27%2Fga-cybernetics%2F&amp;title=Cybernetics%20with%20Transdisciplinary%20Geometric%20Algebra" data-a2a-url="/index.php/2017/01/27/ga-cybernetics/" data-a2a-title="Cybernetics with Transdisciplinary Geometric Algebra"></a></p><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2017/01/27/ga-cybernetics/">Cybernetics with Transdisciplinary Geometric Algebra</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Geometric Algebra: Ascension of the Mind</title>
		<link>/index.php/2017/01/13/ga-computing3/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 14:00:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ahmad Eid]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Geometric Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Blade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Clifford Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Distance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Generative Modeling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hyper-complex Number]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linear Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matrix]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multivector]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Optimizing Compiler]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Versor]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://gacomputing.info/?p=636</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>If you understand something in only one way, then you don&#8217;t really understand it at all. The secret of what anything means to us depends on how we&#8217;ve connected it to all other things&#46;&#46;&#46;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2017/01/13/ga-computing3/">Geometric Algebra: Ascension of the Mind</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-2197 size-large" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/flow-1086468_1280-1024x768.jpg" alt="Abstract Flow" width="1024" height="768" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/flow-1086468_1280-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/flow-1086468_1280-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/flow-1086468_1280-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/flow-1086468_1280.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<blockquote><p>If you understand something in only one way, then you don&#8217;t really understand it at all. The secret of what anything means to us depends on how we&#8217;ve connected it to all other things we know. Well-connected representations let you turn ideas around in your mind, to envision things from many perspectives until you find one that works for you. And that&#8217;s<br />
what we mean by thinking! &#8212; Marvin Minsky.</p></blockquote>
<p><span class="dropcap">I</span> discovered <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geometric_algebra">Geometric Algebra</a> (GA) back in 2003 and it caught my attention immediately. In my whole life as a student, engineer, researcher, and teacher I&#8217;ve never met a symbolic mathematical system so beautifully close to geometric abstractions. In this post, I try to explain how Geometric Algebra can express, unify, and generalize many geometric abstractions we use as engineers and computer scientists.</p>
<h3>The Generative Pattern</h3>
<blockquote><p>What I cannot create, I do not understand &#8212; Richard Feynman</p></blockquote>
<p>There are many ways we can understand Geometric Computing depending on our background and intended applications. One of the ways I find most attractive is the pattern of <strong>Geometric Generators</strong>. To explain geometric generators, I will give some simple examples in 3D Euclidean geometry.</p>
<p>If we have 3 real numbers a, b, and c, what geometric concepts can we represent using these 3 numbers? The following are two possible answers that we can get from most engineers and computer scientists:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>A location in space:</strong> We are familiar with any <strong>point</strong> in our 3D Euclidean space being written as the 3-tuple (a, b, c).</li>
<li><strong>A direction in space:</strong> The same form of 3-tuple (a, b, c) can be also interpreted as a <strong>free vector </strong>in our geometric space.</li>
</ol>
<div id="attachment_2205" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/640px-Terragen_render.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-0" title=""><img class="wp-image-2205 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/640px-Terragen_render-300x225.jpg" alt="Generative Modeling" width="300" height="225" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/640px-Terragen_render-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/640px-Terragen_render.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Generative Modeling can be used in simple geometric constructions up to complex graphics scene generation (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scenery_generator">source</a>)</p></div>
<p>The two concepts are related but have very different geometric semantics and a separate set of legal geometric operations for each. For example, vectors can be linearly combined (scaled and added) to get other vectors, adding two locations has no meaning geometrically, we can add a vector and a point to obtain a new point, etc. There is also some implicit information required to complete these two representations. We assume we have a basic set of 3 <strong>orthogonal axes</strong> that intersect at an <strong>origin </strong>point, we call that construction <strong>the coordinates frame</strong>. If we change the selected frame while keeping the geometric locations and directions as they are in relation to each other, we must update the 3-tuples numerically representing each location and direction in our problem. The main point here is that in order to <strong>generate</strong> a geometric location\direction in 3D Euclidean space we need to use 3 intersecting axes, common for all locations\directions, and 3 real numbers per location\direction. Then we need some algebraic operations, like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linear_combination">linear</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Affine_combination">affine combinations</a>, that we can use to generate a representation of a direction\location from these basic elements.</p>
<p>Let&#8217;s go one step further. If we have two locations P and Q, what can we geometrically generate in our selected space? The first thing we can think of is an <strong>infinite straight line;</strong> a <strong>line segment</strong> and a <strong>ray</strong> are related but different geometric concepts that can be generated by these same two points. What about a point C and a real number r? Maybe a sphere with center C and radius r, or a weighted-point (a location having mass, charge, or density associated with it). What about an infinite flat plane N and a non-parallel line L? We can generate the whole space from these two objects by &#8220;sliding&#8221; N along L. We can also generate a single location (their point of intersection), a single real number (the angle between L and N), a single line (the projection of L on N), a pair of infinite cones by rotating N around L, and many other geometric objects. Just by varying the <strong>geometric operations</strong> we use on N and L we generate new constructions. What if we have an infinitely extending cylinder? We can extract its <strong>axis</strong> (a line), its <strong>radius</strong> (a real number), we can generate many points on its surface (for example to approximate it using a triangular mesh), and we can slice it using flat planes to get circles, ellipses, or pairs of parallel lines.</p>
<div id="attachment_2215" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/6811026597_c282242276_z.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-1" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-2215" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/6811026597_c282242276_z-300x205.jpg" alt="Parametric Architectural Design" width="300" height="205" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/6811026597_c282242276_z-300x205.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/6811026597_c282242276_z.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Parametric Architectural Design is one important application of the Geometric Generators pattern (<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/eager/6811026597">source</a>)</p></div>
<p>Now we begin to see a simple pattern and we can abstract its main components:</p>
<ol>
<li>A set of <strong>Geometric Generators</strong>: A set of abstract geometric concepts that can be used to generate new geometric concepts. This set can be specified using abstract relations (arbitrary origin, orthogonal vectors of unit length, etc.), or can be explicitly represented using numbers (e.g. coordinates) relating them to (or generating them from) a common geometric frame of reference.</li>
<li>A <strong>Geometric Algorithm</strong>: This is a sequence of steps to generate new geometric objects from the set of geometric generators. The new objects by themselves can be used as generators for more objects using other geometric algorithms; this includes the possibility of defining <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recursion_(computer_science)">recursive algorithms</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fractal">fractals</a>.</li>
<li>The <strong>Generated Geometric Concepts</strong>: By applying the geometric algorithm to the geometric generators we obtain new geometric objects of interest. This means that we can in principle use the set of generators in place of the generated concepts. For example, instead of listing all points on a line, we can simply state two points on the same line and the linear relation used for generating all the other points. Now we can transform the line (in the general sense of projective transformations for example) by transforming the generating set: its two points.</li>
</ol>
<p>Anyone who worked with Generative Modeling <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-636-1' id='enref-636-1' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(636)'>1</a></sup> clearly recognizes and practices this pattern. This understanding is not so common, however, among engineers and computer scientists, especially in the early stages of their study and research. Most of us tend to lose sight of deep geometric abstractions hidden behind the many kinds of algebraic representations we are taught to use in our models. This creates serious problems on many levels for our geometric modeling abilities:</p>
<ul>
<li>On the level of understanding the true geometric nature of the problem.</li>
<li>On the level of verifying the geometric model against possible algebraic, algorithmic, or numerical inconsistencies and special cases.</li>
<li>On the level of generalizing the model to other problems or variations of the same problem.</li>
<li>On the level of implementing the model as software.</li>
<li>On the level of symbolically communicating our ideas effectively to other people.</li>
</ul>
<p>We need to find an algebra that can be used to clearly express our generative pattern of geometry in a unified manner, independent of coordinates, and with algebraic relations generalizable to any space dimension.</p>
<h3>An Algebra for Geometric Computing</h3>
<blockquote><p>The two operations of our understanding, intuition and deduction, on which alone we have said we must rely in the acquisition of knowledge. &#8212; Rene Descartes</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_2220" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/1024px-ReverseaccumulationAD.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-2" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-2220" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/1024px-ReverseaccumulationAD-300x175.jpg" alt="Automatic Differentiation" width="300" height="175" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/1024px-ReverseaccumulationAD-300x175.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/1024px-ReverseaccumulationAD-768x448.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/1024px-ReverseaccumulationAD.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The Algebra of Dual Numbers can be used to implement Automatic Differentiation (<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:ReverseaccumulationAD.png" data-rel="lightbox-3" title="">source</a>)</p></div>
<p>For more than 100 years now we have been using many algebraic systems to symbolically and computationally encode our geometric intuition. Algebra enables the deduction of new relations between symbolic representations having geometric significance. Our bag of classical algebras we use to represent many essentially-geometric concepts and operations include:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vector_space">Vectors and Vector Spaces</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matrix_(mathematics)">Matrices</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tensor">Tensors</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real_number">Real Numbers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://betterexplained.com/articles/intuitive-arithmetic-with-complex-numbers/">Complex Numbers</a></li>
<li>Many kinds of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uw6bpPldp2A" data-rel="lightbox-video-0">hyper-complex numbers</a> like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quaternion">Quaternions</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octonion">Octonions</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dual_number">Dual Numbers</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grassmann_number">Grassmann Numbers</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypercomplex_number">many others</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Using only one of these mathematical tools we can never model all aspects of geometric abstractions found in even a single problem of practical interest. We often need to use two or more of these algebras in our symbolic formulation of geometric ideas. Even worse, some geometric algorithms contain steps that are easier (or only possible) to represent using one algebra and\or set of generators, while other steps require a different algebra and\or set of generators <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-636-2' id='enref-636-2' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(636)'>2</a></sup>. ًSo we need many algebraic representations for the same geometric concept, we need conversion steps between the representations. In effect, we need a huge number of algebraically ad-hoc techniques, whatever works, to solve our modeling problems. Sadly, we are completely lost in a jungle of symbolic abstractions, so what can we do?</p>
<p>Similar problems had been solved in some areas of engineering and computer science. Taking a quick look at problems modeled and solved with computers we find unifying algebraic systems at the core. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li>In database design, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Relational_algebra">Relational Algebra</a> is used for modeling the data stored in relational databases, and defining queries on it.</li>
<li>In logic design, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boolean_algebra">Boolean Algebra</a> is fundamental in the development of digital electronics and is provided for in all modern programming languages.</li>
<li>In data science, neural computing, computer graphics, and many other applications <a href="http://www.sosmath.com/matrix/matrix.html">Matrix Algebra</a> is the base of most computations.</li>
<li>In optimization, simulation, and <a href="http://www.autodiff.org/?module=Applications">many other applications</a>, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dual_numbers">algebra of dual numbers</a> is the base for implementing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Automatic_differentiation">Automatic Differentiation</a>, a much better practical replacement for numerical differentiation and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finite_difference_method">finite difference</a> methods.</li>
</ul>
<div id="attachment_2237" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Conformal_Embedding.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-4" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-2237" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Conformal_Embedding-300x256.jpg" alt="Conformal Embedding" width="300" height="256" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Conformal_Embedding-300x256.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Conformal_Embedding.jpg 531w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The Conformal Embedding (<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Conformal_Embedding.svg">source</a>)</p></div>
<p>For geometric computing, however, we don&#8217;t have a single unified algebraic system for our problems; this was my incorrect understanding until 2003 when I first read two online tutorials on <strong>Geometric Algebra</strong> <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-636-3' id='enref-636-3' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(636)'>3</a></sup>. I discovered that all the above algebraic systems are isomorphic to some GA or one of its subalgebras, so we can seamlessly integrate them together. I discovered that most GA relations are geometrically significant and independent of space dimension and coordinate frames.</p>
<p>Since then I discovered firsthand how Geometric Algebra shines as an algebraic system that forces us to think about geometry from the generative perspective I described above. I experienced a high level of clarity, unification, and generalization of geometric ideas I&#8217;ve never felt before. Many ideas became connected immediately after formulating them in the language of Geometric Algebra. This experience is a true ascension of the geometric mind!</p>
<p>Almost all researchers working with Geometric Algebra have a similar experience. For example, Pablo Colapinto describes Geometric Algebra as <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-636-4' id='enref-636-4' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(636)'>4</a></sup>:</p>
<blockquote><p>Geometric algebra (GA) is a combinatoric system of spatial logic based on William Clifford’s hypercomplex algebras of the 19th century. Holistic, scalable, and filled with &#8220;common sense&#8221;, GA integrates various methods for modelling and engineering dynamic systems. [&#8230;] The now classic work by the physicist David Hestenes, New Foundations for Classical Mechanics (1986) makes a strong argument for learning this approach by demonstrating the compactness of the math, while the most recent text by cyberneticist Eduardo Bayro-Corrochano, Geometric Computing: For Wavelet Transforms, Robot Vision, Learning, Control and Action (2010), demonstrates the expressivity of its powers for geometric reasoning. Many other references make a similar case: with its isomorphisms, geometric algebras encapsulate many other mathematical systems. With its outermorphisms, solutions worked out in smaller dimensions can often be extrapolated to higher dimensions. It is an expressive logic that allows intuitive mathematical experimentation across a widening range of disciplines.<br />
Working with the algebra, physicists have developed a conformal split mapping of a 3 dimensional Euclidean space G(3) into a 5-dimensional one, G(4,1), based on Riemannian projection of 3D Euclidean space (R3) onto a hypersphere. Introduced into the geometric algebra community by Hongbo Li, Alan Rockwood, and David Hestenes in 2001, the conformal model greatly simplifies and generalizes calculations of general rigid body movements in Euclidean space. As a mathematical system for describing closed form solutions within Euclidean, spherical, and hyperbolic geometries, conformal geometric algebra opens the door to a rich set of Möbius transformations typically restricted to the 2D plane. The operators which reflect, rotate, translate, twist, dilate, and boost other elements and objects are called versors.</p></blockquote>
<h3>The Universal Matrix</h3>
<blockquote><p>We may always depend on it that algebra, which cannot be translated into good English and sound common sense, is bad algebra. &#8212; William Kingdon Clifford</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_2211" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/NLA.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-5" title=""><img class="wp-image-2211 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/NLA-300x233.jpg" alt="Numerical Linear Algebra" width="300" height="233" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/NLA-300x233.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/NLA.jpg 691w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Many problems in engineering can be modeled and solved using Numerical Linear Algebra software (<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Navier_Stokes_Laminar.svg">source</a>)</p></div>
<p>Many would argue that we can use matrices to represent all kinds of algebras used in practice including <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clifford_algebra">Clifford Algebras</a>; an important subject in modern mathematics known as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representation_theory">Representation Theory</a>. This is true, theoretically speaking, but often impractical in many cases. The basic structure of a matrix and the simplicity of its addition and matrix multiplication operations is both a blessing and a curse.</p>
<p>Because matrices can represent many things, including raw lists\tables of numbers, we can use them as a universal low-level representation in our software implementations. Many numerical software systems used by engineers and computer scientists already do this: <a href="https://www.mathworks.com/products/matlab.html">MATLAB</a>, <a href="http://www.numpy.org/">NumPy</a>, <a href="http://www.alglib.net/">ALGLIB</a>, etc <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-636-5' id='enref-636-5' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(636)'>5</a></sup>. In addition, many applications like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transformation_matrix">computer graphics</a> and <a href="http://planning.cs.uiuc.edu/node111.html">robotics</a> use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homogeneous_coordinates">homogenous-coordinate matrices</a> as a universal representation for Euclidean, affine, and projective transformations. This is the good part, we can develop all our algorithms in the language of matrices based on Numerical Linear Algebra algorithms <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-636-6' id='enref-636-6' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(636)'>6</a></sup>.</p>
<p>The prices we have to pay for using such simple universal algebraic structure are numerous, for example:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Geometric Significance:</strong> Looking at an equation, expression, or algorithm expressed as operations on matrices we often can&#8217;t easily understand its geometric significance. Many algebraic operations on matrices, like transpose, eigenanalysis, determinants, etc. are difficult to interpret in a geometrically meaningful way related to the original problem. In addition, expressing everything using matrices allows for incorrectly applying algebraic operations leading to geometrically meaningless results in the context of our problem. One example is obtaining complex eigenvalues when analyzing a real transformation matrix. These complex values can indicate errors in the algorithm, computational instabilities, or data that must be removed before doing the next step. Blindly accepting all outputs can cause many problems.</li>
<li><strong>Data Redundancy:</strong> For many geometric problems a full matrix representation is too much. Symmetric matrices, diagonal matrices, triangular matrices, and orthogonal matrices all contain numerical redundancies. As an example, one famous <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matrix_representation_of_conic_sections">matrix representation of Conic Sections</a> uses symmetric matrices. Passing this representation to a matrix processing software library may need memory and processing more than necessary.</li>
<li><strong>Extracting Geometric Information:</strong> Looking at the numbers inside a matrix we can&#8217;t immediately extract important geometric information. For example, given a homogeneous general rotation matrix, we can&#8217;t just find the axis and angle of rotation by looking at its numbers. We need to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotation_matrix#Conversion_from_and_to_axis-angle">apply eigenanalysis</a> to extract this important piece of geometric information.</li>
<li><strong>Geometric Type Safety:</strong> Compatibility rules for operations on matrices are too simple for modular software design. It might be algebraically acceptable, for example, to multiply two matrices, but geometrically wrong; resulting in an intermediate result that should have been automatically caught as a compile-time or run-time error. This may lead to many problems in verifying geometric algorithms and code debugging.</li>
<li><strong>Domain Specific Optimizations:</strong> Because matrices are numerically redundant, difficult to interpret geometrically, and low-level universal representations, it&#8217;s usually very difficult to apply high-level domain specific optimizations to the geometric algorithm or computer code. This is one of the main reasons other kinds of algebra are used instead of matrices in many applications.</li>
<li><strong>Communication of Geometric Ideas:</strong> Teaching and communicating abstract geometric ideas using matrices is difficult. Matrix equations are good for low-level computations, but symbolically not suitable as a high-level language for expressing our geometric thoughts clearly. We need much training to look at a matrix equation in some application domain and understand its geometric meaning.</li>
</ul>
<h3>The Geometric Multivector</h3>
<blockquote><p>You don’t see something until you have the right metaphor to let you perceive it. &#8212; James Gleick, Chaos: Making a New Science</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_2272" style="width: 272px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Geometric-Product.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-6" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-2272" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Geometric-Product-262x300.jpg" alt="Geometric Product" width="262" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Geometric-Product-262x300.jpg 262w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Geometric-Product.jpg 482w" sizes="(max-width: 262px) 100vw, 262px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The sophisticated mathematical structure of Geometric Algebra resulting from the geometric product of its basis blades (<a href="http://www.euclideanspace.com/maths/algebra/clifford/d3/">source</a>)</p></div>
<p>Many of these problems can be avoided using Geometric Algebra and its <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multivector">multivectors</a>. GA has a much richer mathematical structure than matrix algebra as I will explain shortly. This sophisticated structure requires some time to learn but it&#8217;s logical and universal, so the learning time is well spent. Studying and using GA for several years I found many representational advantages of using multivectors over matrices, for example:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Geometric Significance</strong>: Two main types of GA multivectors exist: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blade_(geometry)">Blades</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Versor">Versors</a>. Blades can represent many geometric objects depending on the selected GA like directions, positions, lines, planes, hyperplanes, point-pairs, circles, spheres, tangent planes, conic sections, and much more. Versors can represent orthogonal transformations in the selected GA including translations, rotations, uniform scaling, affine and projective transformations, conformal transformations, and more. The geometric significance of multivectors is clear.</li>
<li><strong>Sparse Representation</strong>: Unlike matrices, GA&#8217;s multivectors representing significant geometric objects are practically sparse. This leads to the possibility of implementing many compiler optimizations to get the minimum possible sequence of computations required for some geometric algorithm.</li>
<li><strong>Extracting Geometric Information</strong>: The numerical components of many important multivectors are directly related to the geometric generators of the multivector. For example, it&#8217;s straightforward to extract the center and radius information from a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conformal_geometric_algebra">Conformal GA</a> multivector just be reading the coefficients of its basis blades. Much information can be extracted from multivectors using simple standard GA operations with direct and clear geometric meaning.</li>
<li><strong>Geometric Type Safety</strong>: Multivectors representing different geometric concepts usually contain different basis blades with non-zero coefficients. By simple inspection of a multivector, we can immediately understand its meaning and check its semantics. For example, the Conformal GA multivector representing a circle can have a radius with imaginary value. This indicates, for example, that two spheres do not intersect and the resulting multivector is of correct type: an imaginary circle with absolute radius related to the distance between the two spheres.</li>
<li><strong>Domain-Specific Modeling</strong>: Because of these beautiful properties, we can directly represent our high-level domain knowledge (i.e. Geometric Concepts and Algorithms) using GA&#8217;s operations on multivectors. Designing software systems for Geometric Computing can be on the same path that database design and logic circuits design took before.</li>
<li><strong>Communication of Geometric Ideas:</strong> GA&#8217;s symbolic multivector expressions are compact and geometrically significant. Just by knowing the meaning associated with multivectors in some expression we can easily follow, after some general application-independent training, its geometric significance. This feature makes teaching and geometric information exchange using Geometric Algebra a pleasant and mind opening experience.</li>
</ul>
<p>Naturally, we need both matrix and multivector representations. We just need to select the most appropriate one for the problem. We may, for example, select to express our problem using multivectors for teaching purposes, while coding computations for the same problem with matrices at a later stage. The good news here is that we can create <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optimizing_compiler">optimizing compilers</a> that automatically generate matrices from GA operations on multivectors. We need to explore both methods of representation and never walk with the &#8220;hammer of matrices&#8221; as our only symbolic tool for dealing with all problems.</p>
<h3>Geometric Algebra: The Way Ahead</h3>
<blockquote><p>Instead of five hundred thousand average algebra teachers, we need one good algebra teacher. We need that teacher to create software, videotape themselves, answer questions, let your computer or the iPad teach algebra&#8230; The hallmark of any good technology is that it destroys jobs. &#8212; Michael J. Saylor</p></blockquote>
<p>Geometric Algebra is being explored in many applications, for example:</p>
<ul>
<li>Physics</li>
<li>Computer Graphics</li>
<li>Geometric Modeling</li>
<li>Robotics</li>
<li>Geographical Information Science</li>
<li>Electromagnetics</li>
<li>Computer Vision</li>
<li>Neural Computing</li>
<li>Automatic Theorem Proving</li>
<li>Electrical Power Systems</li>
<li>Signal and Image Processing</li>
<li>Graph Theory</li>
<li>Data Visualization</li>
<li>Mechanical Engineering</li>
</ul>
<p>Many opportunities exist for GA-based research and teaching, for example:</p>
<ul>
<li>Very few researchers develop efficient numerical algorithms for GA multivectors. Numerical Linear Algebra on matrices is much developed in comparison. We need to concentrate on this important task for creating efficient numerical algorithms to deal with multivectors.</li>
<li>We need to reformulate and express common geometric modeling tasks using Geometric Algebra. For example, we need to write books on Computer Graphics or Robotics where each equation is expressed using GA multivectors, not matrices.</li>
<li>We need to explore algorithmic and computational aspects of GA-based models. We need to design optimizing compilers that can understand and translate standard GA operations just like current compilers seamlessly understand floating point numbers.</li>
<li>We need to use GA as a primary language for teaching geometric concepts in all sorts of engineering activities. The use of Geometric Algebra in schools is a big step towards the future of GA adoption and development.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="/index.php/2017/01/28/ga-elements/" target="_blank">In the following post</a>, I will talk about the main mathematical elements of Geometric Algebra and how they integrate to create its full power and beauty. This kind of information is a good starting point for anyone new to the subject and in need for a clear roadmap to follow.</p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/done7.png" data-rel="lightbox-7" title=""><img class="alignright wp-image-2293 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/done7-300x32.png" width="300" height="32" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/done7-300x32.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/done7.png 378w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class='endnotes' id='hhendnotes-636'>
<ol>
<li id='en-636-1'>See for example the <a href="http://www.generative-modeling.org/">Generative Modeling Language</a> (GML) by Sven Havemann described in his very interesting <a href="https://publikationsserver.tu-braunschweig.de/receive/dbbs_mods_00000008">Ph.D. dissertation</a>. For a recent survey on this subject see &#8220;A Survey of Algorithmic Shapes&#8221; by Ulrich Krispel et al available <a href="http://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/7/10/12763">here</a> <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-636-1'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-636-2'>For example rotations of vectors in 3D are best done using Quaternions while other affine transformations, especially composite ones, are better done using matrices! <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-636-2'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-636-3'>Jaap Suter&#8217;s &#8220;<a href="http://www.jaapsuter.com/geometric-algebra/">Geometric Algebra Primer</a>&#8221; and Mikael Nilsson&#8217;s &#8220;<a href="http://cid.nada.kth.se/pdf/CID-201.pdf">Geometric Algebra with Conzilla: Building a Conceptual Web of Mathematics</a>&#8221; <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-636-3'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-636-4'>In his 2011 M.Sc. thesis &#8220;VERSOR: Spatial Computing with Conformal Geometric Algebra&#8221; <a href="http://www.wolftype.com/versor/colapinto_masters_final_02.pdf">available here</a>. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-636-4'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-636-5'>See the list of <a href="http://www.netlib.org/utk/people/JackDongarra/la-sw.html">Freely Available Software for Linear Algebra</a> composed by Jack Dongarra and Hatem Ltaief, University of Tennessee <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-636-5'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-636-6'><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Numerical_linear_algebra">Numerical Linear Algebra</a> is the study of algorithms for performing linear algebra computations, most notably matrix operations, on computers. It is often a fundamental part of engineering and computational science problems, such as image and signal processing, telecommunication, computational finance, materials science simulations, structural biology, data mining, bioinformatics, fluid dynamics, and many other areas. Such software relies heavily on the development, analysis, and implementation of state-of-the-art algorithms for solving various numerical linear algebra problems, in large part because of the role of matrices in finite difference and finite element methods. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-636-6'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
</ol>
</div>
<p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=%2Findex.php%2F2017%2F01%2F13%2Fga-computing3%2F&amp;linkname=Geometric%20Algebra%3A%20Ascension%20of%20the%20Mind" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_twitter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/twitter?linkurl=%2Findex.php%2F2017%2F01%2F13%2Fga-computing3%2F&amp;linkname=Geometric%20Algebra%3A%20Ascension%20of%20the%20Mind" title="Twitter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_google_plus" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/google_plus?linkurl=%2Findex.php%2F2017%2F01%2F13%2Fga-computing3%2F&amp;linkname=Geometric%20Algebra%3A%20Ascension%20of%20the%20Mind" title="Google+" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=%2Findex.php%2F2017%2F01%2F13%2Fga-computing3%2F&amp;title=Geometric%20Algebra%3A%20Ascension%20of%20the%20Mind" data-a2a-url="/index.php/2017/01/13/ga-computing3/" data-a2a-title="Geometric Algebra: Ascension of the Mind"></a></p><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2017/01/13/ga-computing3/">Geometric Algebra: Ascension of the Mind</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Functional History of Numbers (2 of 3)</title>
		<link>/index.php/2015/08/07/history-of-numbers2/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2015 14:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ahmad Eid]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[GA History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Numbers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://gacomputing.info/?p=270</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>As long as algebra and geometry have been separated, their progress have been slow and their uses limited; but when these two sciences have been united, they have lent each mutual forces, and have&#46;&#46;&#46;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2015/08/07/history-of-numbers2/">A Functional History of Numbers (2 of 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Old-Geometry.png" data-rel="lightbox-0" title=""><img class=" size-full wp-image-364 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Old-Geometry.png" alt="Old-Geometry" width="968" height="768" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Old-Geometry.png 968w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Old-Geometry-300x238.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Old-Geometry-768x609.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 968px) 100vw, 968px" /></a></p>
<blockquote><p>As long as algebra and geometry have been separated, their progress have been slow and their uses limited; but when these two sciences have been united, they have lent each mutual forces, and have marched together towards perfection. &#8212; Joseph-Louis Lagrange.</p></blockquote>
<p><span class="dropcap">I</span>n <a href="/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/">part one</a> of this functional history of numbers we saw the development of various number systems we are mostly familiar with. In this part, we will see the development of many number systems that are important for our modern scientific needs, geometrically and computationally. The sad fact about these developments is that we are using and teaching less effective number systems today because of a &#8220;series of unfortunate events&#8221; that took place during the grand drama of human development of modern mathematics.</p>
<h3>Missing the Truth in Pursuit of Beauty</h3>
<blockquote><p>Here as he walked by on the 16th of October 1843 Sir William Rowan Hamilton in a flash of genius discovered the fundamental formula for quaternion multiplication <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">i^{2}=j^{2}=k^{2}=ijk=-1</span> &amp; cut it on a stone of this bridge. &#8212; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_quaternions#/media/File:William_Rowan_Hamilton_Plaque_-_geograph.org.uk_-_347941.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-1" title="">Quaternion plaque</a> on Brougham (Broom) Bridge, Dublin.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_330" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/6a0163057a21c8970d017743e0b713970d.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-2" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-330" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/6a0163057a21c8970d017743e0b713970d-300x150.jpg" alt="Avoiding a gimbal lock using quaternions" width="300" height="150" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/6a0163057a21c8970d017743e0b713970d-300x150.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/6a0163057a21c8970d017743e0b713970d.jpg 694w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Avoiding a gimbal lock using quaternions; see <a href="http://around-the-corner.typepad.com/adn/2012/08/avoid-gimbal-lock-for-rotationdirection-maya-manipulators.html">here</a> for the full article</p></div>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Rowan_Hamilton">Sir William Rowan Hamilton</a> a renounced Irish physicist, astronomer, and mathematician had been interested in complex numbers for a long time. Motivated by the beautiful geometric properties of complex numbers, he was obsessed with generalizing complex numbers to 3 dimensional space while keeping the most fascinating property of complex numbers: the unification of points (data) and transformations (processing) in a single algebraic entity while applying the transformations to points using algebraic multiplication and formal summation. Out of this preoccupation Hamilton was to invent the most beautiful algebra of the century: the algebra of quaternions. Hamilton never arrived at his beautiful generalization; it simply does not exist in the way he imagined. A fact about generalizations of abstract concepts is that they&#8217;re not free; with any generalization of a concept we must give up some of its properties. Often we cannot choose and control an arbitrary set of properties to generalize for some concept; this set may be consistent with the original concept but inconsistent with its generalization. Sadly enough, Hamilton and his followers made some big mistakes that almost banished quaternion algebra from practical applications in physics and engineering for a very long time<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-1' id='enref-270-1' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>1</a></sup>. They literally missed the true beauty of quaternions as rotation operators<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-2' id='enref-270-2' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>2</a></sup> in their stubborn pursuit of a specific form of beauty they imagined as pure mathematicians: a method to divide 3D vectors just like complex numbers. The full story of this unfortunate event can be found in Simon L. Altmann intriguing paper &#8220;Hamilton, Rodrigues, and the Quaternion Scandal&#8221;<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-3' id='enref-270-3' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>3</a></sup>.</p>
<p>On the morning of Monday, 16 October 1843 Hamilton, accompanied by Lady Hamilton, was walking along the Royal Canal in Dublin towards the Royal Irish Academy, where Hamilton was to preside at a meeting. As he was walking past Broome Bridge (referred to as Brougham Bridge by Hamilton and called by this name ever since), Hamilton, in a flash of inspiration, realized that three, rather than two, imaginary units were needed in 3D space, with the properties <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">i^{2}=j^{2}=k^{2}=-1,\;ij=-k,\;ji=-k</span> and cyclic permutation. Hamilton carved these formulae on the stone of the bridge; poor Lady Hamilton had to wait. Armed now with four units, Hamilton called the number <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">A=a\,1+A_{x}\,i+A_{y}\,j+A_{z}\,k</span> where the coefficients here are all real, a quaternion. Hamilton made the product <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">ij=-ji</span> non-commutative. Not only was this the first time that a non-commutative product appeared in mathematics, but this was a true stroke of genius which has given us the last possible <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Division_algebra#Associative_division_algebras">associative division algebra</a><sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-4' id='enref-270-4' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>4</a></sup>. As a complex number <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">C=x+iy</span> is the formal sum of a real part <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">x</span> and an imaginary part <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">iy</span>, a quaternion <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">Q_{A}=a\,1+A_{x}\,i+A_{y}\,j+A_{z}\,k</span> can be viewed as a formal sum of the real part <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">a</span> and the &#8220;pure-quaternion&#8221; part <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">A=A_{x}\,i+A_{y}\,j+A_{z}\,k</span>. It follows that the product of two quaternions <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">Q_{A}=a+A</span> and <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">Q_{B}=b+B</span> is given by: <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">Q_{A}Q_{B}=(ab-A\cdot B)+(aB+bA+A\times B)</span> where <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">A\cdot B=A_{x}B_{x}+A_{y}B_{y}+A_{z}B_{z}</span> and <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">A\times B=(A_{y}B_{z}-A_{z}B_{y})\,i+(A_{z}B_{x}-A_{x}B_{z})\,j+(A_{x}B_{y}-A_{y}B_{x})\,k</span></p>
<p>Although Hamilton did not give names or symbols for these operations, it is here that the scalar and vector products of two vectors appear for the first time in history. The big mistake Hamilton made was treating the pure-quaternion part as a vector (actually it&#8217;s a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bivector#Quaternions">bivector</a>); he even named it a vector. He then treated rotations in 3D space using his newly invented algebra but with many internal contradictions stemming from his imagined goal of generalizing complex numbers while preserving all their &#8220;algebraically beautiful properties&#8221;. Two other unfortunate events happened in the drama of quaternions. First, Gauss had actually discovered quaternions but had never bothered to publish, as shown by Gauss&#8217;s notes from 1819, published in 1900; that certainly didn&#8217;t help Hamilton&#8217;s case. Second, a treatment of rotations and quaternions had been going on for some years before 1843, quite independently of Hamilton and taking a diametrically opposed view to his. This treatment was entirely geometrical, and because it tried to do a simple job in a simple way it was clear and precise and it was entirely successful, but it was largely ignored by everyone. It was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olinde_Rodrigues">Olinde Rodrigues</a> in his 1840 paper who provided a construction to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%27s_rotation_theorem">Euler&#8217;s rotation theorem</a> correctly <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%E2%80%93Rodrigues_formula#Connection_with_quaternions">linking quaternions to rotations</a> <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-5' id='enref-270-5' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>5</a></sup>. Hamilton himself geometrically rediscovered the results of the Rodrigues construction but completely ignored its importance; probably blinded by his original goal of &#8220;algebraic beauty&#8221;.</p>
<div id="attachment_351" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/quaternions.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-3" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-351" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/quaternions-300x220.jpg" alt="Irish stamp on the Quaternions," width="300" height="220" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/quaternions-300x220.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/quaternions-768x564.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/quaternions.jpg 994w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Irish stamp on the Quaternions, issued by Ireland on May 4, 1983. (<a href="http://jeff560.tripod.com/images/quaternions.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-4" title="">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>After Hamilton&#8217;s death, his work began to give fruits but not in the direction which he had expected. His ideas of vectors and of their scalar and vector products were much too important so that people began to try and graft a new skin onto them in order to make these concepts usable. Grassmann in Germany and Heaviside in Britain moved some way in this direction, but they were not much more transparent than Hamilton himself. It was left to Willard Gibbs of Yale to produce not only the first coherent picture of vectors and of their operations but also a good and successful working notation; effectively eliminating quaternions, with all their true beauty as rotation operators, from the picture. This hardened the response of Hamilton&#8217;s followers as one of them, Peter Tait, stated:</p>
<blockquote><p>Even Prof. Willard Gibbs must be ranked as one of the retarders of quaternion progress, in virtue of his pamphlet on Vector Analysis, a sort of hermaphrodite monster, compounded of the notations of Hamilton and of Grassmann.</p></blockquote>
<p>This was not the end of the story for quaternions. They would resurface many years later as advantageous rotation operators in 3D space; currently used in robotics, aviation, and computer graphics to name a few applications. Nevertheless, many important lessons can be taught from the story of the last division algebra. The main lesson being: you have to consistently follow the truth and it will lead to more beauty than the one you might imagine.</p>
<h3>Into Hyperspace Without the Womb of Numbers</h3>
<blockquote><p>The Matrix is everywhere. It is all around us. Even now, in this very room. &#8212; Morpheus, The Matrix.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_367" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Matrix.png" data-rel="lightbox-5" title=""><img class="wp-image-367 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Matrix-300x65.png" alt="Matrix" width="300" height="65" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Matrix-300x65.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Matrix.png 576w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">A Matrix is the &#8220;Womb of Numbers&#8221; in which Linear Algebra was born</p></div>
<p>It&#8217;s said that necessity is the mother of invention; sometimes the lack of necessity brutally kills brilliant ideas. Linear algebra is a fascinating subject with applications in almost every field of science and engineering<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-6' id='enref-270-6' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>6</a></sup>. When you search for a definition for the term &#8220;Linear Algebra&#8221; you will find a definition like:</p>
<blockquote><p>Linear Algebra is a branch of mathematics that is concerned with mathematical structures closed under the operations of addition and scalar multiplication and that includes the theory of systems of linear equations, matrices, determinants, vector spaces, and linear transformations. &#8212; Merriam Webster <a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/linear%20algebra">online dictionary.</a></p></blockquote>
<p>When you take a look at some books about the subject you will find two kinds of books. The first kind<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-7' id='enref-270-7' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>7</a></sup> mostly deals with linear equations, coordinate vectors (i.e. tuples of numbers), matrices, and determinants; this may give the wrong impression that linear algebra is nothing more than the study of matrix algebra and coordinate vectors in Euclidean space. The second kind of books<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-8' id='enref-270-8' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>8</a></sup> deals with an abstract concept of vectors and linear transformations defined axiomatically without giving any special importance to coordinates, and applicable to any metric space Euclidean or not. Now matrices are put to perspective as no more than computational and representational tools for the subject, not the subject itself. Historically<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-9' id='enref-270-9' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>9</a></sup> the first use of linear equations of 2 and 3 unknowns date back to ancient Babylonians and Chinese. The modern study of systems of linear equations can be said to have originated with Leibniz, who in 1693 invented the notion of a determinant for this purpose. Following developments took place by Cramer, Euler, Gauss, Laplace, Cauchy, Weierstrass, Kronecker, Cayley, Frobenius, and many others. All such developments were based on applications from diverse fields of mathematics and physics; a sign of the necessity and universality of linear algebra. In 1848, J.J. Sylvester introduced the term “matrix”, the Latin word for womb and a word related to &#8220;mother&#8221;, as a name for an array of numbers. By the year 1880, many of the fundamental results of linear algebra had been established, but they were not considered as parts of a general theory. In particular, the fundamental notion of vector space, within which such a theory would be framed, was absent. Matrices and coordinate vectors, out of necessity, are at the core of the historical development of linear algebra and vector spaces. In our modern computational age, any software library dealing with linear algebra must have matrices and their computational algorithms as the main component. Every engineer in the world must have some idea about the Matrix Laboratory; <a href="https://www.mathworks.com/products/matlab.html">MATLAB</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_356" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/clifford3d.png" data-rel="lightbox-6" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-356" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/clifford3d-300x97.png" alt="Exterior Product" width="300" height="97" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/clifford3d-300x97.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/clifford3d-768x248.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/clifford3d.png 1012w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Grassmann used vectors to define higher-dimensional subspaces algebraically using his exterior product (<a href="https://slehar.wordpress.com/2014/03/18/clifford-algebra-a-visual-introduction/">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>One mathematician took a fundamentally different approach to linear algebra than all others hoping to approach Leibniz&#8217;s dream of a universal algebra that can deal directly and simply with geometric entities<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-10' id='enref-270-10' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>10</a></sup>; he was Hermann Günther Grassmann. Many have written about the extraordinary role of Grassmann&#8217;s work in modern mathematics and physics including Roger Penrose<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-11' id='enref-270-11' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>11</a></sup>, David Hestenes<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-12' id='enref-270-12' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>12</a></sup>, and many others<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-13' id='enref-270-13' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>13</a></sup>. Desmond Fearnley-Sander describes how Grassmann developed linear algebra by himself in <a href="https://www.maa.org/sites/default/files/pdf/upload_library/22/Ford/DesmondFearnleySander.pdf">his paper</a> &#8220;Hermann Grassmann and the Creation of Linear Algebra&#8221;. From the beginning, Grassmann distinguished linear algebra, as a formal theory independent of any interpretation, from its application in geometry. Grassmann described the concept of vector space and developed the theory of linear independence in a way which is astonishingly similar to the presentation one finds in modern linear algebra texts. He defined the concepts of subspace, linear independence, span, dimension, join and meet of subspaces, and projections of elements onto subspaces. He proved the invariance of dimension under change of basis and obtained the formula for change of coordinates under change of basis. He defined elementary transformations of basis and showed that every change of basis is a product of elementaries. His work led Peano in 1888 to put down the formal definitions of linear algebra that was ignored for 30 years until 1920 when Hermann Weyl and others published formal definitions resulting in the widespread of linear algebra ever since. Few have come closer than Hermann Grassmann to creating, single-handedly, a new subject. In addition, the first fundamental investigation in multi-dimensional geometry was provided by Grassmann in 1844, in which affine geometry was developed not only for three-dimensional space but for multi-dimensional space also. That it was Grassmann who succeeded in establishing an articulated theory of multidimensional space seems to be due largely to the fact that Grassmann was not under the influence of other great mathematicians of his time, and to his predilection for philosophical generalizations<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-14' id='enref-270-14' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>14</a></sup>. The following is an extract from the Foreword of &#8220;Die Ausdehnungslehre: Vollständig und in strenger Form bearbeitet&#8221; (The Theory of Extension, Thoroughly and Rigorously Treated) published by Grassmann in 1862:</p>
<blockquote><p>I remain completely confident that the labor I have expended on the science presented here and which has demanded a significant part of my life as well as the most strenuous application of my powers, will not be lost. It is true that I am aware that the form which I have given the science is imperfect and must be imperfect. But I know and feel obliged to state (though I run the risk of seeming arrogant) that even if this work should again remain unused for another seventeen years or even longer, without entering into the actual development of science, still that time will come when it will be brought forth from the dust of oblivion and when ideas now dormant will bring forth fruit. I know that if I also fail to gather around me (as I have until now desired in vain) a circle of scholars, whom I could fructify with these ideas, and whom I could stimulate to develop and enrich them further, yet there will come a time when these ideas, perhaps in a new form, will arise anew and will enter into a living communication with contemporary developments. For truth is eternal and divine and no phase of it &#8230; can pass without a trace; it remains in existence even if the cloth in which weak mortals dress it disintegrates into dust.</p></blockquote>
<p>Grassmann expected his ideas would be revived even if unused for 17 years or longer; it actually took a hundred years. At that time in the 19th century, Grassmann&#8217;s ideas (especially in geometry) were revolutionary; they were too advanced for the necessities of his age. Ironically, Grassmann was renowned in his day as a linguist but as a mathematician, he had poor notational skills. His ideas were great but his symbolic expression of them was awkward. Few mathematicians of his age acknowledged his brilliance. One of them was the English mathematician and philosopher William Kingdon Clifford. Clifford was the one who would give new form and meaning to Grassmann&#8217;s ideas.</p>
<h3>Lost and Found: Geometric Algebra</h3>
<blockquote><p>The further a mathematical theory is developed, the more harmoniously and uniformly does its construction proceed, and unsuspected relations are disclosed between hitherto separated branches of the science. &#8212; David Hilbert.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_391" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Spinor_on_the_circle.pdf.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-7" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-391" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Spinor_on_the_circle.pdf-300x228.jpg" alt="When the vector is rotated along the Möbius strip it reverses direction after an odd number of full rotations; it's a spinor." width="300" height="228" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Spinor_on_the_circle.pdf-300x228.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Spinor_on_the_circle.pdf-768x585.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Spinor_on_the_circle.pdf.jpg 787w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">When the vector is rotated along the Möbius strip it reverses direction after an odd number of full rotations; it&#8217;s a spinor.</p></div>
<p>Grassmann&#8217;s vectors and subspaces were not numbers in a way complex numbers and quaternions are. In <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exterior_algebra">Grassmann algebra</a>, a finite set of n vectors, representing 1-dimensional subspaces analogous to lines passing through the origin of a coordinate system of the space, are combined using his exterior product to algebraically form entities representing all other subspaces of dimension 2 to n. Grassmann had no interest, however, in representing transformations that &#8220;rotate&#8221; a subspace into another of the same dimension; something all physical and engineering models require to stand and function. Hamilton had the correct algebra for rotating vectors in 3-dimensional space but no generalization to n-dimensional space was present. While Hamilton lost his way insisting on treating rotations in 3D with the algebra of quaternions using direct multiplications, the brilliant but short-lived English mathematician William Kingdon Clifford took the correct path of generalizing rotations to the n-dimensional spaces of Grassmann<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-15' id='enref-270-15' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>15</a></sup>; the resulting beautiful mathematical abstraction was called <a href="https://slehar.wordpress.com/2014/03/18/clifford-algebra-a-visual-introduction/">Clifford Algebra</a>. Clifford successfully unified and generalized Hamilton&#8217;s quaternions and Grassmann&#8217;s vector spaces in a uniform manner that affected physics and science ever since. His motivation was to create an algebra that can act on strange but common objects in geometry and physics called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spinor">spinors</a>. A spinor is an abstraction of an object that reverses its direction when rotated by an odd number of full cycles in space; contrary to our common intuition about physical 3D objects. Clifford also wrote his report at Cambridge &#8220;On the Space-Theory of Matter&#8221;, published in 1876, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Kingdon_Clifford#Premonition_of_relativity">anticipating Albert Einstein’s general relativity</a> by 40 years. Clifford&#8217;s contemporaries considered him acute and original, witty and warm. Felix Klein wrote, regarding Clifford,</p>
<blockquote><p>I recall him with particular pleasure, as a man who understood me thoroughly from the first and soon extended my research.</p></blockquote>
<p>Clifford was also working late into the night, he collapsed twice in two years from overworking, which may have led to his death at a young age; another unfortunate event for the development of his geometric numbers. Although Clifford recognized his algebra&#8217;s unique signiﬁcance as a representation of geometric concepts as conceived by Grassmann, mathematicians abstracted Clifford algebra from its geometric origins after his death and, for the better part of a century, it languished as a minor sub-discipline of mathematics; one more algebra among so many others<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-16' id='enref-270-16' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>16</a></sup>.</p>
<div id="attachment_433" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-hestenes-dev.png" data-rel="lightbox-8" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-433" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-hestenes-dev-300x184.png" alt="ga-hestenes-dev" width="300" height="184" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-hestenes-dev-300x184.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-hestenes-dev-768x471.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-hestenes-dev.png 844w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Revival and Development of GA starting at David Hestenes research efforts</p></div>
<p>In 1966 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Hestenes">David Orlin Hestenes</a> published his book &#8220;Space-Time Algebra&#8221;, motivated by a set of lecture notes by Marcel Riesz later published in 1993; launching him along three main lines of research:</p>
<ol>
<li>A straightforward reformulation of classical physics in terms of Clifford&#8217;s geometric algebra producing the first comprehensive coordinate-free treatment of Newtonian mechanics,  including rotational dynamics as explained in his book &#8220;New Foundations for Classical Mechanics&#8221;, in addition to a similar reformulation of classical electrodynamics.</li>
<li>Reformulating the Dirac equation in terms of Geometric Algebra. This revealed a hidden geometric structure in quantum mechanics, including a  hitherto unrecognized geometric interpretation for the unit imaginary relating it unequivocally to electron spin.</li>
<li>To produce a self-contained system of mathematical tools sufficient for addressing any problem in physics without resorting to alternative mathematical formalisms; as explained in his book &#8220;Clifford Algebra to Geometric Calculus, A Unified Language for Mathematics and Physics&#8221;.</li>
</ol>
<p>Hestenes received <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Hestenes#Awards_and_fellowships">several awards</a> related to his efforts in teaching physics using GA. As he describes his work in reviving Clifford and Grassmann&#8217;s work:</p>
<blockquote><p>I was consciously concerned with questions relating the structure of these mathematical systems to the structure of the physical world. One day Riesz’s notes appeared on the new-book shelf of the UCLA library. The impact on me was immediate and striking! By the time I was half way through the first chapter I was convinced that Clifford algebra was the key to unifying mathematical physics. During the next few years I worked out the framework for a fully geometric unification. The result was published in my book Space Time Algebra (1966). Fortunately, my book was widely distributed, and it helped me establish many fruitful contacts throughout the world in subsequent years. However, I believe its impact would have dissipated had I not followed it up with years of further research, lectures and publications. Also, I believe that the significance of Riesz’s notes would have remained unrecognized without the citation in my book, which eventually led to publication (in 1993). Though the book launched me on a program to unify mathematical physics, I refrained from proclaiming the product as a universal Geometric Algebra and Calculus until subsequent research convinced me that was fully justified. I was well aware that its roots were in the work of Grassmann, but it was not until the English translations of the Ausdehnungslehre by Lloyd Kannenberg that I realized how deep those roots were.</p></blockquote>
<p>Later on, Hestenes ideas in physics found their way into many computer science and engineering applications over the last 15 years. We are still at the beginning of the road to exploring this powerful abstract number system for our ever growing geometric dependent applications.</p>
<h3>GA&#8217;s Multivectors: The Spacious Number System</h3>
<blockquote><p>Physics is mathematical not because we know so much about the physical world, but because we know so little; it is only its mathematical properties that we can discover. &#8212; Bertrand Russell.</p></blockquote>
<p>A geometric algebra is constructed from a set of <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">n</span> basis vectors on a scalar field (for example real or complex numbers) and a symmetric bilinear form defining the metric (i.e. the scalar-valued inner product of pairs of basis vectors). Using Clifford&#8217;s geometric product a set of <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">2^{n}</span> basis blades, representing main subspaces of the algebra of dimensions 0 to <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">n</span>, are constructed. Multivectors, our geometric numbers, are linear combinations of the basis blades. All GA algebraic operations and beauty follow from this simple construction.</p>
<div id="attachment_426" style="width: 964px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-basis-blades.png" data-rel="lightbox-9" title=""><img class="size-full wp-image-426" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-basis-blades.png" alt="ga-basis-blades" width="954" height="294" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-basis-blades.png 954w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-basis-blades-300x92.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-basis-blades-768x237.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 954px) 100vw, 954px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">GA basis blades are constructed from basis vectors using the outer product (<a href="http://www2.ic.uff.br/~laffernandes/projects/ga/2009_SIBGRAPI_tutorial/fernandes_oliveia_SIBGRAPI_2009_tutorial_slides.pdf">Source</a>)</p></div>
<div id="attachment_417" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-R3-blades.png" data-rel="lightbox-10" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-417" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-R3-blades-300x274.png" alt="ga-R3-blades" width="300" height="274" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-R3-blades-300x274.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-R3-blades.png 406w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The 3D Euclidean GA has 8 basis blades constructed from 3 basis vectors (<a href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.158.4974&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>I will not go into the mathematical and geometric properties of GA in this post, after all, the whole site is dedicated to exploring GA, but I will mention some of its general characteristic strengths as an algebraic language for geometry compared to traditional matrix-based linear algebra for geometric modeling<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-17' id='enref-270-17' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>17</a></sup>:</p>
<p>1. GA can be used to model many geometries including non-Euclidean ones. The same algebraic structure can have many geometric modeling interpretations<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-18' id='enref-270-18' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>18</a></sup>.</p>
<div id="attachment_419" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-spaces.png" data-rel="lightbox-11" title=""><img class="wp-image-419 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-spaces-300x227.png" alt="ga-spaces" width="300" height="227" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-spaces-300x227.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-spaces.png 474w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">GA can be used to study non-Euclidean Geometries (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1101.4542v3.pdf">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>2. Many familiar algebraic entities can be considered isomorphic to special cases of multivectors. These include real numbers, complex numbers, quaternions, and vectors of many types (position, direction, and normal vectors), Many types of matrices, typically used as linear transforms, can be replaced by GA multivectors including orthogonal matrices, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pauli_matrices">Pauli matrices</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homogeneous_coordinates">homogeneous transform matrices</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_411" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-rotation.png" data-rel="lightbox-12" title=""><img class="wp-image-411 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-rotation-300x236.png" alt="ga-3d-rotation" width="300" height="236" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-rotation-300x236.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-rotation.png 560w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Quaternions as GA versors (<a href="http://geometricalgebra.net/figures.html">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>3. Grassmann&#8217;s outer product can be used inside GA to construct algebraic entities called blades, one type of multivectors, that represent subspaces of the base vector space. Depending on the selected geometric model for the vectors, blades will be a systematic representation of geometric primitives inside the selected geometry.</p>
<div id="attachment_423" style="width: 271px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-blades-geometry.png" data-rel="lightbox-13" title=""><img class="wp-image-423 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-blades-geometry-261x300.png" alt="ga-blades-geometry" width="261" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-blades-geometry-261x300.png 261w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-blades-geometry.png 579w" sizes="(max-width: 261px) 100vw, 261px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The same GA blade (subspace) can have several geometric interpretations (<a href="http://www2.ic.uff.br/~laffernandes/projects/ga/2009_SIBGRAPI_tutorial/fernandes_oliveia_SIBGRAPI_2009_tutorial_slides.pdf">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>4. Linear transformations on the base vector space can be easily extended and directly applied to blades (subspaces) using what is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outermorphism">outermorphisms</a>. Now we can algebraically manipulate the geometric primitives of our selected geometry by linear transformations without the use of matrices if we want.</p>
<p>5. Orthogonal transformations (linear transformations consisting of a series of reflections on hyperplanes) are very important for many geometric applications. GA can efficiently represent and apply such transformations using a special kind of multivectors called a versor. This is a very good alternative for orthogonal matrices both theoretically and computationally in many situations.</p>
<div id="attachment_410" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-reflection.png" data-rel="lightbox-14" title=""><img class="wp-image-410 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-reflection-300x226.png" alt="ga-3d-reflection" width="300" height="226" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-reflection-300x226.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-reflection.png 530w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">In GA, versors come from using vectors as reflection operators; all orthogonal transformations are series of reflections (<a href="http://geometricalgebra.net/figures.html">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>6. Verosrs can be applied to geometric constructions in a &#8220;covariant&#8221; manner. In traditional matrix algebra, we need to analyze a subspace, representing some geometric entity, to its vector components before applying the orthogonal transform then reconstruct the transformed subspace\entity from the transformed vectors. In GA we can directly apply orthogonal transforms to geometric entities using versors and blades with no need for any extra overhead.</p>
<p>7. In GA many blades can act as versors, leading to the use of geometric entities as orthogonal transformations. One can, say, rotate a plane and reflect a circle on the rotated plane using the same multivectors with no conversion to any other algebraic representations. This is a very different concept, and indeed a very powerful one, compared to the traditional matrix algebra approach.</p>
<div id="attachment_414" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops.png" data-rel="lightbox-15" title=""><img class="wp-image-414 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops-300x141.png" alt="ga-blades" width="300" height="141" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops-300x141.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops-768x362.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops-1024x482.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops-520x245.png 520w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops-720x340.png 720w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops.png 1153w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Geometric entities expressed as GA blades can be used to covariantly transform other geometric entities (<a href="https://staff.fnwi.uva.nl/t.h.koornwinder/specialdays/veldenwegen/Dorst.pdf">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>8. In some cases, GA can be used to find closed form expressions for geometric interpolations and perturbations of non-trivial kinds. This would very much help in developing algorithms for important geometric models.</p>
<div id="attachment_429" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/isea_img2_01_flat2.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-16" title=""><img class="wp-image-429 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/isea_img2_01_flat2-300x146.jpg" alt="isea_img2_01_flat2" width="300" height="146" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/isea_img2_01_flat2-300x146.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/isea_img2_01_flat2-768x373.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/isea_img2_01_flat2-1024x497.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">GA interpolations of motion using versors (<a href="http://isea2011.sabanciuniv.edu/paper/versor-proposal-system-organic-constructivism">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>9. GA can work well with traditional matrix-based modeling techniques. One can use a linear algebra software library and interface it with a GA model easily; no need to model everything into GA from scratch.</p>
<p>10. All the above and other GA characteristics can make life much easier for people creating computational code for geometric modeling applications. GA is consistent and systematic algebraically with direct geometric interpretation. You just need to select your model and do the math; programming is straight forward. For example take a look at <a href="https://vimeo.com/wolftype">these videos</a> created using the <a href="http://versor.mat.ucsb.edu/">Versor GA library</a>.</p>
<p>All these unique characteristics will certainly have deep influence, over the long run, on our understanding and development of geometric models in science and engineering. Many problems related to practical use and teaching of GA remain to be solved, but the concept had already been proven and the way is now much more clear for many researchers. In our next and final part of this functional history of numbers we will investigate another kind of numbers; the numbers we use in computing everything.</p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/done3.png" data-rel="lightbox-17" title=""><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-456" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/done3.png" alt="done3" width="300" height="40" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<hr />
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class='endnotes' id='hhendnotes-270'>
<ol>
<li id='en-270-1'>During my research for this post I found that the 1873 edition of James Clerk Maxwell&#8217;s &#8220;A Treatise on Electricity and Magnetism&#8221; contains 20 Quaternion Equations that later were rewritten by Oliver Heaviside, et al.. See <a href="http://www.rexresearch.com/maxwell.htm">here</a> and <a href="http://visualphysics.org/forum/topics/200-missing-quaternion-equations-maxwells-treatis-electromagnetism-edition-1">here</a> for some details <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-1'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-2'>Simon L. Altmann, &#8220;Rotations, Quaternions, and Double Groups&#8221;. Oxford University Press 1986 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-2'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-3'>Simon L. Altmann, &#8220;Hamilton, Rodrigues, and the Quaternion Scandal&#8221;. Mathematics Magazine 62 (5): 306, December 1989. JSTOR 2689481. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-3'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-4'>As later proven by Frobenius that the only possible associative division algebras are the real, complex, and quaternion algebras <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-4'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-5'>N. J. Wildberger has a series of video lectures on famous math problems, four of which introduce the rotation problem and Hamilton&#8217;s discovery of quaternions; the series can be found <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uRKZnFAR7yw&amp;list=PLIljB45xT85Bfc-S4WHvTIM7E-ir3nAOf&amp;index=12" data-rel="lightbox-video-0">here</a>. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-5'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-6'>See this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8CX-Q0gtSp8" data-rel="lightbox-video-1">intriguing video</a> for a glimpse <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-6'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-7'>For example David Poole, &#8220;Linear Algebra, a Modern Introduction, 4th Edition&#8221;. Cengage Learning 2015 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-7'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-8'>For example Sheldon Axler, &#8220;Linear Algebra Done Right, Third Edition&#8221;. Springer 2015 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-8'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-9'>Israel Kleiner, &#8220;A History of Abstract Algebra&#8221;. Birkhauser Boston 2007 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-9'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-10'>Gottfried Leibniz, letter to Christian Huygens (8 September 1679) &#8220;I believe that, so far as geometry is concerned, we need still another analysis which is distinctly geometrical or linear and which will express situation directly as algebra expresses magnitude directly.&#8221;, in Gottfried Leibniz &#8220;Philosophical Papers and Letters, 2nd Edition&#8221;. Springer 1976 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-10'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-11'>Roger Penrose, &#8220;The Road to Reality: A Complete Guide to the Laws of the Universe&#8221;. Vintage 2007 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-11'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-12'>Gert Schubring (Editor), &#8220;Hermann Günther Graßmann (1809–1877): Visionary Mathematician, Scientist and Neohumanist Scholar, Papers from a Sesquicentennial Conference&#8221;. Springer Netherlands 1996 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-12'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-13'>Hans-Joachim Petsche, Albert C. Lewis, Jörg Liesen, Steve Russ (Editors), &#8220;From Past to Future: Graßmann&#8217;s Work in Context, Graßmann Bicentennial Conference, September 2009&#8221;. Springer Basel 2011 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-13'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-14'>A.N. Kolmogorov and A.P. Yushkevich (Editors), &#8220;Mathematics of the 19th Century, Mathematical Logic Algebra Number Theory Probability Theory&#8221;. Birkhäuser Basel 2001 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-14'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-15'>For a good explanation of the differences between Grassmann algebra and Clifford algebra see Roger Penrose&#8217;s book &#8220;The Road To Reality&#8221; <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-15'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-16'>David Hestenes, &#8220;Oersted Medal Lecture 2002: Reforming the Mathematical Language of Physics&#8221;. American Journal of Physics 71, 104 (2003) <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-16'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-17'>For more very interesting details see Leo Dorst, Daniel Fontijne, and Stephen Mann, &#8220;Geometric Algebra for Computer Science (Revised Edition): An Object-Oriented Approach to Geometry&#8221;. Morgan Kaufmann 2009 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-17'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-18'>G. Sommer (Editor), &#8220;Geometric Computing with Clifford Algebra&#8221;. Springer-Verlag Heidelberg 2000 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-18'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
</ol>
</div>
<p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=%2Findex.php%2F2015%2F08%2F07%2Fhistory-of-numbers2%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Functional%20History%20of%20Numbers%20%282%20of%203%29" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_twitter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/twitter?linkurl=%2Findex.php%2F2015%2F08%2F07%2Fhistory-of-numbers2%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Functional%20History%20of%20Numbers%20%282%20of%203%29" title="Twitter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_google_plus" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/google_plus?linkurl=%2Findex.php%2F2015%2F08%2F07%2Fhistory-of-numbers2%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Functional%20History%20of%20Numbers%20%282%20of%203%29" title="Google+" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=%2Findex.php%2F2015%2F08%2F07%2Fhistory-of-numbers2%2F&amp;title=A%20Functional%20History%20of%20Numbers%20%282%20of%203%29" data-a2a-url="/index.php/2015/08/07/history-of-numbers2/" data-a2a-title="A Functional History of Numbers (2 of 3)"></a></p><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2015/08/07/history-of-numbers2/">A Functional History of Numbers (2 of 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Functional History of Numbers (1 of 3)</title>
		<link>/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/</link>
		<comments>/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2015 13:00:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ahmad Eid]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[GA History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Numbers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://gacomputing.info/?p=251</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>The interest which pupils take in their studies may be greatly increased if the solution of problems and the cold logic of geometrical demonstrations are interspersed with historical remarks and anecdotes. &#8212; Florian Cajori,&#46;&#46;&#46;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/">A Functional History of Numbers (1 of 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/numbers.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-0" title=""><img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-286" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/numbers-1024x768.jpg" alt="Black and white numbers background" width="720" height="540" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/numbers-1024x768.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/numbers-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/numbers-768x576.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/numbers.jpg 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 720px) 100vw, 720px" /></a></p>
<blockquote><p>The interest which pupils take in their studies may be greatly increased if the solution of problems and the cold logic of geometrical demonstrations are interspersed with historical remarks and anecdotes. &#8212; Florian Cajori, A History of Mathematics.</p></blockquote>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>en years ago a dear friend of mine gave me a copy of Earl W. Swokowski&#8217;s 6th edition of Calculus (now out of print). The book contains several short historical sketches called &#8220;Mathematicians and Their Times&#8221; attempting to show a more human side of mathematics in a hope that these brief introductions will whet the appetites of readers to explore the fascinating history of mathematics on their own. I really enjoyed reading about:</p>
<ul>
<li>The life, and horrible death, of the first (known) woman mathematician Hypatia,</li>
<li>The dreams of René Descartes who created Analytic Geometry to join algebra and geometry,</li>
<li>The shyness of the great mathematician Pierre de Fermat who didn&#8217;t have a degree in mathematics.</li>
<li>The bitter <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leibniz%E2%80%93Newton_calculus_controversy">controversy</a> that arose concerning the discovery of calculus between Newton and Leibniz that drove a wedge between British and Continental intellectual communities, hampering the development of calculus.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Bernoulli#Private_life">disturbing jealousy</a> in the Bernoulli family of mathematicians leading to name calling between brothers and Johann Bernoulli expelling his own son from home after awarded the French Academy of Sciences prize.</li>
<li>The phenomenal memory of Leonhard Euler and ability to concentrate on difficult problems while surrounded by 13 playing children and being blind for 17 years! He introduced or established the use of many common mathematical notations and discovered the &#8220;mystical formula&#8221; <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">e^{\pi i}+1=0</span> linking the five most significant numbers in mathematics.</li>
</ul>
<p>Since then I use the same technique in lectures I give to my students to catch their attention; that is one goal of this post. However, another important goal is to link Geometric Algebra to mathematics on the fundamental level of numbers. Here I briefly describe the history of numbers with emphasis on their functional role in mathematics, science, and engineering to put the computational role GA can play into perspective.</p>
<h3>How to Count Sheep and Build Pyramids</h3>
<blockquote><p>It is India that gave us the ingenious method of expressing all numbers by means of ten symbols, each symbol receiving a value of position as well as an absolute value; a profound and important idea which appears so simple to us now that we ignore its true merit. &#8212; Pierre Simon Marquis de Laplace.</p></blockquote>
<p>The first functional use of numbers in human history was, naturally, to count and compare items for trading and regularizing society. Creating the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seven_Wonders_of_the_Ancient_World">wonders of the ancient world</a> and accumulating impressively accurate calendars and <a href="http://www.starteachastronomy.com/archaeoastronomy.html">astronomical observations</a> certainly required advanced numerical skills. Some advanced societies in ancient times (the ancient Egyptians, Babylonians, Chinese, and Indians for example) required a symbolic form of numbers that can represent quantities efficiently while doing arithmetic<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-1' id='enref-251-1' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>1</a></sup>.</p>
<div id="attachment_296" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Platonic-Solids1.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-1" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-296" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Platonic-Solids1-300x236.jpg" alt="Platonic Solids" width="300" height="236" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Platonic-Solids1-300x236.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Platonic-Solids1-768x603.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Platonic-Solids1-1024x804.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Platonic-Solids1.jpg 1179w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Greeks associated geometry with philosophy (<a href="http://joedubs.com/platonic-solids/">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>Greek mathematics, on the other hand, was founded on geometrical ideas, like lengths, areas, and volumes, that left no room for negative numbers, for example. They didn&#8217;t use anything similar to real numbers in proofs and logical arguments because they represented magnitudes by lines or areas constructed geometrically. They practically avoided irrationals using this technique<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-2' id='enref-251-2' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>2</a></sup>. Irrational numbers appear in even the simplest sorts of measurements, as the Pythagoreans discovered when they found that the diagonal of certain geometric figures may be incommensurable with their sides. This discovery upset the conventional mathematical wisdom of the time, and the penalty was death for those who revealed the secret<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-3' id='enref-251-3' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>3</a></sup>. The Greek were horrified by the implications of this discovery that they took a step backward. Where the Pythagoreans claimed the unity of numbers and geometric extension, the later Greeks denied it. Hence, one could not associate numbers with lengths. This caused an unfortunate split between the disciplines of geometry, which dealt with points and lines (extension), and algebra, which dealt with numbers<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-4' id='enref-251-4' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>4</a></sup>.</p>
<p>The most important advancements of these ancient times, negative numbers, the decimal place-value system, and the use of zero, were made by the Indian mathematicians<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-5' id='enref-251-5' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>5</a></sup> and then translated, used, and spread to renaissance Europe 1000 years later by the Islamic civilization.  A surprising fact I came across is that negative numbers did not begin to appear in Europe until the 15th century when scholars began to study and translate the ancient texts that had been recovered from Islamic and Byzantine sources<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-6' id='enref-251-6' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>6</a></sup>. European mathematicians resisted the concept of negative numbers until the 17th century and some referred to them as “absurd quantities&#8221; <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-7' id='enref-251-7' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>7</a></sup>.</p>
<p>The main point that remains constant when reading the history of numbers is: a number system is advanced by the needs of civilization and, at the same time, civilization is advanced by the development of its number system. The concept of a number is practically the fundamental abstraction of all mathematics and science.</p>
<h3>The Rational Laws of Inheritance</h3>
<blockquote><p>The imam and emir of the believers, al-Ma&#8217;mun, encouraged me to write a concise work on the calculations al-jabr (Calculation by Completion) and al-muqabala (Balancing), confined to a pleasant and interesting art of calculation, which people constantly have need of for their inheritances, their wills, their judgements and their transactions, and in all the things they have to do together, notably, the measurement of land, the digging of canals, geometry and other things of that kind. &#8212; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muḥammad_ibn_Mūsā_al-Khwārizmī">Al-Khwarizmi</a>, The Compendious Book on Calculation by Completion and Balancing <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-8' id='enref-251-8' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>8</a></sup>.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_294" style="width: 222px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/d.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-2" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-294" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/d-212x300.jpg" alt="Islamic Inheritance Rules" width="212" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/d-212x300.jpg 212w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/d-768x1086.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/d-724x1024.jpg 724w" sizes="(max-width: 212px) 100vw, 212px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">One simplified version of Islamic inheritance rules</p></div>
<p>The next important function for numbers in human history was to compare ratios of units. The use of ratios motivated the invention of algebra in the form of equations in one unknown that when found results in a rational number. Historically, the terms <strong>algebra</strong> and <strong>algorithm</strong> originate from the same source: the book &#8220;Kitab al muhtasar fi hisab al-gabr w&#8217;al-muqabalah&#8221; by the Muslim scientist Abu Ja&#8217;far Mohammed ibn Musa al-Khorezmi compiled at the academy of science in Bagdad in the ninth century &#8211; uses &#8220;al-gabr&#8221; and &#8220;muqabalah&#8221; to describe symbolic transformations and term reductions respectively, which are performed to solve algebraic equations<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-9' id='enref-251-9' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>9</a></sup>. Algorithmic manipulation of symbolic algebraic expressions remained to be the major task of algebra about until the end of the nineteenth century. At the beginning of the twentieth century, this method was amended and shadowed by developments in abstract algebra. There, the main interest is focused on formal investigations of algebraic structures derived from axioms. This structural algebraic method has taken over considerable parts of mathematics nowadays<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-10' id='enref-251-10' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>10</a></sup>.</p>
<p>As in the case of the decimal system, zero and other ancient advancements, the Islamic civilization translated, developed, and applied these mathematical concepts for hundreds of years until modern European civilization took place. The foundation and soul of the Islamic civilization is the Revelation in its two forms: Qur&#8217;an and Sunnah. The rules for inheritance<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-11' id='enref-251-11' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>11</a></sup> are accurately specified in the revelation but require some degree of mathematical sophistication to be computed correctly. Such rules were the main reason behind the widespread use of rational numbers and the development of algebra back then<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-12' id='enref-251-12' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>12</a></sup>. As stated in one article<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-13' id='enref-251-13' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>13</a></sup>:</p>
<blockquote><p>Perhaps one of the most significant advances made by Arabic mathematics<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-14' id='enref-251-14' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>14</a></sup> began at this time with the work of al-Khwarizmi, namely the beginnings of algebra. It is important to understand just how significant this new idea was. It was a revolutionary move away from the Greek concept of mathematics which was essentially geometry. Algebra was a unifying theory which allowed rational numbers, irrational numbers, geometrical magnitudes, etc., to all be treated as &#8220;algebraic objects&#8221;. It gave mathematics a whole new development path so much broader in concept to that which had existed before, and provided a vehicle for future development of the subject. Another important aspect of the introduction of algebraic ideas was that it allowed mathematics to be applied to itself in a way which had not happened before.</p></blockquote>
<p>Although Arab mathematicians are most well known for their work on algebra, number theory, and number systems, they also made considerable contributions to geometry, trigonometry, and mathematical astronomy<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-15' id='enref-251-15' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>15</a></sup>. The advancement of the number concept, and mathematics in general, by the Islamic civilization enabled remarkable achievements in all aspects of science and technology and directly affected all the following development of mathematics in the last 400 years<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-16' id='enref-251-16' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>16</a></sup> <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-17' id='enref-251-17' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>17</a></sup>. A more fundamental influence of the Islamic civilization on the scientific knowledge of the human race is clearly stated by Robert Briffault in his 1919 book “The Making of Humanity” (publicly available for <a href="https://archive.org/details/makingofhumanity00brifrich">download here</a>):</p>
<blockquote><p>The debt of our science to that of the Arabs does not consist in startling discoveries or revolutionary theories; science owes a great deal more to Arab culture, it owes its existence. The ancient world was, as we saw, pre-scientific. The astronomy and mathematics of the Greeks were a foreign importation never thoroughly acclimatized in Greek culture. The Greeks systematized, generalized and theorized, but the patient ways of investigation, the accumulation of positive knowledge, the minute methods of science, detailed and prolonged observation, experimental inquiry, were altogether alien to the Greek temperament. Only in Hellenistic Alexandria was any, approach to scientific work conducted in the ancient classical world. What we call science arose in Europe as a result of a new spirit of inquiry, of new methods of investigation, of the method of experiment, observation, measurement, of the development of mathematics in a form unknown to the Greeks. That spirit and those methods were introduced into the European world by the Arabs.</p></blockquote>
<h3>Caught in the Field</h3>
<blockquote><p>Mathematics is the queen of the sciences and number theory is the queen of mathematics. She often condescends to render service to astronomy and other natural sciences, but in all relations she is entitled to the first rank. &#8212; Carl Friedrich Gauss.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_292" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/dscn7165.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-3" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-292" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/dscn7165-300x225.jpg" alt="The fractals of nature are periodic discrete patterns " width="300" height="225" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/dscn7165-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/dscn7165-768x575.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/dscn7165-1024x767.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/dscn7165.jpg 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The fractals of nature are periodic discrete patterns</p></div>
<p>Any serious study of the universe reveals a fascinating fact: periodic patterns of discrete nature are <a href="http://fractalfoundation.org/category/natural-fractals/">everywhere</a>. Number theory<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-18' id='enref-251-18' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>18</a></sup> has captured the attention of the best mathematical minds of history for centuries. The research done in this area by great mathematicians like Euler, Gauss, and Riemann, has shown that it is not only beautiful and fascinating, but intimately connected with many other mathematical subjects like analysis, algebraic geometry, and topology. Many concepts in group theory and abstract algebra are in fact generalizations of the properties of integers that have originated from the work of 18th and 19th-century mathematicians in number theory<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-19' id='enref-251-19' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>19</a></sup>. Division of integers (resulting in rational numbers) and properties of prime numbers can be studied using the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modular_arithmetic">modulus</a> operation. When you are doing a modulus operation (Mod n), you are basically dealing with a periodic function that goes from 0 to n-1 and then repeats itself all over again. That gave rise to one important abstraction in mathematics: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finite_field#Applications">The Finite Field</a>. In this way, number theory helps us define periodic properties of systems that are concerned with whole or rational numbers. This is directly related to modern applications in cryptography<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-20' id='enref-251-20' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>20</a></sup>, error correcting codes<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-21' id='enref-251-21' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>21</a></sup>, and simulation<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-22' id='enref-251-22' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>22</a></sup>.</p>
<div id="attachment_582" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Fractal_pyramid.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-4" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-582" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Fractal_pyramid-300x261.jpg" alt="Fractal_pyramid" width="300" height="261" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Fractal_pyramid-300x261.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Fractal_pyramid.jpg 621w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">A relatively recent approach to understanding the nature of fundamental physics, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P-adic_quantum_mechanics">p-adic quantum mechanics</a>, involves the application of p-adic analysis to quantum mechanics.</p></div>
<p>One of the overriding problems in contemporary computing is the accumulation of rounding errors to such a degree as to make the final result all but useless. The currently dominant computational number system in is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IEEE_floating_point">IEEE Standard for Floating-Point Arithmetic;</a> a very error prone system as we will see in <a href="/index.php/2015/08/14/history-of-numbers3/">part 3</a> of this functional history of numbers. Using finite fields and number theory we can arrive at clever ways for performing fast, error-free digital computations based on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farey_sequence">Farey fractions</a> and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_remainder_theorem">Chinese remainder theorem</a><sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-23' id='enref-251-23' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>23</a></sup>. Another approach is by using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P-adic_number">p-adic Arithmetic</a>, a counter-intuitive arithmetic system<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-24' id='enref-251-24' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>24</a></sup>, as a base for fast error-free computations as a possible alternative for the floating-point numbers<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-25' id='enref-251-25' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>25</a></sup>.</p>
<p>The fact that number theory has few direct applications in engineering is unfortunate but understandable. Number theory is indeed like a queen that seldom interact with the commoners directly, nevertheless influences the whole kingdom by its rulings.</p>
<h3>Continuum: Imagining The Real Numbers</h3>
<blockquote><p>The idea of the continuum seems simple to us. We have somehow lost sight of the difficulties it implies…We are told such a number as the square root of 2 worried Pythagoras and his school almost to exhaustion. Being used to such queer numbers from early childhood, we must be careful not to form a low idea of the mathematical intuition of these ancient sages; their worry was highly credible. &#8212; Erwin Schrödinger.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_290" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/slow_motion_photo_stills-1680x1050.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-5" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-290" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/slow_motion_photo_stills-1680x1050-300x188.jpg" alt="the apparent continuity of creation" width="300" height="188" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/slow_motion_photo_stills-1680x1050-300x188.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/slow_motion_photo_stills-1680x1050-768x480.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/slow_motion_photo_stills-1680x1050-1024x640.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">We use Real numbers to model the apparent continuity of creation</p></div>
<p>The set of real numbers rests by all means at the foundation of modern mathematical activity, theoretical and applied. In modern days the word &#8220;number&#8221; is almost equivalent in our minds to &#8220;real number&#8221;. The main function of real numbers is to model the concepts like &#8220;continuum&#8221; and &#8220;continuous motion&#8221; that have always been present in the minds of all mathematicians and scientists, ancient and modern.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m no mathematician, but as an engineer, I&#8217;ve always struggled with irrational and transcendental real numbers. These numbers are &#8220;results of infinite processes&#8221; that can only be expressed symbolically like <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\pi</span>, e, and <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\sqrt{2}</span>, or represented approximately as decimals with finite precision; something is definitely bothering about this class of elusive numbers<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-26' id='enref-251-26' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>26</a></sup>. During high school, to my surprise, I read about paradoxes resulting from the concept of &#8220;continuous real number line&#8221; and &#8220;uncountable infinite sets&#8221; like the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banach%E2%80%93Tarski_paradox">Banach–Tarski paradox</a>. That led me later to some articles questioning the &#8220;<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/math/0411418">reality of real numbers</a>&#8220;; some made by Turing himself<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-27' id='enref-251-27' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>27</a></sup> on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computable_number">computable numbers</a>. Recently I discovered the tangential thoughts of N.J. Wildberger about the <a href="https://njwildberger.com/2012/12/02/difficulties-with-real-numbers/">difficulties with real numbers:</a></p>
<blockquote><p>A hundred years ago, the notion of the “continuum” appeared intuitively straightforward, but it was difficult to pin down precisely. The Greeks had struggled with irrational numbers, but the decimal number approach of Simon Stevin in the 16th century seemed reasonable, especially considering that in practice the further digits beyond the three dots in pi=3.14159263… are hardly of practical significance. Great mathematicians like Newton, Euler, Gauss, Lagrange and others were always interested in a combination of applied questions (physics and astronomy mostly) along with more theoretical questions. In the later part of the nineteenth century an increasing preoccupation with trying to pin down the fundamentals of analysis led to both more careful definitions but also to the realization that the default view of irrational numbers as infinite decimals was shaky.<br />
However with the advent of relativity theory and quantum mechanics, the concept of the continuum again became murky: if time is relative and perhaps finite in extent, and space has an inherent graininess which is not infinitely divisible, then what exactly are we modelling with our notion of the &#8216;infinite number line&#8217;?<br />
While engineers and scientists viewed real numbers primarily as “decimals which go on till we don’t care anymore”, nineteenth century mathematicians introduced the ideas of “equivalence classes of Cauchy sequences of rational numbers”, or as “Dedekind cuts”, or sometimes as “continued fractions”. Each view has different difficulties, but always there is the crucial problem of discussing `infinite objects’ without sufficient regard to how to specify them.</p></blockquote>
<p>Some physicists took some steps to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real_number#In_physics">avoid real numbers</a> in the foundations of physics. As an engineer, I know real numbers are useful and indispensable abstractions, but I realized long ago they are too abstract (i.e. too detached from the physical world) to be taken for granted as completely consistent with applications. As a software developer I know, in agreement with Wildberger&#8217;s view, we need to avoid irrational numbers in our software whenever we can for many practical reasons. If <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\pi</span> appears in an intermediate equation in my model I should rewrite the equations to eliminate <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\pi</span> from the final algorithm to be implemented whenever possible. For real numbers to be functional we, software developers, need to avoid coding most of them!</p>
<h3>Fractions &#8230; To Be Continued</h3>
<blockquote><p>But, surprisingly, one of the most striking and powerful representations of numbers is completely ignored in the mathematics that is taught in schools and it rarely makes an appearance in university courses, unless you take a special option in number theory. Yet continued fractions are one of the most revealing representations of numbers. Numbers whose decimal expansions look unremarkable and featureless are revealed to have extraordinary symmetries and patterns embedded deep within them when unfolded into a continued fraction. &#8212; John D. Barrow, <a href="https://plus.maths.org/content/chaos-numberland-secret-life-continued-fractions">Chaos in Numberland: The secret life of continued fractions</a>.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_567" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/phi-dna.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-6" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-567" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/phi-dna-300x278.jpg" alt="phi-dna" width="300" height="278" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/phi-dna-300x278.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/phi-dna.jpg 558w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The golden ration can be found everywhere in nature even in our DNA (<a href="http://www.interferencetheory.com/Articles/ArticlesGoldenRatio/files/5d222bf41ab67d8a339b4aa3f165c797-4.html">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>Not all irrationals are created equal, some are more irrational than others. The most irrational of all real numbers is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_ratio">Golden Ratio</a> <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\varphi=\frac{1}{2}(1+\sqrt{5})</span>; it&#8217;s the hardest irrational to approximate by any rational number<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-28' id='enref-251-28' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>28</a></sup>. Some of the greatest mathematical minds of all ages have spent endless hours over this simple ratio and its properties. Many books<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-29' id='enref-251-29' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>29</a></sup> have been written specifically for exploring its, often unexpected, appearances in biology, arts, music, history, architecture, and psychology<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-30' id='enref-251-30' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>30</a></sup>. One of the best ways for studying this fascinating number is by its <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continued_fraction">continued fraction</a> representation [1; 1, 1, 1, &#8230;].</p>
<p><div id="attachment_558" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/continued-fraction-pi.jpg" data-rel="lightbox-7" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-558" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/continued-fraction-pi-300x208.jpg" alt="A continued fraction approximation of Pi: [3; 7, 15, 1, 292, 1, 1, 2, ...] (Source)" width="300" height="208" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/continued-fraction-pi-300x208.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/continued-fraction-pi.jpg 575w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">A continued fraction approximation of Pi: [3; 7, 15, 1, 292, 1, 1, 2, &#8230;] (<a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/roots-of-unity/don-8217-t-recite-digits-to-celebrate-pi-recite-its-continued-fraction-instead/">Source</a>)</p></div>Continued fractions can be used to reveal many interesting properties of many <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mathematical_constants_by_continued_fraction_representation">interesting numbers</a>; they possess many outstanding properties:</p>
<ul>
<li>Rational numbers have unique finite continued fraction representations; irrational numbers have unique infinite representations. Contrast this property to traditional number systems (for example decimal and binary) that have infinite representations for both rationals and irrationals.</li>
<li>Continued fractions are, in a quantifiable way, the best approximations of numbers. If you truncate the continued fraction expansion of a number q, the rational number that you get is the closest you can get to q without having to resort to a larger denominator.</li>
<li>The continued fraction expansion of the square root of an integer (that isn&#8217;t a perfect square) always repeats. For example the square root of 3 has a representation [1; 1, 2, 1, 2, 1, 2, &#8230;]. Moreover, partial fractions with repeating numbers are exactly the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadratic_irrational">quadratic irrationals</a>.</li>
<li>There is a very high probability that integers appearing in continued fraction representations are of small value; the probability distribution of such integers is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gauss%E2%80%93Kuzmin_distribution">Gauss–Kuzmin distribution</a><sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-31' id='enref-251-31' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>31</a></sup>.</li>
</ul>
<div id="attachment_578" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/elec-ladder.png" data-rel="lightbox-8" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-578" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/elec-ladder-300x166.png" alt="elec-ladder" width="300" height="166" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/elec-ladder-300x166.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/elec-ladder.png 370w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Electrical ladder network input impedance Z is given by continued fraction. See <a href="https://projecteuclid.org/euclid.bams/1183493356">this paper</a> for detailed analysis</p></div>
<p>Continued fractions appear in the study of many chaotic systems. Numbers whose Continued fractions end in an infinite string of 1&#8217;s, like the golden ratio, are called noble numbers. The golden mean is the &#8220;noblest&#8221; of all because all of its quotients are 1&#8217;s. The designation &#8220;noble numbers&#8221; stem from the fact that in many nonlinear dynamical systems “winding numbers”, the frequency ratios of orbits in phase space, that equal noble numbers are the most resistant against the onset of chaotic motion, which is ubiquitous in nature<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-32' id='enref-251-32' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>32</a></sup>; think of turbulence or the weather, for that matter. The very stability of the entire solar system depends on the nobility of orbital period ratios<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-33' id='enref-251-33' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>33</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Continued fractions have many important geometric interpretations, especially in terms of <a href="http://www.geometrie.tugraz.at/karpenkov/cf2011s.html">integer geometry</a>; the geometry of points that are pairwise integer distances apart<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-34' id='enref-251-34' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>34</a></sup>. In addition, the same idea behind continued fractions can be applied to approximate general functions by rational functions; the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pad%C3%A9_approximant">Padé approximant</a>. The Padé approximant often gives a better approximation of the function than truncating its Taylor series, and it may still work where the Taylor series does not converge. For these reasons Padé approximants are used extensively in computer calculations. I believe that many problems in science and engineering can be approached much effectively using continued fractions and their generalizations; we just need to have a deeper understanding of such problems to detect their &#8220;fractionally continued&#8221; nature.</p>
<h3>The Lateral Unity</h3>
<blockquote><p>I tell you, with complex numbers you can do anything. &#8212; John Derbyshire.</p></blockquote>
<p>Complex numbers are not just another generalization of real numbers on the &#8220;number line&#8221;; they literally introduce a whole new dimension to the &#8220;concept of number&#8221; allowing the symbolic representation and manipulation of geometric entities on a higher level than real numbers do. This is similar in some degree to the use of C instead of Assembly in software development for example. As an electrical engineer, I use complex numbers in many applications in signal processing, electrical circuits, and many others. The most important mathematical function for electrical engineers is the &#8220;vector rotating at frequency <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\omega</span>&#8220;: <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">e^{i\omega t}</span>. The whole of Fourier Transform theory is based on this single complex function with a significant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imaginary_number#Geometric_interpretation">geometric interpretation</a>. Historically the algebraic representation of complex numbers came first in the 16th century when trying to find real algebraic solutions for the roots of cubic and quartic polynomials; hitting the wall of the &#8220;roots of negative numbers&#8221;. The term &#8220;imaginary&#8221; for these quantities was coined by René Descartes, although he was at pains to stress their imaginary nature. It was Gauss who introduced the term &#8220;complex number&#8221; when submitting his ideas to the Royal Society of Gottingen. He provided a geometric representation of this class of numbers<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-35' id='enref-251-35' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>35</a></sup>:</p>
<blockquote><p>If this subject has hitherto been considered from the wrong viewpoint and thus enveloped in mystery and surrounded by darkness, it is largely an unsuitable terminology which should be blamed. Had +1, -1 and <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\sqrt{-1}</span>, instead of being called positive, negative and imaginary (or worse still, impossible) unity, been given the names say, of direct, inverse and lateral unity, there would hardly have been any scope for such obscurity.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_285" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/ComplexSet-big.png" data-rel="lightbox-9" title=""><img class="size-medium wp-image-285" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/ComplexSet-big-300x219.png" alt="Complex Numbers" width="300" height="219" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/ComplexSet-big-300x219.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/ComplexSet-big-768x561.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/ComplexSet-big.png 974w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Complex Numbers (<a href="http://thinkzone.wlonk.com/Numbers/NumberSets.htm">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>Complex numbers are indispensable for modern science and engineering; mainly because they contain all other commonly used sets of numbers while adding more meaning and power. Nevertheless, the most important function of complex numbers, in my opinion, is generalizing the concept of a number from 1 dimension to 2 dimensions in a geometric manner; logically backed by algebra. The Cartesian form of a complex number <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">x+iy</span> introduced the important idea of &#8220;formal sum&#8221; of algebraic quantities (real <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">x</span> and imaginary <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">iy</span>) to the common math user; including high school students. The polar form of a complex number <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">re^{i\theta}</span> introduced the geometric meaning of the product operation as a &#8220;scaled rotation transformation&#8221;. Just reading the first chapter of Needham&#8217;s brilliant book &#8220;Visual Complex Analysis&#8221;<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-36' id='enref-251-36' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>36</a></sup> can show you the depth of algebraic expressiveness for geometric ideas complex numbers can have. Using the Cartesian and polar forms of  complex numbers one can:</p>
<ul>
<li>Extend the concept of a number from 1 dimension (the number line) to 2 dimensions (the complex plane).</li>
<li>Represent points and vectors in a plane using a single symbolic entity with a full set of operations (i.e. a complex number and its arithmetic).</li>
<li>Represent the operations of translation (using the addition of complex numbers) and scaled rotation (using complex numbers multiplication) in a plane that can act on points and vectors; effectively unifying &#8220;data&#8221; and &#8220;processing&#8221; algebraically using a single algebraic entity, the complex number.</li>
<li>Allowing geometric transformations to be expressed as functions (maps) on the complex plane; a very powerful concept linking geometry to calculus.</li>
</ul>
<p>These ideas are fundamental for the following developments of the concept of a number that we will continue perusing in <a href="/index.php/2015/08/07/history-of-numbers2/">part two</a> of this functional history of numbers.</p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/done2.png" data-rel="lightbox-10" title=""><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-298" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/done2.png" alt="done2" width="300" height="40" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<hr />
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class='endnotes' id='hhendnotes-251'>
<ol>
<li id='en-251-1'>Calvin C. Clawson, &#8220;The Mathematical Traveler, Exploring the Grand History of Numbers&#8221;. Springer Science 1994 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-1'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-2'>James Gow, &#8220;A Short History of Greek Mathematics&#8221;, Cambridge University Press 2010 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-2'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-3'>Joseph H. Silverman, &#8220;A Friendly Introduction to Number Theory, 4th Edition&#8221;. Pearson 2012 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-3'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-4'>Calvin C. Clawson, &#8220;The Mathematical Traveler, Exploring the Grand History of Numbers&#8221;. Springer Science 1994 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-4'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-5'>A good online article of two parts giving a summary of the contributions of ancient Indian mathematicians can be found <a href="http://www.vedicsciences.net/articles/history-of-numbers.html">here</a> and <a href="http://www.vedicsciences.net/articles/history-of-numbers-part-2.html">here</a>. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-5'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-6'>J. L. Berggren, &#8220;Episodes in the Mathematics of Medieval Islam&#8221;. Springer 1986 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-6'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-7'>Art Johnson, &#8220;Famous Problems and Their Mathematicians&#8221;. Greenwood Publishing Group 1999 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-7'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-8'>For a very interesting documetary about some of the contrubutions of Al-Khawarizmi see Jim Al-Khalili&#8217;s &#8220;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sAxWF_W6Q9w" data-rel="lightbox-video-0">Science in a Golden Age &#8211; Al-Khwarizmi: The Father of Algebra</a>&#8221; <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-8'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-9'>This <a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/terry_moore_why_is_x_the_unknown?language=en">TED video</a> explains why is &#8216;x&#8217; the symbol for an unknown relating it to the Arabic word &#8220;Chay&#8217;a&#8221; or &#8220;thing&#8221; <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-9'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-10'>Johannes Grabmeier, Erich Kaltofen, Volker Weispfenning (Editors), &#8220;Computer Algebra Handbook &#8211; Foundations, Applications, Systems&#8221;. Springer 2003 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-10'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-11'>During my research for this post, I found some articles stating a misconception about females having less inheritance than males in Islam. The truth is giving women less inheritance is not a universal law of inheritance in Islam. As clearly explained <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamic_inheritance_jurisprudence#Women_and_inheritance">here</a>:<br />
<blockquote><p>However, this principle is not universally applicable, and there are other circumstances where women might receive equal shares to men. For example, the share of the mother and father of a childless decedent. Also the share of a uterine brother is equal to the share of a uterine sister, as do the shares of their descendants &#8230; Some times women get double the share then that of men, for example if there are only parents and husband, husband will receive half, father gets 1/6 and mother gets 2/6.</p></blockquote>
<p>A good study for the reasons behind giving less inheritance to women in some situations can be found <a href="http://www.kantakji.com/media/3799/4015.pdf">here</a>. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-11'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-12'>Contrast this religion-motivated development of science in the middle ages Islamic lands with the (lack of) development of science in the same period called dark age Europe that lasted until the 12th century, driven by religion and continuous wars in the direction of scientific degeneracy. See <a href="https://www.quora.com/Why-did-science-make-little-real-progress-in-Europe-in-the-Middle-Ages-3?redirected_qid=489923">this article</a> for more interesting details <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-12'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-13'>O&#8217;Connor, John J.; Robertson, Edmund F., &#8220;<a href="http://www-history.mcs.st-and.ac.uk/HistTopics/Arabic_mathematics.html">Arabic mathematics: forgotten brilliance?</a>&#8220;, MacTutor History of Mathematics archive, University of St Andrews. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-13'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-14'>more accurately Islamic mathematics, many Muslim scientists and mathematicians were not of Arab origin <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-14'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-15'>Salim T.S. Al-Hassani, &#8220;1001 Inventions: The Enduring Legacy of Muslim Civilization, 3rd Edition&#8221;. National Geographic 2012. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-15'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-16'>Firas Alkhateeb, &#8220;Lost Islamic History: Reclaiming Muslim Civilization from the Past 1st Edition&#8221;. Hurst 2014. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-16'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-17'>Michael H. Morgan, &#8220;Lost History: The Enduring Legacy of Muslim Scientists, Thinkers, and Artists&#8221;. National Geographic 2008 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-17'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-18'>Joseph H. Silverman, &#8220;A Friendly Introduction to Number Theory, 4th Edition&#8221;. Pearson 2012 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-18'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-19'>Diane L. Herrmann, Paul J. Sally Jr., &#8220;Number, Shape, &amp; Symmetry: An Introduction to Number Theory, Geometry, and Group Theory 1st Edition&#8221;. CRC Press 2012 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-19'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-20'>Jeffrey Hoffstein, Jill Pipher, and Joseph H. Silverman, &#8220;An Introduction to Mathematical Cryptography, 2nd Edition&#8221;. Springer Science 2014 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-20'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-21'>Oliver Pretzel, &#8220;Error-Correcting Codes and Finite Fields&#8221;. Clarendon Press 1992 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-21'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-22'>Stephen Wolfram, &#8220;A New Kind of Science&#8221;, Wolfram Media 2002 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-22'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-23'>See chapter 4 and 16 of M. R. Schroeder, &#8220;Number Theory in Science and Communication, 4th Edition&#8221;. Springer 2006 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-23'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-24'>You can find a very simple and informal introduction by N. J. Wildberger using &#8220;Reversimals&#8221; or 10-adic numbers <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XXRwlo_MHnI&amp;list=PL5A714C94D40392AB&amp;index=65" data-rel="lightbox-video-1">here</a>, and a tutorial for this system <a href="http://cryptocode.net/docs/r09.pdf">here</a> <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-24'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-25'>R. T. Gregory, E. V. Krishnamurthy, &#8220;Methods and Applications of Error-Free Computation&#8221;. Springer 1984 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-25'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-26'>See for example N.J. Wildberger&#8217;s video &#8220;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=REeaT2mWj6Y" data-rel="lightbox-video-2">Inconvenient truths about sqrt(2)</a>&#8221; <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-26'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-27'>B. Jack Copeland, &#8220;The Essential Turing&#8221;. Clarendon Press, Oxford 2004. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-27'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-28'>Jay Kappraff, &#8220;Beyond Measure &#8211; A Guided Tour Through Nature, Myth, and Number&#8221;. World Scientific 2002 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-28'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-29'>See for example Livio, Mario, &#8220;The Golden Ratio: The Story of Phi, The World&#8217;s Most Astonishing Number&#8221;. Broadway Books 2002, and H.E. Huntley, &#8220;The Divine Proportion: A Study in Mathematical Beauty&#8221;. Dover Publications 1970 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-29'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-30'><a href="https://www.goldennumber.net/">This site</a> is dedicated to sharing the best information on Phi with insights from dozens of Contributors on a broad range of topics. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-30'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-31'>This is explained more in John D. Barrow article <a href="https://plus.maths.org/content/chaos-numberland-secret-life-continued-fractions">here</a> <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-31'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-32'>M. R. Schroeder, &#8220;Number Theory in Science and Communication, 4th Edition&#8221;. Springer 2006 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-32'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-33'>See <a href="https://tallbloke.wordpress.com/2013/02/20/a-remarkable-discovery-all-solar-system-periods-fit-the-fibonacci-series-and-the-golden-ratio-why-phi/">this article</a> relating Solar system periods to the Golden Ratio <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-33'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-34'>Oleg Karpenkov, &#8220;Geometry of Continued Fractions&#8221;. Springer 2013 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-34'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-35'>Paul J. Nahin, &#8220;An Imaginary Tale&#8221;. Princeton University Press 1998 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-35'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-36'>Tristan Needham, &#8220;Visual Complex Analysis&#8221;. Oxford University Press 2000 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-36'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
</ol>
</div>
<p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=%2Findex.php%2F2015%2F07%2F24%2Fhistory-of-numbers1%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Functional%20History%20of%20Numbers%20%281%20of%203%29" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_twitter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/twitter?linkurl=%2Findex.php%2F2015%2F07%2F24%2Fhistory-of-numbers1%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Functional%20History%20of%20Numbers%20%281%20of%203%29" title="Twitter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_google_plus" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/google_plus?linkurl=%2Findex.php%2F2015%2F07%2F24%2Fhistory-of-numbers1%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Functional%20History%20of%20Numbers%20%281%20of%203%29" title="Google+" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=%2Findex.php%2F2015%2F07%2F24%2Fhistory-of-numbers1%2F&amp;title=A%20Functional%20History%20of%20Numbers%20%281%20of%203%29" data-a2a-url="/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/" data-a2a-title="A Functional History of Numbers (1 of 3)"></a></p><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/">A Functional History of Numbers (1 of 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
