<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Projective Geometry &#8211; Geometric Algebra Explorer</title>
	<atom:link href="/index.php/tag/projective-geometry/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Voyaging the Computational Universe with Geometric Algebra</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 19:18:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.8.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/cropped-GAExplorer-Icon-150x150.jpg</url>
	<title>Projective Geometry &#8211; Geometric Algebra Explorer</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Projective Insights</title>
		<link>/index.php/2017/03/17/projective-insights/</link>
		<comments>/index.php/2017/03/17/projective-insights/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2017 18:43:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ahmad Eid]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[GA Math]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometric Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interview]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Biquaternions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Duality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Euclidean Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hyperbolic Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Projective Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rational Trigonometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spherical Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Visualization]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://gacomputing.info/?p=2706</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>In this post, I interview Dr. Charles Gunn, a mathematician, movie-maker, and teacher whose mathematical activities center around projective geometry and its connection to the human being and the world.  He is particularly excited by his recent work on Projective Geometric Algebra (PGA), which he believes has a great role to play in bringing the benefits of GA to a wider audience.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2017/03/17/projective-insights/">Projective Insights</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class='dropshadowboxes-container ' style='width:auto;'>
                            <div class='dropshadowboxes-drop-shadow dropshadowboxes-rounded-corners dropshadowboxes-inside-and-outside-shadow dropshadowboxes-lifted-both dropshadowboxes-effect-default' style=' border: 1px solid #dddddd; height:; background-color:#ffffff;    '>
                            
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/maxpixel.freegreatpicture.com-Sunrise-Crystal-Ball-New-Brighton-1239724.jpg"><img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2723" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/maxpixel.freegreatpicture.com-Sunrise-Crystal-Ball-New-Brighton-1239724-1024x576.jpg" alt="Projective Insights" width="1024" height="576" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/maxpixel.freegreatpicture.com-Sunrise-Crystal-Ball-New-Brighton-1239724-1024x576.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/maxpixel.freegreatpicture.com-Sunrise-Crystal-Ball-New-Brighton-1239724-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/maxpixel.freegreatpicture.com-Sunrise-Crystal-Ball-New-Brighton-1239724-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/maxpixel.freegreatpicture.com-Sunrise-Crystal-Ball-New-Brighton-1239724.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></p>
<div class="su-animate" style="visibility:hidden;-webkit-animation-duration:2s;-webkit-animation-delay:0s;animation-duration:2s;animation-delay:0s;" data-animation="fadeInUp" data-duration="2" data-delay="0">
<div class="su-quote su-quote-style-default su-quote-has-cite"><div class="su-quote-inner su-clearfix">
<p>Projective geometry is all geometry.</p>
<span class="su-quote-cite">Arthur Cayley</span></div></div>
</div>

                            </div>
                        </div>
<hr />
<span class="dropcap">P</span><strong><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Projective_geometry" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rojective Geometry</a></strong> is the branch of geometry dealing with the properties and invariants of geometric figures under projection. In older literature, projective geometry is sometimes called &#8220;higher geometry,&#8221; &#8220;geometry of position,&#8221; or &#8220;descriptive geometry&#8221;. The most amazing result arising in projective geometry is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duality_(projective_geometry)" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>duality principle</strong></a>, which states that a duality exists between theorems such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pascal's_theorem" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pascal&#8217;s theorem</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brianchon%27s_theorem" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Brianchon&#8217;s theorem</a> which allows one to be instantly transformed into the other. More generally, all the propositions in projective geometry occur in dual pairs, which have the property that, starting from either proposition of a pair, the other can be immediately inferred by interchanging the parts played by the words &#8220;point&#8221; and &#8220;line.&#8221;</p>
<hr />
<div class="su-animate" style="visibility:hidden;-webkit-animation-duration:2s;-webkit-animation-delay:0s;animation-duration:2s;animation-delay:0s;" data-animation="fadeInUp" data-duration="2" data-delay="0">
<div class="su-note" style="border-color:#dad5cc;border-radius:10px;-moz-border-radius:10px;-webkit-border-radius:10px;"><div class="su-note-inner su-clearfix" style="background-color:#f2ede3;border-color:#fcfbf9;color:#464646;border-radius:10px;-moz-border-radius:10px;-webkit-border-radius:10px;">
<div class='content-column three_fourth'><h3>About Dr. Charles Gunn</h3>
<p>In this post, I interview <a href="http://page.math.tu-berlin.de/~gunn/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dr. Charles Gunn</a>, a mathematician, movie-maker, and teacher whose mathematical activities center around projective geometry and its connection to the human being and the world.  He is particularly excited by his recent work on <strong><a href="http://dgd.service.tu-berlin.de/wordpress/vismathws12/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Projective Geometric Algebra</a> (PGA)</strong>, which he believes has a great role to play in bringing the benefits of GA to a wider audience.</p></div>
<div class='content-column one_fourth last_column'><div class='dropshadowboxes-container dropshadowboxes-center ' style='width:100%;'>
                            <div class='dropshadowboxes-drop-shadow dropshadowboxes-rounded-corners dropshadowboxes-outside-shadow dropshadowboxes-lifted-both dropshadowboxes-effect-default' style='width:auto; border: 1px solid #dddddd; height:; background-color:#ffffff;    '>
                            
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/mugshot2012-01-small.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-2725 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/mugshot2012-01-small.jpg" alt="Dr. Charles Gunn" width="200" height="279" /></a></p>

                            </div>
                        </div></div><div class='clear_column'></div>
</div></div>
</div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="su-service"><div class="su-service-title" style="padding-left:46px;min-height:32px;line-height:32px"><i class="fa fa-comments-o" style="font-size:32px;color:#333"></i> Tell us about your interest in Projective Geometric Algebra (PGA). Why do you focus on this particular area? Do you have specific PGA-related long-term goals?</div><div class="su-service-content su-clearfix" style="padding-left:46px">
<p>My interest in PGA is a natural outgrowth of my long-standing interest in projective geometry. One of the phases in this process was my work at the <a href="http://www.geom.uiuc.edu/">Geometry Center</a> at the University of Minnesota (1987-1993), where we created interactive visualizations of hyperbolic and spherical space for the first time using the projective models of these spaces, under the guidance of the late Bill Thurston.</p>
<p>It was natural then that when I went back (quite a bit later) to get a Ph. D. I looked into how not just to make pictures but how to do physics in these non-euclidean spaces. That&#8217;s when I became aware of a certain family of geometric algebras that I have since christened PGA and that formed the technical foundation for <a href="http://page.math.tu-berlin.de/~gunn/Documents/Papers/Thesis-final.pdf">my thesis</a> (Technical University Berlin, 2011).</p>
<p>The non-euclidean cases were already familiar to the pioneers of GA in the 1870&#8217;s such as Clifford and Klein; the euclidean case, however, is a bit tricky and was first enunciated by Jon Selig in around 2000. I have gone on to explore PGA more thoroughly and have published a series of articles devoted especially to the euclidean case; since I think it&#8217;s a fantastic tool &#8212; both conceptually and practically &#8212; for doing euclidean geometry. It includes as sub-algebras the well-known vector, quaternion, and dual (or bi-) quaternion algebras, but offers much more besides. It deserves to be much better-known than it is, especially in the applied mathematics and engineering community. In the article &#8220;<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1411.6502">Geometric algebras for euclidean geometry</a>&#8221; I have shown that for classical &#8220;flat&#8221; euclidean geometry, PGA exhibits distinct advantages over the alternative approaches. It serves also as an ideal stepping-stone both scientifically and pedagogically to more complex GAs such as CGA. This article and others can be accessed at my <a href="http://page.math.tu-berlin.de/~gunn/PGA/">PGA resource page</a>.</p>
</div></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="su-service"><div class="su-service-title" style="padding-left:46px;min-height:32px;line-height:32px"><i class="fa fa-comments-o" style="font-size:32px;color:#333"></i> What do you think about the great legacy of 19th-century geometry? Do you feel the scientific community is properly making good use of this legacy? Are there serious obstacles in the way of discovering the true power of 19th-century geometry? Can PGA be useful in this context?</div><div class="su-service-content su-clearfix" style="padding-left:46px">
<div class='dropshadowboxes-container dropshadowboxes-right ' style='width:auto;'>
                            <div class='dropshadowboxes-drop-shadow dropshadowboxes-rounded-corners dropshadowboxes-outside-shadow dropshadowboxes-lifted-both dropshadowboxes-effect-default' style=' border: 1px solid #dddddd; height:; background-color:#ffffff;    '>
                            
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/borromean4Fold.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-2719 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/borromean4Fold-300x300.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/borromean4Fold-300x300.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/borromean4Fold-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/borromean4Fold-160x160.jpg 160w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/borromean4Fold-320x320.jpg 320w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/borromean4Fold.jpg 512w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>

                            </div>
                        </div>
<p>The development of mathematics in the 19th century was unique: radical advances were made in every field but an underlying unity was preserved so that leading mathematicians still had an overview of the whole. The transition to the 20th century saw an increasing specialization, the cost was a splintering of the whole. Decisions were made that in retrospect appear to have been motivated more by an ideology of abstraction than by a balanced practical judgment. PGA I think has the potential to stand as &#8220;living proof&#8221; that 19th-century mathematics still has much to offer to the contemporary community of applied geometry. It unifies two of William Clifford&#8217;s greatest inventions: biquaternions and geometric algebra, in the simplest, most elegant way imaginable, and provides an unsurpassed framework for doing kinematics and rigid body mechanics in euclidean (or non-euclidean) space.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it&#8217;s also important to note that PGA also contains seeds for the future. I&#8217;m particularly interested in this regard in dual euclidean space, which is a metric geometry obtained from euclidean geometry by dualizing it. It arises naturally as a variant of PGA. It was described by Felix Klein in the 19th century but was so unfamiliar that is was relegated to being a curiosity. There is an increasing volume of research, however, indicating that it might play an important role in future science by balancing a certain one-sidedness in our contemporary spatial awareness. Ch. 10 of my thesis contains an introduction to this fascinating theme, available on the resource site above.</p>
<p>The prospect of using PGA in this way to better understand Nature also resonates with the 19th-century heritage.  The great pioneers of that era &#8212; Möbius, Plücker, Riemann, Grassmann, Clifford, and Klein, among others &#8212; were all inspired, in their mathematical research, by physical questions. I personally think that mathematics needs such real-world connections in order to develop healthily and am curious to see whether PGA can help to strengthen such connections.</p>
</div></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="su-service"><div class="su-service-title" style="padding-left:46px;min-height:32px;line-height:32px"><i class="fa fa-comments-o" style="font-size:32px;color:#333"></i> In one of your papers, you talk about representing N. J. Wildberger's Rational Trigonometry via PGA. Tell us about some interesting aspects of Rational Trigonometry from your point of view. How can PGA representation exhibit distinct advantages over the original coordinates-based approach?</div><div class="su-service-content su-clearfix" style="padding-left:46px">
<div class='dropshadowboxes-container dropshadowboxes-right ' style='width:auto;'>
                            <div class='dropshadowboxes-drop-shadow dropshadowboxes-rounded-corners dropshadowboxes-outside-shadow dropshadowboxes-lifted-both dropshadowboxes-effect-default' style=' border: 1px solid #dddddd; height:; background-color:#ffffff;    '>
                            
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/hqdefault.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-2718 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/hqdefault-300x225.jpg" alt="Rational Trigonometry" width="300" height="225" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/hqdefault-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/hqdefault.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>

                            </div>
                        </div>
<p>I am no expert on <a href="http://www.cut-the-knot.org/pythagoras/RationalTrig/CutTheKnot.shtml">Wildberger&#8217;s Rational Trigonometry</a>, although I find the basic idea intriguing. One avoids the messiness of evaluating irrational and/or transcendental functions by working with the sine/cosine of the angle rather than with the angle itself, the square of the norm of a vector instead of the norm, etc. A friend loaned me a copy of Wildberger&#8217;s book as I was finishing my thesis and I made it a project to see how many of his results I could rephrase in the language of PGA. I was surprised myself by how well this process went. For example, the fundamental concepts of rational trigonometry &#8212; quadrance and spread &#8212; reveal themselves in PGA to be precisely dual to each other, a fact not obvious in the original treatment. Furthermore, many of the derivations in PGA are, in my humble opinion, clearer and shorter than the coordinate-based ones in the original. I determined that the whole subject could probably be rephrased in this way using PGA but the lack of time has prevented further work in this direction. This experience is typical when I &#8220;translate&#8221; standard treatments of Euclidean geometry into PGA: often I discover a remarkable conciseness and elegance in the PGA version.</p>
</div></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="su-service"><div class="su-service-title" style="padding-left:46px;min-height:32px;line-height:32px"><i class="fa fa-comments-o" style="font-size:32px;color:#333"></i> Tell us about the process of creating software for PGA investigations. What characteristics should this kind of software have? Which software development paradigms you feel most suitable for this process? What are the components you find lacking in current programming languages in this regard?</div><div class="su-service-content su-clearfix" style="padding-left:46px">
<p>I am not a software purist; I used whatever helps me get the job done. Robustness and thorough documentation are my primary criteria. All my PGA investigations also involve visualization, so these two themes go hand-in-hand. Among commercial products, my favorite tool is Mathematica and I use it for prototype development. In fact, I used Mathematica to check all the results in my thesis for correctness.</p>
<div class='dropshadowboxes-container dropshadowboxes-right ' style='width:auto;'>
                            <div class='dropshadowboxes-drop-shadow dropshadowboxes-rounded-corners dropshadowboxes-outside-shadow dropshadowboxes-lifted-both dropshadowboxes-effect-default' style=' border: 1px solid #dddddd; height:; background-color:#ffffff;    '>
                            
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/borromean4Fold-8k_cr.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-2716 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/borromean4Fold-8k_cr-300x203.png" alt="" width="300" height="203" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/borromean4Fold-8k_cr-300x203.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/borromean4Fold-8k_cr.png 625w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>

                            </div>
                        </div>
<p>For production software, I favor public domain software. Throughout my career (since writing my first hidden-surface removal algorithm on punch cards in 1978 at UNC-CH) I have developed such visualization software in parallel to my mathematical interests, as I found that existing 3D tools were/are generally not flexible enough to render what I wanted to. I worked on the <a href="http://www.geomview.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">geomview project</a> at the Geometry Center in the early 90&#8217;s. The latest incarnation in this direction is the <a href="http://www3.math.tu-berlin.de/jreality/jrealityStatic/index.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Java 3D scene graph jReality</a>, which I&#8217;ve been involved with at the TU Berlin since 2003. Like geomview, it is built on the foundation of projective geometry and can be then specialized to support different metric geometries such as Euclidean, hyperbolic, and spherical geometry, and has been further specialized by me for my PGA research.</p>
<p>I have also been learning Haskell recently since its pure functional, polymorphic style is particularly well-suited to reliably mapping mathematical domains such as PGA and it seems to be gaining quite a large following. I have looked at other GA packages, hoping to apply them to PGA, but at the time I looked none of them supported a degenerate metric (a key feature of Euclidean PGA). If anyone reading this knows of a standard GA package that supports a non-metric &#8220;duality&#8221; operator please let me know (projgeom@gmail.com).</p>
</div></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="su-service"><div class="su-service-title" style="padding-left:46px;min-height:32px;line-height:32px"><i class="fa fa-comments-o" style="font-size:32px;color:#333"></i> In one of your papers, you describe an algorithm for decorating the edges of a regular tetrahedron with helical ribbons to generate new interesting forms. Do you feel there is a strong connection between Projective Geometry and Art? Can PGA be useful as an abstract generative modeling language for such activity?</div><div class="su-service-content su-clearfix" style="padding-left:46px">
<div class='dropshadowboxes-container dropshadowboxes-right ' style='width:auto;'>
                            <div class='dropshadowboxes-drop-shadow dropshadowboxes-rounded-corners dropshadowboxes-outside-shadow dropshadowboxes-lifted-both dropshadowboxes-effect-default' style=' border: 1px solid #dddddd; height:; background-color:#ffffff;    '>
                            
<div id="attachment_2739" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/ribbonEdges-01.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-2739" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/ribbonEdges-01-300x283.jpg" alt="Ribbon Edges Sculpture" width="300" height="283" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/ribbonEdges-01-300x283.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/ribbonEdges-01-768x723.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/03/ribbonEdges-01.jpg 1000w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Ribbon edge sculpture 3D print</p></div>

                            </div>
                        </div>
<p>My work on &#8220;generative sculpture&#8221; grew out of my experimenting with 3D printing at the 3D Lab of the TU Berlin beginning about 10 years ago. I was interested in printing polyhedra with different sorts of symmetry. I set myself the challenge of seeing whether I could maintain the identity of the polyhedron while smoothing out the &#8220;sharp corners&#8221; at the vertices, and <a href="http://page.math.tu-berlin.de/~gunn/Documents/Papers/ribbonEdges.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the &#8220;ribbon edges&#8221; paper</a> was the outcome. (For details see my web page at the TUB). Although there was no direct connection to projective geometry in this work, I do think projective geometry can have a similar effect &#8212; compared to Euclidean geometry (or any metric geometry) it is a much more flexible and mobile geometry and contains within it many possibilities for metamorphosis and polarities characteristic of change and interaction. These I think may have to do with how form, especially living form, emerges in the first place, before it arrives at its fixed Euclidean form. There&#8217;s much work that remains to be done in this direction, I believe projective geometry itself still contains lots of surprises for inquiring minds.</p>
</div></div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2017/03/17/projective-insights/">Projective Insights</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/index.php/2017/03/17/projective-insights/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cybernetics with Transdisciplinary Geometric Algebra</title>
		<link>/index.php/2017/01/27/ga-cybernetics/</link>
		<comments>/index.php/2017/01/27/ga-cybernetics/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 13:23:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ahmad Eid]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[GA Applications]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometric Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interview]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer Vision]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Control]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cybernetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometric Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lie Groups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neural Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Projective Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robotics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://gacomputing.info/?p=2369</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>A Cyberneticist, or cybernetician, is a person practicing Cybernetics: a transdisciplinary approach for exploring regulatory systems; their structures, constraints, and possibilities. Professor Eduardo Bayro-Corrochano is one such leading academic who uses Geometric Algebra to handle the diverse fields of theoretical knowledge and practical application he needs. Such fields include Robotics, Neural Computing, Computer Vision, and Lie Algebras. In this post, I interview Prof. Eduardo Bayro who tells us about how using GA in his work can simplify dealing with such diverse fields, and how can GA relate, generalize, and unify ideas from these fields together in his mind and the minds of his students.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2017/01/27/ga-cybernetics/">Cybernetics with Transdisciplinary Geometric Algebra</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class='dropshadowboxes-container ' style='width:auto;'>
                            <div class='dropshadowboxes-drop-shadow dropshadowboxes-rounded-corners dropshadowboxes-inside-and-outside-shadow dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved-horizontal-2 dropshadowboxes-effect-default' style=' border: 1px solid #dddddd; height:; background-color:#ffffff;    '>
                            
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Cybernetics.jpg"><img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2372" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Cybernetics-1024x680.jpg" alt="Cybernetics" width="1024" height="680" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Cybernetics-1024x680.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Cybernetics-300x199.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Cybernetics-768x510.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Cybernetics.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></p>
<div class="su-animate" style="visibility:hidden;-webkit-animation-duration:2s;-webkit-animation-delay:0s;animation-duration:2s;animation-delay:0s;" data-animation="fadeInUp" data-duration="2" data-delay="0">
<div class="su-quote su-quote-style-default su-quote-has-cite"><div class="su-quote-inner su-clearfix">
<p>Hard sciences are successful because they deal with the soft problems; soft sciences are struggling because they deal with the hard problems.</p>
<span class="su-quote-cite">Heinz von Foerster</span></div></div>
</div>

                            </div>
                        </div>
<hr />
<span class="dropcap">A</span> Cyberneticist, or cybernetician, is a person practicing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cybernetics" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cybernetics</a>: a transdisciplinary approach for exploring regulatory systems; their structures, constraints, and possibilities. Professor Eduardo Bayro-Corrochano is one such leading academic who uses Geometric Algebra to handle the diverse fields of theoretical knowledge and practical application he needs. Such fields include Robotics, Neural Computing, Computer Vision, and Lie Algebras. In this post, I interview Prof. Eduardo Bayro who tells us about how using GA in his work can simplify dealing with such diverse fields, and how can GA relate, generalize, and unify ideas from these fields together in his mind and the minds of his students.</p>
<hr />
<div class="su-animate" style="visibility:hidden;-webkit-animation-duration:2s;-webkit-animation-delay:0s;animation-duration:2s;animation-delay:0s;" data-animation="fadeInUp" data-duration="2" data-delay="0">
<div class="su-note" style="border-color:#acb3bd;border-radius:10px;-moz-border-radius:10px;-webkit-border-radius:10px;"><div class="su-note-inner su-clearfix" style="background-color:#BFC7D2;border-color:#f2f4f6;color:#464646;border-radius:10px;-moz-border-radius:10px;-webkit-border-radius:10px;">
<div class='content-column three_fourth'><h3>About Professor Eduardo Bayro</h3>
<p>Professor Eduardo Bayro started working on the applications of GA in the late 1990’s. His work is to stress the application of GA in cybernetics which typically involves Robotics, Neural Computing, Computer Vision, and Lie Algebras. Using GA-based geometric computing he tackled problems related to the building of intelligent machines, particularly Humanoids, to formulate algorithms for dealing with computer graphics curves, spheres, hyperplanes, and simple geometric tasks. Another goal is to build intelligent machines with real devices using geometric control, geometric perception and even quaternion wavelet transform, quaternion spike, or quantum quaternion neurons. Currently, he is preparing a new book series of 3 volumes on these topics. He is laying out the theory of future geometric intelligent robots and machines with powerful FPGA and Nvidia geometric accelerators.</p></div>
<div class='content-column one_fourth last_column'><div class='dropshadowboxes-container dropshadowboxes-center ' style='width:100%;'>
                            <div class='dropshadowboxes-drop-shadow dropshadowboxes-rounded-corners dropshadowboxes-outside-shadow dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved-horizontal-2 dropshadowboxes-effect-default' style='width:auto; border: 1px solid #dddddd; height:; background-color:#ffffff;    '>
                            
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Prof.-Eduardo-Bayro.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-2380 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Prof.-Eduardo-Bayro-180x300.jpg" alt="Prof. Eduardo Bayro" width="180" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Prof.-Eduardo-Bayro-180x300.jpg 180w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Prof.-Eduardo-Bayro.jpg 409w" sizes="(max-width: 180px) 100vw, 180px" /></a></p>

                            </div>
                        </div></div><div class='clear_column'></div>
</div></div>
</div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="su-service"><div class="su-service-title" style="padding-left:46px;min-height:32px;line-height:32px"><i class="fa fa-comments-o" style="font-size:32px;color:#333"></i> Tell us about the benefits of using Geometric Algebra in Geometric Computing applications.</div><div class="su-service-content su-clearfix" style="padding-left:46px">
<p>Geometric Algebra (GA) is a powerful geometric language for the modeling of the physics of systems. It is a highly intuitive language and provides many algebraic tools very useful to tackle complex equation manipulations. GA allows economical representations of transformations due to the GA multivector representation as opposite to analytic geometry or vector calculus. GA-based representations avoid redundant parameters and elegantly encapsulate the geometry of the problem. As a result due to its economical representations, GA is a well-suited framework for the development of real-time computations.</p>
</div></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="su-service"><div class="su-service-title" style="padding-left:46px;min-height:32px;line-height:32px"><i class="fa fa-comments-o" style="font-size:32px;color:#333"></i> How can using GA simplify dealing with the diverse fields of interdisciplinary applications you are working on? What about its range of applicability?</div><div class="su-service-content su-clearfix" style="padding-left:46px">
<div class='dropshadowboxes-container dropshadowboxes-right ' style='width:auto;'>
                            <div class='dropshadowboxes-drop-shadow dropshadowboxes-rounded-corners dropshadowboxes-outside-shadow dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved-horizontal-2 dropshadowboxes-effect-default' style=' border: 1px solid #dddddd; height:; background-color:#ffffff;    '>
                            
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/normal_ams_borro.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-2386 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/normal_ams_borro-257x300.jpg" alt="Non-Euclidean Geometry" width="257" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/normal_ams_borro-257x300.jpg 257w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/normal_ams_borro.jpg 400w" sizes="(max-width: 257px) 100vw, 257px" /></a></p>

                            </div>
                        </div>
<p>GA achieves the unification of many domains like multilinear algebra, multivariable analysis, conformal geometry, Lie group and Lie algebras, projective geometry, quantum mechanics and general relativity. GA allows:</p>
<ul>
<li>Extending and completing algebraic operations on vectors and multi-vectors.</li>
<li>Providing unified concepts for geometry and algebra.</li>
<li>Providing explicit interpretation of geometric entities and operations on them in arbitrary dimensions with Euclidean and pseudo-Euclidean metrics.</li>
<li>Acting as an advanced formalism for rotations and in general Lie groups in arbitrary dimensions.</li>
<li>Acting as a metalanguage for high-level reasoning.</li>
</ul>
<p>Because of these features, Geometric Algebra has a wide range of applications: graphics engineering, signal and image processing, computer vision, neural networks and quantum computing, machine learning, and robotics.</p>
</div></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="su-service"><div class="su-service-title" style="padding-left:46px;min-height:32px;line-height:32px"><i class="fa fa-comments-o" style="font-size:32px;color:#333"></i> Tell us about the recent developments of applying GA in your research activities.</div><div class="su-service-content su-clearfix" style="padding-left:46px">
<div class='dropshadowboxes-container dropshadowboxes-right ' style='width:auto;'>
                            <div class='dropshadowboxes-drop-shadow dropshadowboxes-rounded-corners dropshadowboxes-outside-shadow dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved-horizontal-2 dropshadowboxes-effect-default' style=' border: 1px solid #dddddd; height:; background-color:#ffffff;    '>
                            
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/jetson-tk1.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-2382 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/jetson-tk1-300x171.png" alt="jetson-tk1" width="300" height="171" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/jetson-tk1-300x171.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/jetson-tk1.png 350w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>

                            </div>
                        </div>
<p>Recent achievements in geometric accelerators using packets like Versor (P. Colapinto) or Gaalop (Geometric Algebra Algorithms Optimizer, D. Hildenbrand) allow us with FPGA or NVidia to accelerate computations even more. In my lab, we develop and build intelligent machines like in medical robotics or humanoids. The development of GA algorithms follows: algorithmic modeling, using our own C++ programs or Versor, then simply the algorithms with Maple or Gaalop and accelerate them with either FPFGA or Nvidia. The results are quite impressive for real time applications and the visualization of computing in higher dimensions which in turn helps us to gain insight and achieve correctness in the prove of theorems and improve the performance of our algorithms. We are working now to develop in the next 3 years a single small chip for geometric computing using GA with a power superior as the <a href="http://www.nvidia.com/object/jetson-tk1-embedded-dev-kit.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jetson TK1 Nvidia</a> card.</p>
</div></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="su-service"><div class="su-service-title" style="padding-left:46px;min-height:32px;line-height:32px"><i class="fa fa-comments-o" style="font-size:32px;color:#333"></i> In your opinion, are there any relations between Neural Learning and Geometric Learning? How do you use GA as a tool for exploring such relations?</div><div class="su-service-content su-clearfix" style="padding-left:46px">
<div class='dropshadowboxes-container dropshadowboxes-right ' style='width:auto;'>
                            <div class='dropshadowboxes-drop-shadow dropshadowboxes-rounded-corners dropshadowboxes-outside-shadow dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved-horizontal-2 dropshadowboxes-effect-default' style=' border: 1px solid #dddddd; height:; background-color:#ffffff;    '>
                            
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/neurons-1739997_640.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-2383 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/neurons-1739997_640-300x214.jpg" alt="Neurons" width="300" height="214" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/neurons-1739997_640-300x214.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/neurons-1739997_640.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>

                            </div>
                        </div>
<p>The tricky question is what should be a true geometric learning? We started by generalizing the McCulloch-Pitts neuron replacing its inner product via the geometric product, so the neural network weights are then multivectors and the learning rules are formulated using the gradient of multivectors as well. Our networks for classification via their kernels map the data using multivectors to a direct product of Hilbert spaces to separate multivector clusters, this helps a lot to find optimal hyperplanes. We have worked on geometric neural computing since 1995, in fact, we have generalized in GA most of the neural networks: i.e. multivector valued [SOM, NeuralGAS, MLP, ART], Clifford SVM and Quaternion Spike neural Network, currently we are developing the quaternion quantum Neural Network. This year we are also focusing on geometric high-order recurrent Neural Networks.</p>
</div></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="su-service"><div class="su-service-title" style="padding-left:46px;min-height:32px;line-height:32px"><i class="fa fa-comments-o" style="font-size:32px;color:#333"></i> Tell us about your books describing your valuable work and experience with GA, and the new books you are currently preparing.</div><div class="su-service-content su-clearfix" style="padding-left:46px">
<div class='dropshadowboxes-container dropshadowboxes-right ' style='width:auto;'>
                            <div class='dropshadowboxes-drop-shadow dropshadowboxes-rounded-corners dropshadowboxes-outside-shadow dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved-horizontal-2 dropshadowboxes-effect-default' style=' border: 1px solid #dddddd; height:; background-color:#ffffff;    '>
                            
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Geometric-Computing-Book.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-2384 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Geometric-Computing-Book-199x300.jpg" alt="Geometric Computing Book" width="199" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Geometric-Computing-Book-199x300.jpg 199w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Geometric-Computing-Book.jpg 331w" sizes="(max-width: 199px) 100vw, 199px" /></a></p>

                            </div>
                        </div>
<p>I have been teaching since 1997 using the material of my work which was then published in two books:</p>
<ul>
<li>Geometric Computing for Perception Action Systems. Eduardo Bayro-Corrochano, Springer-Verlag, April 2001.</li>
<li>Geometric Computing: for Wavelet Transforms, Robot Vision, Learning, Control, and Action. Eduardo Bayro-Corrochano, Springer-Verlag, 2010.</li>
</ul>
<p>I am preparing a more comprehensive series in three volumes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Vol. I: GA for computer vision and machine learning,</li>
<li>Vol. II: GA for Robotics,</li>
<li>Vol. III: GA for Signal Processing, Filtering, Transforms and Quantum Computing.</li>
</ul>
<p>These three volumes are based on my first two books, of course, while including new exciting results. My books generally differ from many the current books on GA applications because my books cover computer vision, graphics engineering, neural networks, machine learning, robotics, integral transforms, and ultimately the endeavor of building intelligent machines with GA; they present real applications. The other books are more related to the foundations of GA and its restricted use to the develop algorithms in computer science and its sub-fields like computer graphics. That is why my continuous work during all these years is helping to be able to prepare these new three volumes, which I believe will certainly establish the true geometric computing for the future development of intelligent machines.</p>
</div></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="su-service"><div class="su-service-title" style="padding-left:46px;min-height:32px;line-height:32px"><i class="fa fa-comments-o" style="font-size:32px;color:#333"></i> Tell us about your practical experience teaching applied Geometric Algebra. How do you overcome the challenges you face while using GA in teaching?</div><div class="su-service-content su-clearfix" style="padding-left:46px">
<div class='dropshadowboxes-container dropshadowboxes-right ' style='width:auto;'>
                            <div class='dropshadowboxes-drop-shadow dropshadowboxes-rounded-corners dropshadowboxes-outside-shadow dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved dropshadowboxes-curved-horizontal-2 dropshadowboxes-effect-default' style=' border: 1px solid #dddddd; height:; background-color:#ffffff;    '>
                            
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/robocup-400467_640.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-2387 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/robocup-400467_640-300x198.jpg" alt="Robocup" width="300" height="198" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/robocup-400467_640-300x198.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/robocup-400467_640.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>

                            </div>
                        </div>
<p>I call for studying and applying GA for future cybernetics in my lectures at different universities in Europe, North America (MIT) and Latin America. I have students with different backgrounds as in physics, mathematics, or engineering; some well prepared for some topics and less for others, so I start as in a fractal approach for conveying knowledge:</p>
<ul>
<li>We study 2D- and 3D-GA to become acquainted with the formulation of the geometric primitives and the use of different Clifford operations.</li>
<li>Then we model the kinematics of points, lines and planes particularly to understand well screw theory and differential kinematics.</li>
<li>Then I explain the basic of differential geometry like the Geometric Laplace-Beltrami Operator for applications in Euclidean and pseudo-Euclidean spaces.</li>
<li>We study in depth Lie Groups and Lie algebras using spinors and versors for Euclidean, Affine, and 2D and 3D projective geometry.</li>
<li>Then I explain projective geometry using Euclidean and Minkowski metrics for the projective plane and spaces and extensions of the projective space in R(3,3).</li>
</ul>
<p>In this manner, the students have learned the most important ingredients to move the Conformal Geometric Algebra and high dimensional geometric algebras like G(6,3) and G(8,2). Thanks to our optimized routines for GA in C++ (with NVidia) and Maple (using the Clifford 14.0 package of R. Ablamowicz), we can prove theorems and develop real-time algorithms for intelligent machines.</p>
</div></div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2017/01/27/ga-cybernetics/">Cybernetics with Transdisciplinary Geometric Algebra</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/index.php/2017/01/27/ga-cybernetics/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
