<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>GA History &#8211; Geometric Algebra Explorer</title>
	<atom:link href="/index.php/category/geometric-algebra/ga-history/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Voyaging the Computational Universe with Geometric Algebra</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 06:57:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.8.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/cropped-GAExplorer-Icon-150x150.jpg</url>
	<title>GA History &#8211; Geometric Algebra Explorer</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Founders of Geometric Calculus</title>
		<link>/index.php/2017/01/17/founding-geometric-calculus/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 17:21:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ahmad Eid]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[GA History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometric Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interview]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Clifford Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Differential Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Garret Sobczyk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Foundations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometric Calculus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linear Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mathematics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Prof. David Hestenes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://gacomputing.info/?p=2331</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Foundations of modern Geometric Algebra and Geometric Calculus were laid down by Prof. David Hestenes and Dr. Garret Sobczyk 50 years ago. In this post, I interview Dr. Garret Sobczyk who tells us about his fascinating life journey with Prof. Hestenes. Their journey eventually inspired many researchers to follow their lead in learning, developing, and applying Geometric Algebra and Geometric Calculus to many fields of science.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2017/01/17/founding-geometric-calculus/">Founders of Geometric Calculus</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/bridge-246913_1280.jpg"><img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2340" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/bridge-246913_1280-1024x682.jpg" alt="Bridge" width="1024" height="682" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/bridge-246913_1280-1024x682.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/bridge-246913_1280-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/bridge-246913_1280-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/bridge-246913_1280.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></p>
<blockquote><p>Our minds are finite, and yet even in those circumstances of finitude, we are surrounded by possibilities that are infinite, and the purpose of human life is to grasp as much as we can out of that infinitude. &#8212; Alfred North Whitehead</p></blockquote>
<span class="dropcap">F</span>oundations of modern Geometric Algebra and Geometric Calculus were laid down by Prof. David Hestenes and Dr. Garret Sobczyk 50 years ago. In this post, I interview Dr. Garret Sobczyk who tells us about his fascinating life journey with Prof. Hestenes. Their journey eventually inspired many researchers to follow their lead in learning, developing, and applying Geometric Algebra and Geometric Calculus to many fields of science.</p>
<hr />
<p><strong>Dr. Garret Sobczyk</strong></p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/me.png"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-2338" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/me.png" alt="Dr. Garret Sobczyk" width="230" height="384" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/me.png 230w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/me-180x300.png 180w" sizes="(max-width: 230px) 100vw, 230px" /></a>Dr. Garret Sobczyk is Emeritus Professor of Mathematics, Universidad de las Americas-Puebla, Mexico. Dr. Sobczyk first learned about Clifford geometric algebras from Prof. David Hestenes as a graduate student in mathematics at Arizona State University in 1966. He became convinced early on that geometric algebra is rightly considered to be the completion of the real number system to include the concept of direction. He obtained his Ph.D. in mathematics in 1971 and eagerly set forth to convince the world. This quest led him to spend 5 years in Poland as a postdoctoral student at the Institute of Theoretical Physics in Wroclaw, before returning to the United States in 1983. He coauthored with Prof. David Hestenes the book, “Clifford Algebra to Geometric Calculus: A Unified Language for Mathematics and Physics”, published in 1985. He held several academic positions in the United States and Mexico, before settling with his Polish wife Wanda at the Universidad de Las Americas in Cholula, Mexico in 1993. He has published over 30 articles exploring the close relationships between geometric algebra and linear and multilinear algebra and other topics and is a member of Sistema Nacional de Investigadores de Mexico.</p>
<hr />
<h3>The Fellowship of Founders</h3>
<p><span style="color: #003366;"><strong>Tell us about your early work with Dr. David Hestenes. What made you decide to work with him on the development of Geometric Algebra (GA) and Geometric Calculus (GC)?</strong></span></p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/World-Line.jpg"><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-2345" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/World-Line-293x300.jpg" alt="World-Line" width="293" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/World-Line-293x300.jpg 293w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/World-Line.jpg 450w" sizes="(max-width: 293px) 100vw, 293px" /></a>Thank you, Ahmad, for giving me the opportunity to share with you some of my early memories as a graduate student at Arizona State University (ASU) working in geometric algebra.</p>
<p>It was in 1965 when I had just completed my Master’s Degree in Mathematics and was looking for direction to continue my studies for a Ph.D. that I decided to explore possibilities in mathematical physics. Professor David Hestenes, a new professor at ASU, was offering a course in electrodynamics that caught my attention. On the first day of class, he began by introducing Geometric Algebra (GA) and the geometric product of vectors. I was amazed that I had never heard of the concept of a bivector as a directed area, or of the geometric product of vectors. It was over the course of that year that I decided that I wanted to dedicate my efforts for my Ph.D. into developing GA as a basic language in mathematics that I believed it to be then, and still do now a half a century later!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #003366;"><strong>I suspect it wasn&#8217;t easy for you to learn and apply Geometric Algebra back then. What did you do?</strong></span></p>
<p>Indeed, I did not have an easy beginning. David, at first suggested topics in Kellogg’s Potential Theory and Harmonic Analysis or generalizing Elliptic Functions. All of these were very good topics which have been extensively developed by European groups such as the Delanghe-Sommen group in Belgium, and others, but I was unable to make any real progress in these areas. It was at this point, almost in desperation, that I started to look at very basic ideas in linear algebra and differential geometry. Surely, if GA was indeed a basic language (over the continual skepticism of my Father; then a Professor of Mathematics at Clemson University, with a Ph.D. from Princeton University when he was a 23 year old), GA should offer new insights in these basic fields. Even to this day, most mathematicians believe that trying to reformulate differential geometry in GA is only putting old wine in new bottles.</p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Killing-vector-s2.jpg"><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-2346" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Killing-vector-s2-300x240.jpg" alt="Killing-vector-s2" width="300" height="240" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Killing-vector-s2-300x240.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Killing-vector-s2.jpg 512w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a>I undertook a serious study of linear and multilinear algebra out of books by Gel’fand, Shilov, and Greub, and basic differential geometry. I was also greatly influenced by books such as “Science Awakening” by van der Waerden, Tobias Dantzig’s book, “Number The Language of Science”, Wilder’s “Evolution of Mathematical Concepts”, and Michael Crowe’s “History of Vector Analysis”. I considered my first “breakthrough” in linear algebra to be when I discovered how to derive the Cayley-Hamilton theorem in GA by first looking at the simplest 2-dimensional case. I spent a great deal of time developing the notion of the vector and simplicial derivatives in GA as a basic tool in linear algebra. Almost all of my 1971 Ph.D. thesis consisted of a systematic development of the general simplicial derivative as a basic tool in linear algebra.</p>
<p>It was only toward the end of my thesis that I was able to start making progress in laying down the basic ideas of Riemannian Curvature in differential geometry, material which David and I developed further over a period of four years afterwards, and would later make up the heart of our book “Clifford Algebra to Geometric Calculus: A Unified Language for Mathematics and Physics”, which wasn’t published until a decade later in 1984.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3>Facing the Real World</h3>
<p><span style="color: #003366;"><strong>Tell us about your steps after finishing your Ph.D. Were you able to easily get recognition for your groundbreaking work with Prof. Hestenes?</strong></span></p>
<p>After finishing my Ph.D. at ASU in 1971, I was unsuccessful in obtaining any academic position. The first academic job crunch was on and for every teaching position at a University or College there were hundreds of applicants, and Mathematics Departments to which I applied were suspicious of me working in an unknown area and with a young theoretical physicist as my thesis adviser. Fortunately, ASU kept me on for an additional year as a Visiting Assistant Professor, which gave us the chance to continue working closely together in developing GA. At first, we planned on publishing four papers, which later formed the basis of our book. The following year, I was still unsuccessful in obtaining any academic position.</p>
<p>At first, I visited a number of American University Mathematics Departments with well-known people in differential geometry, but none were interested in GA or in my work. I also realized that my basic knowledge of differential geometry was insufficient to convince anyone of any need to reformulate it in a new language. In 1973, I visited European Universities in different countries and was invited to give a number of talks about GA, but it was only in Poland that I was offered a Research Fellowship with the Polish Academy of Sciences, which allowed me to continue to develop basic tools in GA that eventually went into our book CA to GC in 1984. I returned to Poland in 1976 with a Postdoctoral Research Grant from Stoney Brook University in NY, allowing me to continue my work with new colleagues at the Institute of Theoretical Physics in Wroclaw until 1980.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #003366;"><strong>Were you able to use your knowledge of GA in teaching? How did you manage that in the following years?</strong></span></p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/CA2GC.jpg"><img class="alignright wp-image-2347 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/CA2GC-200x300.jpg" alt="Clifford Algebra to Geometric Calculus" width="200" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/CA2GC-200x300.jpg 200w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/CA2GC.jpg 333w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></a>I enjoyed two academic appointments as an Assistant and Associate professor of Mathematics at Spring Hill College, Mobile, Ala., and at Lander College, Greenwood, SC in the 1980’s, and began developing material to teach undergraduate students GA and calculus. Finally, in 1984, our book CA to GC was published, which provided a needed boost to my career, but even to this day, the book has been largely ignored by the majority of the Mathematics Community.</p>
<p>It was difficult to teach GA and GC to students at this level because it usually takes a full year to get students comfortable with GA, and an undergraduate student is expected to master many other subjects as well. As my Finnish friend and colleague, the late Professor Pertti Lounesto remarked, about the best you can do is “smuggled it in” under the guise of closely related material, such as vector analysis and differential forms.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #003366;"><strong>We can see how difficult your journey had been following your ideas. Did the situation get better at a later stage?</strong></span></p>
<p>Fortunately, during the 1990’s and into the new century, Professor Hestenes was successful at drawing considerable new interest to the area among computer scientists and engineers, by utilizing GA in an innovative way to lay down the foundations of projective and conformal geometries.</p>
<p>In 1990 I accepted a very promising offer by Professor Jaime Keller of the Universidad Nacional Autonoma de Mexico to work with him as Assistant Editor of the new International Journal that he was creating, “Advances in Applied Clifford Algebras”, with the hope of both consolidating this growing field of research, and promoting wider international recognition. It was an exciting two years of growth, and of discovering the exotic culture of modern Mexico, alongside the ancient Mayan civilization that may well have been among the earliest to invent the concept of the number zero, and a base 20 type number system.</p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/bookcover1.jpg"><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-2359" src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/bookcover1-200x300.jpg" alt="bookcover1" width="200" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/bookcover1-200x300.jpg 200w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/bookcover1-768x1154.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/bookcover1-681x1024.jpg 681w, /wp-content/uploads/2017/01/bookcover1.jpg 827w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></a>At the Universidad de Las Americas &#8211; Puebla, over the years 1993 &#8211; present, I continued to develop material for teaching GA at the undergraduate level, with an emphasis on basic linear algebra and elementary differential geometry, leading to the publication of my book, “New Foundations in Mathematics: The Geometric Concept of Number”, Birkhauser-Springer 2013. In this book, I emphasize the development of linear algebra and basic ideas of differential geometry in terms of GA, including the basic concept of the spectral basis. The idea of a spectral basis is what really connects the ideas of a geometric algebra to the traditional approaches to linear algebra and ubiquitous matrices. When GA is properly understood as providing a geometric basis for matrices, the well-established consistency of matrix algebra, in turn, proves the mathematical soundness of GA, without the need to go into more complicated arguments involving tensor analysis and the higher level abstract concepts of advanced mathematics. Also, in the book, I lay down preliminary material on application of the idea of a spectral basis in basic ideas in numerical analysis, such as Hermite interpolation and rational approximation.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3>Present and Future</h3>
<p><span style="color: #003366;"><strong>How do you see the current state of GA and GC among researchers?</strong></span></p>
<p>Clifford analysis, as developed by various groups, both in the United States and Europe enjoys recognition as a respectable area of research in advanced mathematics. In addition to the work of Professor Hestenes, Professor Baylis in Canada, other researchers in Mexico, China and around the World, geometric algebra has enjoyed increasing success among theoretical physicists in relativity and quantum mechanics. Clifford algebra is also used by some of the top theoretical physicists at prestigious universities in string theory and its generalizations. As you know, it has also attracted significant and growing attention in the computer science and engineering communities.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #003366;"><strong>What are your expectations of the future of GA and GC in teaching? What kind of research do you believe should be conducted to effectively relate GA and GC to mainstream mathematics and applications?</strong></span></p>
<p>I have no easy answer to this question. One of the main obstacles to teaching GA is the lack of powerful computer software to aid and check abstract hand calculations, although many new software products are becoming available. Two software packages that I have found to be useful in my teaching and research is the original stand-alone early numerical software package “CLICAL” by Lounesto, and the Mexican developed Mathematica Package [cliffordt.nb] 2007, by G. Aragon-Camarasa, J.L. Aragon, and M.A. Rodriguez. There are quite are a number of recent attempts to introduce GA at the undergraduate level that I am aware of. However, GA is still hardly recognized at all at the undergraduate level, as I firmly believe that it should be. I believe that it is the natural completion of the concept of number to include the concept of direction, and it should be taught that way down into the high school level. It is in this area that I have concentrated my own efforts. There is much left to be done to correctly lay down the foundations, even at a fundamental level, in order to facilitate progress at progressively more advanced levels in mathematics, physics, computer science, and engineering, including diverse areas such as quantum computing, robotics, the structure Lie groups and Lie Algebras, and artificial intelligence. The future lies in the hands of the younger generations.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2017/01/17/founding-geometric-calculus/">Founders of Geometric Calculus</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Functional History of Numbers (3 of 3)</title>
		<link>/index.php/2015/08/14/history-of-numbers3/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2015 14:00:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ahmad Eid]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[GA History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Numbers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://gacomputing.info/?p=395</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>There are 3 kinds of science: the experimental, the theoretical, and the simulated. Over the whole history of human discovery, experimental scientific activities guided, and in many times surprised, the human imagination's search to understand and control the observable universe. After sometime human knowledge seekers used the language of mathematics to create simplified, consistent theoretical models for the complex data and patterns they experimentally observe; abstractions were now put on paper. The third kind of scientific activity only appeared recently, about 75 years ago, when the first electronic computers were made; effectively creating the "human computational universe" and upgrading our scientific methods to a whole new level. The idea of this third kind of science is to computationally and visually investigate our theoretical mathematical models encoded as computer programs executed on various sets of inputs to get new patterns, ideas, and "virtual" discoveries that can be verified experimentally later or at least may provide grounds for new abstractions, theories, and practical applications. This third kind of science, the science and art of computer simulations, is now unavoidable in all scientific research and education activities. All this is made possible by using only the two numbers 1 and 0; a.k.a True and False.<br />
After our journey with classic numbers in part one and geometric numbers in part two, in this final part of our functional history of numbers, we will take a look at a third kind of numbers: the computational numbers.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2015/08/14/history-of-numbers3/">A Functional History of Numbers (3 of 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_396" style="width: 730px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Solenoid-large.jpg"><img class="wp-image-396 size-large" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Solenoid-large-1024x768.jpg" alt="Solenoid-large" width="720" height="540" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Solenoid-large.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Solenoid-large-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Solenoid-large-768x576.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 720px) 100vw, 720px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Magnetic Field Simulation. (<a href="https://nylander.wordpress.com/2006/05/17/magnetic-field-of-a-solenoid/">Source</a>)</p></div>
<blockquote><p>Science is what we understand well enough to explain to a computer. Art is everything else we do. &#8212; Donald Knuth.</p></blockquote>
<span class="dropcap">T</span>here are 3 kinds of science: the experimental, the theoretical, and the simulated<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-1' id='enref-395-1' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>1</a></sup>. Over the whole history of human discovery experimental scientific activities guided, and in many times surprised, the human imagination&#8217;s search to understand and control the observable universe. After sometime human knowledge seekers used the language of mathematics to create simplified, consistent theoretical models for the complex data and patterns they experimentally observe; abstractions were now put on paper. The third kind of scientific activity only appeared recently, about 75 years ago, when the first electronic computers were made; effectively creating the &#8220;human computational universe&#8221; and upgrading our scientific methods to a whole new level. The idea of this third kind of science is to computationally and visually investigate our theoretical mathematical models encoded as computer programs executed on various sets of inputs to get new patterns, ideas, and &#8220;virtual&#8221; discoveries that can be verified experimentally later or at least may provide grounds for new abstractions, theories, and practical applications. This third kind of science, the science and art of computer simulations, is now unavoidable in all scientific research and education activities. All this is made possible by using only the two numbers <strong>1</strong> and <strong>0;</strong> a.k.a <strong>True</strong> and <strong>False</strong>.</p>
<p>After our journey with classic numbers in <a href="/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/">part one</a> and geometric numbers in <a href="/index.php/2015/08/07/history-of-numbers2/">part two</a>, in this final part of our functional history of numbers, we will take a look at a third kind of numbers: the computational numbers.</p>
<h3>True or False: From Laws of Thought to Switching Algebra</h3>
<blockquote><p>It appeared to me that, although Logic might be viewed with reference to the idea of quantity, it had also another and a deeper system of relations. If it was lawful to regard it from without, as connecting itself through the medium of Number with the intuitions of Space and Time, it was lawful also to regard it from within, as based upon facts of another order which have their abode in the constitution of the Mind. &#8212; George Boole, The Mathematical Analysis of Logic.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/boole/">George Boole</a>, famous for his knowledge, kindness, and total lack of egoism was an English mathematician who died from bad cold, at the age of 49, resulting from walking from his house to his College under heavy rain and lecturing in wet clothes. Boole&#8217;s greatest achievement was to create an algebra of logic: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boolean_algebra_(structure)">Boolean algebra</a>. Boole had minimal formal education due to the poverty of his family. His fellow students considered him to be something of a genius. His early training in languages<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-2' id='enref-395-2' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>2</a></sup> had its share among the inﬂuences which led to the construction of Boole’s logic: he built his logic in the same way he felt languages were built<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-3' id='enref-395-3' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>3</a></sup>. Boole’s thinking may have been spurred on by a heated controversy raging at the time between two formidable academics working in this area<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-4' id='enref-395-4' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>4</a></sup>. They were the British mathematician and logician Augustus De Morgan and the Scottish philosopher and metaphysician Sir William Hamilton; the creator of quaternions. Boole came up with an ingenious formulation that synthesized the approaches of both De Morgan and Hamilton. Indeed De Morgan praised Boole’s work on logic saying:</p>
<blockquote><p>Boole&#8217;s system of logic is but one of many proofs of genius and patience combined &#8230; That the symbolic processes of algebra, invented as tools of numerical calculation, should be competent to express every act of thought, and to furnish the grammar and dictionary of an all-containing system of logic, would not have been believed until it was proved<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-5' id='enref-395-5' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>5</a></sup>.</p></blockquote>
<p>Boole discussed, in the Introduction of his book &#8220;The Mathematical Analysis of Logic&#8221;, the issue of the relevance of symbols in scientiﬁc expositions. His aim was probably to correct Hamilton’s opinion that the symbolization of mathematics could lead to the destruction of the reﬂective powers of students of that discipline. He contended that if symbols are used with full understanding of the laws which render them useful, “an intellectual discipline of high order is provided”. In 1854 Boole published his book &#8220;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Laws_of_Thought">The Laws of Thought</a>&#8220;. Boole’s goals were “to go under, over, and beyond” Aristotle’s logic by providing it with mathematical foundations involving equations; extending the class of problems it could treat from assessing validity to solving equations, and expanding the range of applications it could handle (e.g. from propositions having only two terms to those having arbitrarily many).</p>
<div id="attachment_496" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Baops.png"><img class="wp-image-496" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Baops.png" alt="Baops" width="300" height="226" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Baops.png 787w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Baops-300x226.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Baops-768x579.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Switching Algebra by Shannon is based on Boolean Algebra (<a href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Digital_Circuits/Logic_Operations">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Boole#20th-century_development">Boole&#8217;s work</a> and that of later logicians initially appeared to have no engineering uses. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claude_Shannon">Claude Shannon</a> attended a philosophy class at the University of Michigan which introduced him to Boole&#8217;s studies. Shannon recognized that Boole&#8217;s work could form the basis of mechanisms and processes in the real world and that it was therefore highly relevant. In 1937 Shannon went on to write his <a href="http://dspace.mit.edu/handle/1721.1/11173">master&#8217;s thesis</a>:&#8221;A symbolic analysis of relay and switching circuits&#8221;, at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, in which he showed how Boolean algebra could optimize the design of systems of electromechanical relays then used in telephone routing switches. He also proved that circuits with relays could solve Boolean algebra problems; a great milestone in the development of Switching Theory. Andrew Emerson in an <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2001/mar/08/obituaries.news">article</a> in The Guardian states:</p>
<blockquote><p>That dissertation has since been hailed as one of the most significant master&#8217;s theses of the 20th century. To all intents and purposes, its use of binary code and Boolean algebra paved the way for the digital circuitry that is crucial to the operation of modern computers and telecommunications equipment.</p></blockquote>
<p>Employing the properties of electrical switches to process logic is the basic concept that underlies all modern electronic digital computers. Victor Shestakov at Moscow State University proposed a theory of electric switches based on Boolean logic even earlier than Claude Shannon in 1935. But the first publication of Shestakov&#8217;s result took place only in 1941 in Russian<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-6' id='enref-395-6' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>6</a></sup>. Hence Boolean algebra became the foundation of practical digital circuit design; and Boole, via Shannon and Shestakov, provided the theoretical grounding for the Digital Age.</p>
<h3>The Three of Balance</h3>
<blockquote><p>Perhaps the prettiest number system of all, is the balanced ternary notation &#8230; and perhaps the symmetric properties and simple arithmetic of this number system will prove to be quite important someday; when the &#8220;flip-flop&#8221; is replaced by a &#8220;flip-flap-flop&#8221;. &#8212; Donald E. Knuth, The Art of Computer Programming Volume 2.</p></blockquote>
<p>The reason behind the exclusive use of binary numbers in computing is purely physical as the electronic transistors of computers only have 2 stable states. All computer applications require testing conditions and taking actions accordingly through the ubiquitous If-Then statement. Life isn&#8217;t binary, though; you must occasionally say &#8220;I don&#8217;t know the answer&#8221; to be human. We actually need at least 3 states for our decision-making models: True, False, and Unknown. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Null_(SQL)">symbol &#8220;NULL&#8221;</a> in modern database management systems is one shining example of needing the unknown in modern computing.</p>
<div id="attachment_486" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Bachet-weight-problem.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-486" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Bachet-weight-problem-300x131.png" alt="Bachet-weight-problem" width="300" height="131" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Bachet-weight-problem-300x131.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Bachet-weight-problem-768x335.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Bachet-weight-problem.png 902w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Bachet&#8217;s Problem: as few weights to weigh them all (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1010.5486">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>Mathematically, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ternary_computer">ternary</a> (i.e. base 3) number system is more efficient than a binary system in many ways; it offers <a href="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/extras/bph-publications/AmSci-2001-11-Hayes-ternary.pdf">the most economical way</a> of representing integers among all number systems. A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balanced_ternary">balanced ternary</a> number system is based on the numbers (-1, 0, and 1) instead of (0, 1, and 2). This number system first appeared in the 18th century and was used for solving the Bachet’s Weights Problem attributed to Bachet in the early 17th century, but actually dating back all the way to Fibonacci or earlier<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-7' id='enref-395-7' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>7</a></sup>, as one of the first problems of integer partitions:</p>
<blockquote><p>What is the least number of pound weights that can be used on a scale pan to weigh any integral number of pounds from 1 to 40 inclusive, if the weights can be placed in either of the scale pans?</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_380" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/fowlerdiagram.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-380" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/fowlerdiagram-300x150.jpg" alt="A model of the ternary calculating machine of Thomas Fowler" width="300" height="150" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/fowlerdiagram-300x150.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/fowlerdiagram.jpg 621w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">A model of the ternary calculating machine of Thomas Fowler. See <a href="http://www.mortati.com/glusker/fowler/about.htm">here</a> for more details.</p></div>
<p>The first true appearance of “pure” balanced ternary notation was in an article by Léon Lalanne in 1840, who was a designer of mechanical devices for arithmetic. <a href="http://www.mortati.com/glusker/fowler/fowlerbio.htm">Thomas Fowler</a> independently invented and constructed a balanced ternary calculator at about the same time. The balanced ternary number system was mentioned only rarely for the next 100 years, until the development of the first electronic computers at the Moore School of Electrical Engineering in 1945–1946; at that time it was given serious consideration as a possible replacement for the decimal system. The complexity of arithmetic circuitry for balanced ternary arithmetic is not much greater than it is for the binary system, and a given number requires only 63% as many digit positions for its representation<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-8' id='enref-395-8' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>8</a></sup>. An implementation of this uncommonly used but beautiful symmetric number system in several computer languages can be found in <a href="http://rosettacode.org/wiki/Balanced_ternary">this Rosetta Code article</a>. A Demonstration of the weighting problem can be found in <a href="http://demonstrations.wolfram.com/BalancedTernaryNotation/">this Wolfram demonstration</a>.</p>
<p>Perhaps someday ternary computers would replace our binary ones as described by Douglas W. Jones who wrote <a href="http://homepage.cs.uiowa.edu/~jones/ternary/">The Ternary Manifesto</a>. Some researchers even began to suggest hardware implementations of this number system; for example, a system based on the <a href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/679270/?reload=true&amp;arnumber=679270">Josephson junction</a>, and another system based on a <a href="http://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1238/Physica.Topical.118a00098/meta;jsessionid=70C4C8ABF84CB6757494D0680027D880.c5.iopscience.cld.iop.org">ternary optical computer architecture</a>. Maybe we will see the &#8220;flip-flap-flop&#8221; in the near future after all.</p>
<h3>The Curious Case of Floating Points</h3>
<blockquote><p>There are 10 types of people in this world: those who understand binary and those who don&#8217;t. &#8212; Author Unknown.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_478" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/IEEE-754-ENGLISH.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-478" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/IEEE-754-ENGLISH-300x120.jpg" alt="IEEE-754-ENGLISH" width="300" height="120" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/IEEE-754-ENGLISH-300x120.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/IEEE-754-ENGLISH-768x306.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/IEEE-754-ENGLISH-1024x408.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/IEEE-754-ENGLISH.jpg 1586w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The IEEE-754 Standard for Floating-Point Numbers (<a href="http://www.puntoflotante.net/FLOATING-POINT-FORMAT-IEEE-754.htm">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>All the geometric number systems we talked about earlier (the complex numbers, quaternions, vectors, and multivectors) can be represented inside a computer as data structures consisting of real number components. The problem is that most real numbers are impossible to accurately represent inside our computationally limited space, in time and storage, so we have to approximate. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floating_point">floating-point numbers</a> are the standard system for storing and manipulating approximations of real numbers in modern computers. The dedicated circuitry inside computers ensure fast floating-point based computations; some even rely on the GPU for <a href="http://gpgpu.org/">accelerating parallel computations</a>. As useful as they are, floating-point numbers have many <a href="http://docs.oracle.com/cd/E19957-01/806-3568/ncg_goldberg.html">bad mathematical properties</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li>They are only a subset of rational numbers; all irrationals are impossible to represent as they have infinite decimals.</li>
<li>Many common rational decimal numbers we intuitively use can only be represented in binary as recurring decimals. For example, the number (0.1) in decimal is (0.0 0011 0011 0011 0011 0011 &#8230;) in binary; leading also to an approximate representation for such simple decimals!</li>
<li>Floating point numbers are not closed under any of the basic operations of addition, subtraction, multiplication or division; a numerical recipe for computational disaster under chaos theory!</li>
<li>They don&#8217;t obey the important property of associativity: a+(b+c) is not always equal to (a+b)+c for floating point numbers a,b,c. The same problem is present in associativity of multiplication and distributivity of multiplication over addition.</li>
<li>They are not uniformly distributed on the real number line. This is a serious problem for geometric modeling applications; applying a transformation on an object near the origin is different than applying the same transformation to the same object far from the origin.</li>
<li>They have a limited range, accuracy, and precision for many practical applications.</li>
<li>Two floating-point numbers in different format must be scaled before being added together. In other words, the binary points must be aligned before the addition can be performed resulting in possible loss of accuracy.</li>
<li>Because of all of the above, equality and ordering tests are sometimes problematic; we must use tolerances and intervals instead of direct equality tests in many applications.</li>
</ul>
<div id="attachment_384" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/strange_attractors-0086.jpg.jpeg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-384" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/strange_attractors-0086.jpg-300x297.jpeg" alt="Chaos Theory" width="300" height="297" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/strange_attractors-0086.jpg-300x297.jpeg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/strange_attractors-0086.jpg-150x150.jpeg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/strange_attractors-0086.jpg.jpeg 440w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">If not careful, floating point errors combined with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaos_theory">chaos theory</a> can destroy simulation results.</p></div>
<p>All these problems make direct implementation of mathematical models difficult for many applications. We need to add an additional &#8220;layer of protection&#8221; to ensure the model will work for an acceptable range of inputs just to avoid the bad effects of floating-point arithmetic<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-9' id='enref-395-9' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>9</a></sup>. There exist some approaches to reduce the bad effects of these numbers in computing like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decimal_floating_point">decimal floating-point</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fixed-point_arithmetic#Precision_loss_and_overflow">fixed-point arithmetic,</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P-adic_number">p-adic arithmetic</a>. One other radically different solution is avoiding irrationals in our models from the start by only using rational numbers<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-10' id='enref-395-10' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>10</a></sup>; something that would definitely please the ancient Greeks. This approach requires us to create a library for &#8220;big integers&#8221; and base a rational numbers library on it. Another approach, common in financial applications, is to use very small units of measurement, like cents for example, and do all computations using integers; then do a final step of simple division when showing the results after accurately computing them. In any case, the floating-point binary number system will not go away anytime soon; we must take care when coding our geometric models not to allow these strange numbers to destroy the beauty of our geometry.</p>
<h3>The Symbolic Meaning of Trees</h3>
<blockquote><p>I had a very selfish reason for building Mathematica. I wanted to use it myself, a bit like Galileo got to use his telescope four hundred years ago. But I wanted to look, not at the astronomical universe, but at the computational universe. &#8212; Stephen Wolfram.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_510" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/MemoryAddressContent.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-510" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/MemoryAddressContent-300x228.png" alt="MemoryAddressContent" width="300" height="228" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/MemoryAddressContent-300x228.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/MemoryAddressContent.png 661w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Pointers and Strings are the bases for all data structures (<a href="https://www3.ntu.edu.sg/home/ehchua/programming/cpp/cp4_PointerReference.html">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>Binary integers are not just used for numerical calculations; their more important uses are for encoding symbols (using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/String_(computer_science)">strings of characters</a>) and for referencing memory locations (using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pointer_(computer_programming)">pointers</a>). Humans reason by symbols, they invent names for new entities on daily basis. Computers are required to store textual data and complex relations between symbolic entities to be useful; not just act as fast calculators. Strings and pointers are the bases for all other data structures that ever existed. Using sets of binary integers encoding symbols, their memory locations, and their semantic properties we have created arrays, stacks, queues, hash tables, heaps, trees, graphs, and geometrically optimized spatial data structures<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-11' id='enref-395-11' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>11</a></sup>. In the collective experience of computer scientists and software engineers, the most widely used data structures are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tree_(data_structure)">trees</a> of various kinds; think XML.</p>
<p>For our specific purpose of computational applications, there exists one type of software systems that relies completely on trees and their transformations: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symbolic_computation">Symbolic Computation Systems</a> a.k.a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_algebra_system">Computer Algebra Systems</a> (CAS). The mathematical and logical base for modern CAS date back to George Boole&#8217;s method of separation of symbols, the contemporary name for a method which is a precursor of today&#8217;s abstract mathematical formalization<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-12' id='enref-395-12' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>12</a></sup>. Computer algebra can be defined as<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-13' id='enref-395-13' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>13</a></sup>:</p>
<blockquote><p>Computer Algebra is a subject of science devoted to methods for solving mathematically formulated problems by symbolic algorithms, and to implementation of these algorithms in software and hardware. It is based on the exact finite representation of finite or infinite mathematical objects and structures, and allows for symbolic and abstract manipulation by a computer. Structural mathematical knowledge is used during the design as well as for verification and complexity analysis of the respective algorithms. Therefore computer algebra can be effectively employed for answering questions from various areas of computer science and mathematics, as well as natural sciences and engineering, provided they can be expressed in a mathematical model.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_468" style="width: 305px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/expr-tree.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-468" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/expr-tree-295x300.png" alt="expr-tree" width="295" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/expr-tree-295x300.png 295w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/expr-tree.png 679w" sizes="(max-width: 295px) 100vw, 295px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Computer Algebra Systems use and manipulate trees of symbols to accurately represent data, mathematical expressions, and algorithmic procedures (<a href="https://mathematica.stackexchange.com/questions/11632/how-to-generate-a-random-tree">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>Although properly speaking, computer algebra should be a sub-field of scientific computing, they are generally considered as distinct fields because scientific computing is usually based on numerical computation with approximate floating point numbers, while symbolic computation emphasizes exact computation with expressions containing variables that have not any given value and are thus manipulated as symbols (therefore the name of symbolic computation).</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_algebra_system#History">Historically</a>, computer algebra evolved out of two quite different sources: the requirements of theoretical physicists and research into classical symbolic artificial intelligence in the 60&#8217;s. Physics is one of the oldest application fields of computer algebra; in fact, many of the early computer algebra systems were designed or strongly influenced by physicists in order to suit their research needs, in particular, the need to handle highly complicated mathematical relations with parameters in an exact way. The other source for CAS development was symbolic AI, the dominant paradigm of AI research from the middle fifties until the late 1980s, that was motivated by the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physical_symbol_system">physical symbol system hypothesis</a>, later challenged from many directions, stating: &#8220;a physical symbol system has the necessary and sufficient means for general intelligent action&#8221;. For example, Mathematica contains some form of an internal knowledge base and inference engine, the main components of an expert system symbolic AI, as part of its core components. In addition, many of the historical developments required for the normal construction and operation of modern CAS were developed out of symbolic AI research including timesharing, interactive interpreters, graphical user interfaces and the computer mouse, rapid development environments, the linked list data structure, automatic storage management, symbolic programming, functional programming, dynamic programming and object-oriented programming<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-14' id='enref-395-14' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>14</a></sup>.</p>
<p>As of today, the most popular commercial systems are <a href="http://www.wolfram.com/mathematica/">Mathematica</a> and <a href="https://www.maplesoft.com/products/maple/">Maple</a>, which are commonly used by research mathematicians, scientists, and engineers. Freely available alternatives include <a href="http://www.sagemath.org/">Sage</a> which can act as a front-end to several other free and nonfree CAS. Computer algebra systems have profoundly impacted scientific activities in many ways:</p>
<ul>
<li>Standard problems in high school mathematics can be solved by the push of a button nowadays; for example, see the Wolfram Demonstration Project <a href="http://demonstrations.wolfram.com/">online site</a>.</li>
<li>They enable to teach the more application-oriented material, which is usually more extensive but also more interesting, and there is more time to explore more general and conceptual aspects of mathematics. Both can considerably improve comprehension of mathematical methods, their potential, and their limitations, by non-mathematicians.</li>
<li>The use of computer algebra systems has become a standard tool for experiments in advanced research that help to find, support, or refute conjectures. They have become absolutely indispensable in the design and update of tables of mathematical, physical or other scientific objects.</li>
<li>The goals of computer algebra constituted a major challenge for the development and refinement of a wide range of computer science tools and methods, among them list processing, abstract data types, parametric polymorphism, constraint logic programming, parallel computing at various levels of granularity, dynamical memory management, user interfaces and interfaces between systems, mathematical knowledge representation and management.</li>
</ul>
<p>This site is concerned with exploring the computational universe using geometric algebra. Naturally, the main utility for such exploration will definitely be based on a computer algebra system.</p>
<h3>Arriving at an Exact Value, Give or Take</h3>
<blockquote><p>As far as the laws of mathematics refer to reality, they are not certain; and as far as they are certain, they do not refer to reality. &#8212; Albert Einstein, Sidelights on Relativity.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_527" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Sci-method-Eng-method.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-527" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Sci-method-Eng-method-300x200.png" alt="Sci-method-Eng-method" width="300" height="200" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Sci-method-Eng-method-300x200.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Sci-method-Eng-method-768x511.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Sci-method-Eng-method.png 981w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">In both science and engineering, data gathered from measurements or generated from models are approximations to reality (<a href="https://www.sciencebuddies.org/science-fair-projects/engineering-design-process/engineering-design-compare-scientific-method">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>In science and engineering, data gathering is of prime importance. Our ability to measure has developed over the ages to remarkable levels of accuracy. Many of our computational algorithms are originally designed to deal explicitly with well defined exact numerical values. On the other hand, real data obtained by measurement, however accurate, are mere approximations of the actual value. Sometimes there is not even an exact value but just an acceptable range of values of some random variable. Repeatability, the main feature of scientific experimentation, is in many cases only possible within a &#8220;margin of error&#8221; or tolerance. To make things more complicated, there are many natural and computational systems that are very sensitive to small changes in their initial conditions and parameter variations; any small deviation from our theoretical computations will result in unpredictable behavior of the studied system; this is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaos_theory">chaos theory</a>. Many solutions are used for this type of problem: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Probability_theory">probability theory</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fuzzy_logic">fuzzy logic</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Propagation_of_uncertainty">propagation of error</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interval_arithmetic">interval arithmetic</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_530" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Archimedes_pi.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-530" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Archimedes_pi-300x101.png" alt="Archimedes_pi" width="300" height="101" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Archimedes_pi-300x101.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Archimedes_pi.png 707w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Archimedes used a method based on intervals to approximate Pi. See <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_rJdkhlWZVQ">this video</a> for a full explanation</p></div>
<p>Interval arithmetic is a method developed by mathematicians <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interval_arithmetic#History">since the 1950s and 1960s</a> as an approach to putting bounds on rounding errors and measurement errors in mathematical computation and thus developing numerical methods that yield reliable results. Very simply put, it represents each value as a range of possibilities. For example, instead of estimating the height of someone using standard arithmetic as 2.0 meters, using interval arithmetic we might be certain that that person is somewhere between 1.97 and 2.03 meters. Whereas classical arithmetic defines operations on individual numbers, interval arithmetic defines a set of operations on intervals. Interval arithmetic is not a completely new phenomenon in mathematics; it has appeared several times under different names in the course of history. For example, Archimedes calculated lower and upper bounds 223/71 &lt; π &lt; 22/7 in the 3rd century BC.</p>
<div id="attachment_533" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/interval-arith.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-533" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/interval-arith-300x128.png" alt="interval-arith" width="300" height="128" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/interval-arith-300x128.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/interval-arith.png 567w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Basic rules for arithmetic on real intervals. Though simple, they have many bad mathematical and semantic properties</p></div>
<p>At some point in time, research in interval computations was too optimistic; especially in applications related to global optimization<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-15' id='enref-395-15' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>15</a></sup>. But as research progressed many problems started to show. Most of these problems resulted from the bad semantics behind the basic rules of interval arithmetic. For example the operation of subtraction of intervals is not the reverse of addition, simple equations on intervals like A + X = [0, 0] and A X = [1, 1] have no interval solution. Another problem is interval dependency where traditional interval computation algorithms assume all occurrences of intervals to be independent so in an expression like x(1 + 2x) the two x&#8217;s are considered independent resulting in flawed outcomes. This means that most traditional floating point algorithms will never work correctly for intervals. Specific algorithms for solving the same problems will need to be developed specifically for intervals.</p>
<p>The more fundamental problem with intervals arises from the logical interpretation of intervals in practical applications. If we take the interval [a, b] for, say, a temperature satisfying some condition (predicate); what do we really mean by it:</p>
<ul>
<li>All values inside this interval satisfy the given condition.</li>
<li>There exist one or more values inside this interval satisfying the given condition.</li>
</ul>
<p>The difference may seem minor at first glance but it actually leads to different semantics in problems having many variables and many interactions between the variables. Realizing such problems researchers began to investigate other computational laws for intervals based on the actual semantics of their applications<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-16' id='enref-395-16' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>16</a></sup>. This serious problem with interval semantics is the main cause preventing the universal use of interval arithmetic in many computational problems, even though many <a href="http://www.cs.utep.edu/interval-comp/intsoft.html">software libraries</a> already exist for handling traditional interval arithmetic, including the <a href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7140721/?reload=true&amp;arnumber=7140721&amp;filter%3DAND%28p_Publication_Number%3A7140719%29">IEEE Std 1788-2015</a> standard. I suspect that no single number system can alone handle all kinds of inaccuracies in data and intermediate computations. We need to re-think our algebra and algorithms for each problem area to select the most suitable solutions.</p>
<h3>A Functional Definition of Numbers</h3>
<blockquote><p>The real danger is not that computers will begin to think like men, but that men will begin to think like computers. &#8212; Sydney J. Harris.</p></blockquote>
<p>In our 3 part journey with numbers we saw some of the functional roles they play in our modern &#8220;computation oriented&#8221; civilization. It&#8217;s very difficult to give a single universal definition of a number. The reason is that each branch of mathematics, physics, and engineering depends on different kinds of numbers with many interpretations of each. Nevertheless, we can approach a definition using the functional role number systems play in our continuous investigations. The general characteristics of numbers include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Numbers are abstract symbolic mathematical entities with basic operations of, at least, addition and multiplication; algebra is the art and science of manipulating numbers. Some number systems are closed under their operations and some are not (for example floating-point numbers).</li>
<li>Numbers always result from finite or infinite processes (counting, partitioning, extending in dimension, geometric construction, digital manipulation etc.). We can only use infinite processes as conceptual abstractions while we can only implement our computational abstractions using finite processes.</li>
<li>The same number or class of numbers can be found\utilized through many processes: geometric, algebraic, physical, measurement, limiting, computing etc. In this sense, numbers are the most fundamental of all abstractions serving a universal encoding and exchange of information medium between all parts of the human scientific activity.</li>
</ul>
<p>Numbers are no more than abstract tools of the mind; they must be used wisely and creatively. Geometric algebra and its multivectors can be an excellent theoretical base for geometric modeling that encompass, generalize, and interpret complex, quaternion, and vector based abstractions. On the algorithmic and implementation side, we need much more work because of the limited ability to use floating-point numbers for representing our abstract numerical patterns. We need to create new algorithms for our computational needs even for well-studied mathematical models. The blind conversion of abstractions into implementations result in all sorts of problems<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-395-17' id='enref-395-17' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(395)'>17</a></sup>. One very powerful interactive geometry software, <a href="https://www.cinderella.de/tiki-index.php">Cinderella</a>, avoided many of the problems other similar systems face not by increasing floating point accuracy or using interval arithmetic, but be intelligently using more advanced geometry-oriented algebraic structures on complex numbers; see <a href="https://doc.cinderella.de/tiki-index.php?page=Theoretical+Background">this technical background</a> for some details. This level of intelligence in software design require creative use of our number systems usually unobtainable by studying traditional mathematics\engineering textbooks alone.</p>
<div id="attachment_597" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/finished-diagram-for-dikw.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-597" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/finished-diagram-for-dikw-300x111.png" alt="finished-diagram-for-dikw" width="300" height="111" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/finished-diagram-for-dikw-300x111.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/finished-diagram-for-dikw-768x285.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/finished-diagram-for-dikw-1024x380.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/finished-diagram-for-dikw.png 1173w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">A closer look at the DIKW pyramid: starting at data we can arrive at wisdom and create vision (<a href="https://psuf10.wordpress.com/2014/02/16/a-walking-tour-of-the-pathway-to-wisdom/">Souce</a>)</p></div>
<p>If we take a closer look at the famous <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DIKW_Pyramid">DIKW Pyramid</a>, we see that numbers are needed at every stage in our non-stop pursuit of wisdom. However, the effective use of numbers in such pursuit of wisdom requires much wisdom in its own right. We need deep knowledge about a problem we&#8217;re trying to solve in order to select the best numbers to represent our solution, and we need to use whatever numbers we see potentially useful to reach a deep understanding of our problem. In effect, using numbers in a scientific activity should be an iterative process of four steps applied again and again on the long run:</p>
<ol>
<li>Select one or several number systems for the problem.</li>
<li>Represent your data and model with the selected number systems.</li>
<li>Study your system using the numeric tools you&#8217;ve selected.</li>
<li>Assess your findings and, perhaps, change some or all numbers you&#8217;ve worked with to more suitable number systems.</li>
</ol>
<p>Some number system might be better at an early stage of data gathering, some other might be better at a later stage of analysis, yet another one should be used at an implementation stage on computers, while a totally different number system is best used for teaching concepts of the exact same problem. For each problem area we need to be deeply aware of its application and computation requirements to select and use suitable number systems to arrive at our goals. Any other path will result in a large number of ad hoc trial and error based techniques that may never advance our understanding, both collective and individual, for our particular application area. I don&#8217;t believe that we are at the danger of arriving at an &#8220;artificial intelligence&#8221; that can perform such &#8220;deeply creative and artistic&#8221; methods of selecting and using numbers anytime soon, or perhaps never. I do believe that many of us have completely been converted into &#8220;mindless computational machines&#8221; blindly using certain limited sets of number systems that we were taught to use with no idea whatsoever about the universe of other number systems out of our immediate scope of narrow specialty; this is a clear and present danger to our human scientific side. I hope this site may widen the &#8220;numerical horizon&#8221; of some of us, including me, to the point of no return.</p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/done4.png"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-545" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/done4.png" alt="done4" width="300" height="40" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<hr />
<div class='endnotes' id='hhendnotes-395'>
<ol>
<li id='en-395-1'>Stephen Wolfram, &#8220;A New Kind of Science&#8221;. Wolfram Research 2002 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-1'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-2'>It&#8217;s worth noticing that 3 of our central mathematicians in this series were brilliant linguists: Hamilton, Grassmann, and Boole. See the studies <a href="http://basilo.kaist.ac.kr/mathnet/kms_tex/981583.pdf">here</a> and <a href="http://lshss.pubs.asha.org/article.aspx?articleid=1832557">here</a> for the relation between mathematics and language <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-2'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-3'>Luis M. Laita et al., &#8220;George Boole, a Forerunner of Symbolic Computation&#8221;. International Conference AISC 2000 Madrid, Spain, July 17–19, 2000 Revised Papers <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-3'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-4'>Luis M. Laita, &#8220;Influences on Boole&#8217;s logic: The controversy between William Hamilton and Augustus De Morgan&#8221;. Annals of Science Volume 36, Issue 1, 1979 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-4'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-5'>George Boole 200, University College Cork, <a href="https://georgeboole200.ucc.ie/boole/legacy/phil/">Online</a> <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-5'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-6'>Radomir S. Stankovic and Jaakko Astola, &#8220;From Boolean Logic to Switching Circuits and Automata &#8211; Towards Modern Information Technology&#8221;. Springer 2011 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-6'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-7'>Mohammad Bagheri, &#8220;Recreational Problems from Hasib Tabari’s Miftāh al-mu’āmalāt&#8221;. GANITA BHARATI Vol. 21, 1999. <a href="http://www.mb-kushyar.com/articles_e/RECREATIONAL%20PROBLEMS%20FROM%20HASIB%20TABARI.pdf">Online Version</a>. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-7'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-8'>Donald E. Knuth, &#8220;The Art of Computer Programming Volume 2: Seminumerical Algorithms, 3rd Edition&#8221;. Addison-Wesley Professional 1997 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-8'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-9'>For real instances of disastrous software failure due to floating-point errors see section 3.10 &#8220;The Elephant in the Living Room&#8221; in Ronald T. Kneusel, &#8220;Numbers and Computers&#8221;. Springer 2015 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-9'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-10'>N.J. Wildberger, &#8220;Divine Proportions: Rational Trigonometry to Universal Geometry&#8221;. Wild Egg Books 2005 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-10'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-11'>Hanan Samet, &#8220;Foundations of Multidimensional and Metric Data Structures&#8221;. Morgan Kaufmann 2006 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-11'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-12'>Luis de Ledesma et al., &#8220;A Computational Approach to George Boole&#8217;s Discovery of Mathematical Logic&#8221;. Artificial Intelligence Volume 91 Issue 2, April 1997 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-12'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-13'>Johannes Grabmeier, Erich Kaltofen, Volker Weispfenning (Editors), &#8220;Computer Algebra Handbook &#8211; Foundations, Applications, Systems&#8221;. Springer 2003 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-13'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-14'>Stuart Russell, Peter Norvig, &#8220;Artificial Intelligence: A Modern Approach, 2nd Ed.&#8221;. Prentice Hall 2002 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-14'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-15'>Eldon Hansen, G. William Walster (Editors), &#8220;Global Optimization Using Interval Analysis: Revised And Expanded, 2nd Edition&#8221;. CRC Press 2003 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-15'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-16'>Sainz, M.A., Armengol, J., Calm, R., Herrero, P., Jorba, L., Vehi, J, &#8220;Modal Interval Analysis &#8211; New Tools for Numerical Information&#8221;. Springer 2014 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-16'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-395-17'>Joab Winkler, Mahesan Niranjan (Editors), &#8220;Uncertainty in Geometric Computations&#8221;. Springer 2002 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-395-17'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
</ol>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2015/08/14/history-of-numbers3/">A Functional History of Numbers (3 of 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Functional History of Numbers (2 of 3)</title>
		<link>/index.php/2015/08/07/history-of-numbers2/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2015 14:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ahmad Eid]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[GA History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Numbers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://gacomputing.info/?p=270</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>In part one of this functional history of numbers we saw the development of various number systems we are mostly familiar with. In this part, we will see the development of many number systems that are important for our modern scientific needs, geometrically and computationally. The sad fact about these developments is that we are using and teaching less effective number systems today because of a "series of unfortunate events" that took place during the grand drama of human development of modern mathematics.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2015/08/07/history-of-numbers2/">A Functional History of Numbers (2 of 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Old-Geometry.png"><img class=" size-full wp-image-364 aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Old-Geometry.png" alt="Old-Geometry" width="968" height="768" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Old-Geometry.png 968w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Old-Geometry-300x238.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Old-Geometry-768x609.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 968px) 100vw, 968px" /></a></p>
<blockquote><p>As long as algebra and geometry have been separated, their progress have been slow and their uses limited; but when these two sciences have been united, they have lent each mutual forces, and have marched together towards perfection. &#8212; Joseph-Louis Lagrange.</p></blockquote>
<span class="dropcap">I</span>n <a href="/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/">part one</a> of this functional history of numbers we saw the development of various number systems we are mostly familiar with. In this part, we will see the development of many number systems that are important for our modern scientific needs, geometrically and computationally. The sad fact about these developments is that we are using and teaching less effective number systems today because of a &#8220;series of unfortunate events&#8221; that took place during the grand drama of human development of modern mathematics.</p>
<h3>Missing the Truth in Pursuit of Beauty</h3>
<blockquote><p>Here as he walked by on the 16th of October 1843 Sir William Rowan Hamilton in a flash of genius discovered the fundamental formula for quaternion multiplication <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">i^{2}=j^{2}=k^{2}=ijk=-1</span> &amp; cut it on a stone of this bridge. &#8212; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_quaternions#/media/File:William_Rowan_Hamilton_Plaque_-_geograph.org.uk_-_347941.jpg">Quaternion plaque</a> on Brougham (Broom) Bridge, Dublin.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_330" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/6a0163057a21c8970d017743e0b713970d.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-330" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/6a0163057a21c8970d017743e0b713970d-300x150.jpg" alt="Avoiding a gimbal lock using quaternions" width="300" height="150" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/6a0163057a21c8970d017743e0b713970d-300x150.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/6a0163057a21c8970d017743e0b713970d.jpg 694w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Avoiding a gimbal lock using quaternions; see <a href="http://around-the-corner.typepad.com/adn/2012/08/avoid-gimbal-lock-for-rotationdirection-maya-manipulators.html">here</a> for the full article</p></div>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Rowan_Hamilton">Sir William Rowan Hamilton</a> a renounced Irish physicist, astronomer, and mathematician had been interested in complex numbers for a long time. Motivated by the beautiful geometric properties of complex numbers, he was obsessed with generalizing complex numbers to 3 dimensional space while keeping the most fascinating property of complex numbers: the unification of points (data) and transformations (processing) in a single algebraic entity while applying the transformations to points using algebraic multiplication and formal summation. Out of this preoccupation Hamilton was to invent the most beautiful algebra of the century: the algebra of quaternions. Hamilton never arrived at his beautiful generalization; it simply does not exist in the way he imagined. A fact about generalizations of abstract concepts is that they&#8217;re not free; with any generalization of a concept we must give up some of its properties. Often we cannot choose and control an arbitrary set of properties to generalize for some concept; this set may be consistent with the original concept but inconsistent with its generalization. Sadly enough, Hamilton and his followers made some big mistakes that almost banished quaternion algebra from practical applications in physics and engineering for a very long time<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-1' id='enref-270-1' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>1</a></sup>. They literally missed the true beauty of quaternions as rotation operators<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-2' id='enref-270-2' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>2</a></sup> in their stubborn pursuit of a specific form of beauty they imagined as pure mathematicians: a method to divide 3D vectors just like complex numbers. The full story of this unfortunate event can be found in Simon L. Altmann intriguing paper &#8220;Hamilton, Rodrigues, and the Quaternion Scandal&#8221;<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-3' id='enref-270-3' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>3</a></sup>.</p>
<p>On the morning of Monday, 16 October 1843 Hamilton, accompanied by Lady Hamilton, was walking along the Royal Canal in Dublin towards the Royal Irish Academy, where Hamilton was to preside at a meeting. As he was walking past Broome Bridge (referred to as Brougham Bridge by Hamilton and called by this name ever since), Hamilton, in a flash of inspiration, realized that three, rather than two, imaginary units were needed in 3D space, with the properties <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">i^{2}=j^{2}=k^{2}=-1,\;ij=-k,\;ji=-k</span> and cyclic permutation. Hamilton carved these formulae on the stone of the bridge; poor Lady Hamilton had to wait. Armed now with four units, Hamilton called the number <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">A=a\,1+A_{x}\,i+A_{y}\,j+A_{z}\,k</span> where the coefficients here are all real, a quaternion. Hamilton made the product <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">ij=-ji</span> non-commutative. Not only was this the first time that a non-commutative product appeared in mathematics, but this was a true stroke of genius which has given us the last possible <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Division_algebra#Associative_division_algebras">associative division algebra</a><sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-4' id='enref-270-4' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>4</a></sup>. As a complex number <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">C=x+iy</span> is the formal sum of a real part <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">x</span> and an imaginary part <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">iy</span>, a quaternion <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">Q_{A}=a\,1+A_{x}\,i+A_{y}\,j+A_{z}\,k</span> can be viewed as a formal sum of the real part <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">a</span> and the &#8220;pure-quaternion&#8221; part <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">A=A_{x}\,i+A_{y}\,j+A_{z}\,k</span>. It follows that the product of two quaternions <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">Q_{A}=a+A</span> and <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">Q_{B}=b+B</span> is given by: <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">Q_{A}Q_{B}=(ab-A\cdot B)+(aB+bA+A\times B)</span> where <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">A\cdot B=A_{x}B_{x}+A_{y}B_{y}+A_{z}B_{z}</span> and <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">A\times B=(A_{y}B_{z}-A_{z}B_{y})\,i+(A_{z}B_{x}-A_{x}B_{z})\,j+(A_{x}B_{y}-A_{y}B_{x})\,k</span>
<p>Although Hamilton did not give names or symbols for these operations, it is here that the scalar and vector products of two vectors appear for the first time in history. The big mistake Hamilton made was treating the pure-quaternion part as a vector (actually it&#8217;s a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bivector#Quaternions">bivector</a>); he even named it a vector. He then treated rotations in 3D space using his newly invented algebra but with many internal contradictions stemming from his imagined goal of generalizing complex numbers while preserving all their &#8220;algebraically beautiful properties&#8221;. Two other unfortunate events happened in the drama of quaternions. First, Gauss had actually discovered quaternions but had never bothered to publish, as shown by Gauss&#8217;s notes from 1819, published in 1900; that certainly didn&#8217;t help Hamilton&#8217;s case. Second, a treatment of rotations and quaternions had been going on for some years before 1843, quite independently of Hamilton and taking a diametrically opposed view to his. This treatment was entirely geometrical, and because it tried to do a simple job in a simple way it was clear and precise and it was entirely successful, but it was largely ignored by everyone. It was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olinde_Rodrigues">Olinde Rodrigues</a> in his 1840 paper who provided a construction to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%27s_rotation_theorem">Euler&#8217;s rotation theorem</a> correctly <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%E2%80%93Rodrigues_formula#Connection_with_quaternions">linking quaternions to rotations</a> <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-5' id='enref-270-5' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>5</a></sup>. Hamilton himself geometrically rediscovered the results of the Rodrigues construction but completely ignored its importance; probably blinded by his original goal of &#8220;algebraic beauty&#8221;.</p>
<div id="attachment_351" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/quaternions.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-351" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/quaternions-300x220.jpg" alt="Irish stamp on the Quaternions," width="300" height="220" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/quaternions-300x220.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/quaternions-768x564.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/quaternions.jpg 994w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Irish stamp on the Quaternions, issued by Ireland on May 4, 1983. (<a href="http://jeff560.tripod.com/images/quaternions.jpg">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>After Hamilton&#8217;s death, his work began to give fruits but not in the direction which he had expected. His ideas of vectors and of their scalar and vector products were much too important so that people began to try and graft a new skin onto them in order to make these concepts usable. Grassmann in Germany and Heaviside in Britain moved some way in this direction, but they were not much more transparent than Hamilton himself. It was left to Willard Gibbs of Yale to produce not only the first coherent picture of vectors and of their operations but also a good and successful working notation; effectively eliminating quaternions, with all their true beauty as rotation operators, from the picture. This hardened the response of Hamilton&#8217;s followers as one of them, Peter Tait, stated:</p>
<blockquote><p>Even Prof. Willard Gibbs must be ranked as one of the retarders of quaternion progress, in virtue of his pamphlet on Vector Analysis, a sort of hermaphrodite monster, compounded of the notations of Hamilton and of Grassmann.</p></blockquote>
<p>This was not the end of the story for quaternions. They would resurface many years later as advantageous rotation operators in 3D space; currently used in robotics, aviation, and computer graphics to name a few applications. Nevertheless, many important lessons can be taught from the story of the last division algebra. The main lesson being: you have to consistently follow the truth and it will lead to more beauty than the one you might imagine.</p>
<h3>Into Hyperspace Without the Womb of Numbers</h3>
<blockquote><p>The Matrix is everywhere. It is all around us. Even now, in this very room. &#8212; Morpheus, The Matrix.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_367" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Matrix.png"><img class="wp-image-367 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Matrix-300x65.png" alt="Matrix" width="300" height="65" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Matrix-300x65.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Matrix.png 576w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">A Matrix is the &#8220;Womb of Numbers&#8221; in which Linear Algebra was born</p></div>
<p>It&#8217;s said that necessity is the mother of invention; sometimes the lack of necessity brutally kills brilliant ideas. Linear algebra is a fascinating subject with applications in almost every field of science and engineering<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-6' id='enref-270-6' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>6</a></sup>. When you search for a definition for the term &#8220;Linear Algebra&#8221; you will find a definition like:</p>
<blockquote><p>Linear Algebra is a branch of mathematics that is concerned with mathematical structures closed under the operations of addition and scalar multiplication and that includes the theory of systems of linear equations, matrices, determinants, vector spaces, and linear transformations. &#8212; Merriam Webster <a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/linear%20algebra">online dictionary.</a></p></blockquote>
<p>When you take a look at some books about the subject you will find two kinds of books. The first kind<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-7' id='enref-270-7' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>7</a></sup> mostly deals with linear equations, coordinate vectors (i.e. tuples of numbers), matrices, and determinants; this may give the wrong impression that linear algebra is nothing more than the study of matrix algebra and coordinate vectors in Euclidean space. The second kind of books<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-8' id='enref-270-8' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>8</a></sup> deals with an abstract concept of vectors and linear transformations defined axiomatically without giving any special importance to coordinates, and applicable to any metric space Euclidean or not. Now matrices are put to perspective as no more than computational and representational tools for the subject, not the subject itself. Historically<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-9' id='enref-270-9' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>9</a></sup> the first use of linear equations of 2 and 3 unknowns date back to ancient Babylonians and Chinese. The modern study of systems of linear equations can be said to have originated with Leibniz, who in 1693 invented the notion of a determinant for this purpose. Following developments took place by Cramer, Euler, Gauss, Laplace, Cauchy, Weierstrass, Kronecker, Cayley, Frobenius, and many others. All such developments were based on applications from diverse fields of mathematics and physics; a sign of the necessity and universality of linear algebra. In 1848, J.J. Sylvester introduced the term “matrix”, the Latin word for womb and a word related to &#8220;mother&#8221;, as a name for an array of numbers. By the year 1880, many of the fundamental results of linear algebra had been established, but they were not considered as parts of a general theory. In particular, the fundamental notion of vector space, within which such a theory would be framed, was absent. Matrices and coordinate vectors, out of necessity, are at the core of the historical development of linear algebra and vector spaces. In our modern computational age, any software library dealing with linear algebra must have matrices and their computational algorithms as the main component. Every engineer in the world must have some idea about the Matrix Laboratory; <a href="https://www.mathworks.com/products/matlab.html">MATLAB</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_356" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/clifford3d.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-356" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/clifford3d-300x97.png" alt="Exterior Product" width="300" height="97" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/clifford3d-300x97.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/clifford3d-768x248.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/clifford3d.png 1012w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Grassmann used vectors to define higher-dimensional subspaces algebraically using his exterior product (<a href="https://slehar.wordpress.com/2014/03/18/clifford-algebra-a-visual-introduction/">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>One mathematician took a fundamentally different approach to linear algebra than all others hoping to approach Leibniz&#8217;s dream of a universal algebra that can deal directly and simply with geometric entities<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-10' id='enref-270-10' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>10</a></sup>; he was Hermann Günther Grassmann. Many have written about the extraordinary role of Grassmann&#8217;s work in modern mathematics and physics including Roger Penrose<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-11' id='enref-270-11' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>11</a></sup>, David Hestenes<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-12' id='enref-270-12' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>12</a></sup>, and many others<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-13' id='enref-270-13' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>13</a></sup>. Desmond Fearnley-Sander describes how Grassmann developed linear algebra by himself in <a href="https://www.maa.org/sites/default/files/pdf/upload_library/22/Ford/DesmondFearnleySander.pdf">his paper</a> &#8220;Hermann Grassmann and the Creation of Linear Algebra&#8221;. From the beginning, Grassmann distinguished linear algebra, as a formal theory independent of any interpretation, from its application in geometry. Grassmann described the concept of vector space and developed the theory of linear independence in a way which is astonishingly similar to the presentation one finds in modern linear algebra texts. He defined the concepts of subspace, linear independence, span, dimension, join and meet of subspaces, and projections of elements onto subspaces. He proved the invariance of dimension under change of basis and obtained the formula for change of coordinates under change of basis. He defined elementary transformations of basis and showed that every change of basis is a product of elementaries. His work led Peano in 1888 to put down the formal definitions of linear algebra that was ignored for 30 years until 1920 when Hermann Weyl and others published formal definitions resulting in the widespread of linear algebra ever since. Few have come closer than Hermann Grassmann to creating, single-handedly, a new subject. In addition, the first fundamental investigation in multi-dimensional geometry was provided by Grassmann in 1844, in which affine geometry was developed not only for three-dimensional space but for multi-dimensional space also. That it was Grassmann who succeeded in establishing an articulated theory of multidimensional space seems to be due largely to the fact that Grassmann was not under the influence of other great mathematicians of his time, and to his predilection for philosophical generalizations<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-14' id='enref-270-14' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>14</a></sup>. The following is an extract from the Foreword of &#8220;Die Ausdehnungslehre: Vollständig und in strenger Form bearbeitet&#8221; (The Theory of Extension, Thoroughly and Rigorously Treated) published by Grassmann in 1862:</p>
<blockquote><p>I remain completely confident that the labor I have expended on the science presented here and which has demanded a significant part of my life as well as the most strenuous application of my powers, will not be lost. It is true that I am aware that the form which I have given the science is imperfect and must be imperfect. But I know and feel obliged to state (though I run the risk of seeming arrogant) that even if this work should again remain unused for another seventeen years or even longer, without entering into the actual development of science, still that time will come when it will be brought forth from the dust of oblivion and when ideas now dormant will bring forth fruit. I know that if I also fail to gather around me (as I have until now desired in vain) a circle of scholars, whom I could fructify with these ideas, and whom I could stimulate to develop and enrich them further, yet there will come a time when these ideas, perhaps in a new form, will arise anew and will enter into a living communication with contemporary developments. For truth is eternal and divine and no phase of it &#8230; can pass without a trace; it remains in existence even if the cloth in which weak mortals dress it disintegrates into dust.</p></blockquote>
<p>Grassmann expected his ideas would be revived even if unused for 17 years or longer; it actually took a hundred years. At that time in the 19th century, Grassmann&#8217;s ideas (especially in geometry) were revolutionary; they were too advanced for the necessities of his age. Ironically, Grassmann was renowned in his day as a linguist but as a mathematician, he had poor notational skills. His ideas were great but his symbolic expression of them was awkward. Few mathematicians of his age acknowledged his brilliance. One of them was the English mathematician and philosopher William Kingdon Clifford. Clifford was the one who would give new form and meaning to Grassmann&#8217;s ideas.</p>
<h3>Lost and Found: Geometric Algebra</h3>
<blockquote><p>The further a mathematical theory is developed, the more harmoniously and uniformly does its construction proceed, and unsuspected relations are disclosed between hitherto separated branches of the science. &#8212; David Hilbert.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_391" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Spinor_on_the_circle.pdf.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-391" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Spinor_on_the_circle.pdf-300x228.jpg" alt="When the vector is rotated along the Möbius strip it reverses direction after an odd number of full rotations; it's a spinor." width="300" height="228" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Spinor_on_the_circle.pdf-300x228.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Spinor_on_the_circle.pdf-768x585.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Spinor_on_the_circle.pdf.jpg 787w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">When the vector is rotated along the Möbius strip it reverses direction after an odd number of full rotations; it&#8217;s a spinor.</p></div>
<p>Grassmann&#8217;s vectors and subspaces were not numbers in a way complex numbers and quaternions are. In <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exterior_algebra">Grassmann algebra</a>, a finite set of n vectors, representing 1-dimensional subspaces analogous to lines passing through the origin of a coordinate system of the space, are combined using his exterior product to algebraically form entities representing all other subspaces of dimension 2 to n. Grassmann had no interest, however, in representing transformations that &#8220;rotate&#8221; a subspace into another of the same dimension; something all physical and engineering models require to stand and function. Hamilton had the correct algebra for rotating vectors in 3-dimensional space but no generalization to n-dimensional space was present. While Hamilton lost his way insisting on treating rotations in 3D with the algebra of quaternions using direct multiplications, the brilliant but short-lived English mathematician William Kingdon Clifford took the correct path of generalizing rotations to the n-dimensional spaces of Grassmann<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-15' id='enref-270-15' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>15</a></sup>; the resulting beautiful mathematical abstraction was called <a href="https://slehar.wordpress.com/2014/03/18/clifford-algebra-a-visual-introduction/">Clifford Algebra</a>. Clifford successfully unified and generalized Hamilton&#8217;s quaternions and Grassmann&#8217;s vector spaces in a uniform manner that affected physics and science ever since. His motivation was to create an algebra that can act on strange but common objects in geometry and physics called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spinor">spinors</a>. A spinor is an abstraction of an object that reverses its direction when rotated by an odd number of full cycles in space; contrary to our common intuition about physical 3D objects. Clifford also wrote his report at Cambridge &#8220;On the Space-Theory of Matter&#8221;, published in 1876, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Kingdon_Clifford#Premonition_of_relativity">anticipating Albert Einstein’s general relativity</a> by 40 years. Clifford&#8217;s contemporaries considered him acute and original, witty and warm. Felix Klein wrote, regarding Clifford,</p>
<blockquote><p>I recall him with particular pleasure, as a man who understood me thoroughly from the first and soon extended my research.</p></blockquote>
<p>Clifford was also working late into the night, he collapsed twice in two years from overworking, which may have led to his death at a young age; another unfortunate event for the development of his geometric numbers. Although Clifford recognized his algebra&#8217;s unique signiﬁcance as a representation of geometric concepts as conceived by Grassmann, mathematicians abstracted Clifford algebra from its geometric origins after his death and, for the better part of a century, it languished as a minor sub-discipline of mathematics; one more algebra among so many others<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-16' id='enref-270-16' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>16</a></sup>.</p>
<div id="attachment_433" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-hestenes-dev.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-433" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-hestenes-dev-300x184.png" alt="ga-hestenes-dev" width="300" height="184" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-hestenes-dev-300x184.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-hestenes-dev-768x471.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-hestenes-dev.png 844w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Revival and Development of GA starting at David Hestenes research efforts</p></div>
<p>In 1966 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Hestenes">David Orlin Hestenes</a> published his book &#8220;Space-Time Algebra&#8221;, motivated by a set of lecture notes by Marcel Riesz later published in 1993; launching him along three main lines of research:</p>
<ol>
<li>A straightforward reformulation of classical physics in terms of Clifford&#8217;s geometric algebra producing the first comprehensive coordinate-free treatment of Newtonian mechanics,  including rotational dynamics as explained in his book &#8220;New Foundations for Classical Mechanics&#8221;, in addition to a similar reformulation of classical electrodynamics.</li>
<li>Reformulating the Dirac equation in terms of Geometric Algebra. This revealed a hidden geometric structure in quantum mechanics, including a  hitherto unrecognized geometric interpretation for the unit imaginary relating it unequivocally to electron spin.</li>
<li>To produce a self-contained system of mathematical tools sufficient for addressing any problem in physics without resorting to alternative mathematical formalisms; as explained in his book &#8220;Clifford Algebra to Geometric Calculus, A Unified Language for Mathematics and Physics&#8221;.</li>
</ol>
<p>Hestenes received <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Hestenes#Awards_and_fellowships">several awards</a> related to his efforts in teaching physics using GA. As he describes his work in reviving Clifford and Grassmann&#8217;s work:</p>
<blockquote><p>I was consciously concerned with questions relating the structure of these mathematical systems to the structure of the physical world. One day Riesz’s notes appeared on the new-book shelf of the UCLA library. The impact on me was immediate and striking! By the time I was half way through the first chapter I was convinced that Clifford algebra was the key to unifying mathematical physics. During the next few years I worked out the framework for a fully geometric unification. The result was published in my book Space Time Algebra (1966). Fortunately, my book was widely distributed, and it helped me establish many fruitful contacts throughout the world in subsequent years. However, I believe its impact would have dissipated had I not followed it up with years of further research, lectures and publications. Also, I believe that the significance of Riesz’s notes would have remained unrecognized without the citation in my book, which eventually led to publication (in 1993). Though the book launched me on a program to unify mathematical physics, I refrained from proclaiming the product as a universal Geometric Algebra and Calculus until subsequent research convinced me that was fully justified. I was well aware that its roots were in the work of Grassmann, but it was not until the English translations of the Ausdehnungslehre by Lloyd Kannenberg that I realized how deep those roots were.</p></blockquote>
<p>Later on, Hestenes ideas in physics found their way into many computer science and engineering applications over the last 15 years. We are still at the beginning of the road to exploring this powerful abstract number system for our ever growing geometric dependent applications.</p>
<h3>GA&#8217;s Multivectors: The Spacious Number System</h3>
<blockquote><p>Physics is mathematical not because we know so much about the physical world, but because we know so little; it is only its mathematical properties that we can discover. &#8212; Bertrand Russell.</p></blockquote>
<p>A geometric algebra is constructed from a set of <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">n</span> basis vectors on a scalar field (for example real or complex numbers) and a symmetric bilinear form defining the metric (i.e. the scalar-valued inner product of pairs of basis vectors). Using Clifford&#8217;s geometric product a set of <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">2^{n}</span> basis blades, representing main subspaces of the algebra of dimensions 0 to <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">n</span>, are constructed. Multivectors, our geometric numbers, are linear combinations of the basis blades. All GA algebraic operations and beauty follow from this simple construction.</p>
<div id="attachment_426" style="width: 964px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-basis-blades.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-426" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-basis-blades.png" alt="ga-basis-blades" width="954" height="294" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-basis-blades.png 954w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-basis-blades-300x92.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-basis-blades-768x237.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 954px) 100vw, 954px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">GA basis blades are constructed from basis vectors using the outer product (<a href="http://www2.ic.uff.br/~laffernandes/projects/ga/2009_SIBGRAPI_tutorial/fernandes_oliveia_SIBGRAPI_2009_tutorial_slides.pdf">Source</a>)</p></div>
<div id="attachment_417" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-R3-blades.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-417" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-R3-blades-300x274.png" alt="ga-R3-blades" width="300" height="274" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-R3-blades-300x274.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-R3-blades.png 406w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The 3D Euclidean GA has 8 basis blades constructed from 3 basis vectors (<a href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.158.4974&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>I will not go into the mathematical and geometric properties of GA in this post, after all, the whole site is dedicated to exploring GA, but I will mention some of its general characteristic strengths as an algebraic language for geometry compared to traditional matrix-based linear algebra for geometric modeling<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-17' id='enref-270-17' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>17</a></sup>:</p>
<p>1. GA can be used to model many geometries including non-Euclidean ones. The same algebraic structure can have many geometric modeling interpretations<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-270-18' id='enref-270-18' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(270)'>18</a></sup>.</p>
<div id="attachment_419" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-spaces.png"><img class="wp-image-419 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-spaces-300x227.png" alt="ga-spaces" width="300" height="227" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-spaces-300x227.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-spaces.png 474w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">GA can be used to study non-Euclidean Geometries (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1101.4542v3.pdf">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>2. Many familiar algebraic entities can be considered isomorphic to special cases of multivectors. These include real numbers, complex numbers, quaternions, and vectors of many types (position, direction, and normal vectors), Many types of matrices, typically used as linear transforms, can be replaced by GA multivectors including orthogonal matrices, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pauli_matrices">Pauli matrices</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homogeneous_coordinates">homogeneous transform matrices</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_411" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-rotation.png"><img class="wp-image-411 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-rotation-300x236.png" alt="ga-3d-rotation" width="300" height="236" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-rotation-300x236.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-rotation.png 560w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Quaternions as GA versors (<a href="http://geometricalgebra.net/figures.html">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>3. Grassmann&#8217;s outer product can be used inside GA to construct algebraic entities called blades, one type of multivectors, that represent subspaces of the base vector space. Depending on the selected geometric model for the vectors, blades will be a systematic representation of geometric primitives inside the selected geometry.</p>
<div id="attachment_423" style="width: 271px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-blades-geometry.png"><img class="wp-image-423 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-blades-geometry-261x300.png" alt="ga-blades-geometry" width="261" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-blades-geometry-261x300.png 261w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-blades-geometry.png 579w" sizes="(max-width: 261px) 100vw, 261px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The same GA blade (subspace) can have several geometric interpretations (<a href="http://www2.ic.uff.br/~laffernandes/projects/ga/2009_SIBGRAPI_tutorial/fernandes_oliveia_SIBGRAPI_2009_tutorial_slides.pdf">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>4. Linear transformations on the base vector space can be easily extended and directly applied to blades (subspaces) using what is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outermorphism">outermorphisms</a>. Now we can algebraically manipulate the geometric primitives of our selected geometry by linear transformations without the use of matrices if we want.</p>
<p>5. Orthogonal transformations (linear transformations consisting of a series of reflections on hyperplanes) are very important for many geometric applications. GA can efficiently represent and apply such transformations using a special kind of multivectors called a versor. This is a very good alternative for orthogonal matrices both theoretically and computationally in many situations.</p>
<div id="attachment_410" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-reflection.png"><img class="wp-image-410 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-reflection-300x226.png" alt="ga-3d-reflection" width="300" height="226" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-reflection-300x226.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-3d-reflection.png 530w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">In GA, versors come from using vectors as reflection operators; all orthogonal transformations are series of reflections (<a href="http://geometricalgebra.net/figures.html">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>6. Verosrs can be applied to geometric constructions in a &#8220;covariant&#8221; manner. In traditional matrix algebra, we need to analyze a subspace, representing some geometric entity, to its vector components before applying the orthogonal transform then reconstruct the transformed subspace\entity from the transformed vectors. In GA we can directly apply orthogonal transforms to geometric entities using versors and blades with no need for any extra overhead.</p>
<p>7. In GA many blades can act as versors, leading to the use of geometric entities as orthogonal transformations. One can, say, rotate a plane and reflect a circle on the rotated plane using the same multivectors with no conversion to any other algebraic representations. This is a very different concept, and indeed a very powerful one, compared to the traditional matrix algebra approach.</p>
<div id="attachment_414" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops.png"><img class="wp-image-414 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops-300x141.png" alt="ga-blades" width="300" height="141" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops-300x141.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops-768x362.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops-1024x482.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops-520x245.png 520w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops-720x340.png 720w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/ga-ops.png 1153w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Geometric entities expressed as GA blades can be used to covariantly transform other geometric entities (<a href="https://staff.fnwi.uva.nl/t.h.koornwinder/specialdays/veldenwegen/Dorst.pdf">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>8. In some cases, GA can be used to find closed form expressions for geometric interpolations and perturbations of non-trivial kinds. This would very much help in developing algorithms for important geometric models.</p>
<div id="attachment_429" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/isea_img2_01_flat2.jpg"><img class="wp-image-429 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/isea_img2_01_flat2-300x146.jpg" alt="isea_img2_01_flat2" width="300" height="146" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/isea_img2_01_flat2-300x146.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/isea_img2_01_flat2-768x373.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/08/isea_img2_01_flat2-1024x497.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">GA interpolations of motion using versors (<a href="http://isea2011.sabanciuniv.edu/paper/versor-proposal-system-organic-constructivism">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>9. GA can work well with traditional matrix-based modeling techniques. One can use a linear algebra software library and interface it with a GA model easily; no need to model everything into GA from scratch.</p>
<p>10. All the above and other GA characteristics can make life much easier for people creating computational code for geometric modeling applications. GA is consistent and systematic algebraically with direct geometric interpretation. You just need to select your model and do the math; programming is straight forward. For example take a look at <a href="https://vimeo.com/wolftype">these videos</a> created using the <a href="http://versor.mat.ucsb.edu/">Versor GA library</a>.</p>
<p>All these unique characteristics will certainly have deep influence, over the long run, on our understanding and development of geometric models in science and engineering. Many problems related to practical use and teaching of GA remain to be solved, but the concept had already been proven and the way is now much more clear for many researchers. In our next and final part of this functional history of numbers we will investigate another kind of numbers; the numbers we use in computing everything.</p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/done3.png"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-456" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/done3.png" alt="done3" width="300" height="40" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<hr />
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class='endnotes' id='hhendnotes-270'>
<ol>
<li id='en-270-1'>During my research for this post I found that the 1873 edition of James Clerk Maxwell&#8217;s &#8220;A Treatise on Electricity and Magnetism&#8221; contains 20 Quaternion Equations that later were rewritten by Oliver Heaviside, et al.. See <a href="http://www.rexresearch.com/maxwell.htm">here</a> and <a href="http://visualphysics.org/forum/topics/200-missing-quaternion-equations-maxwells-treatis-electromagnetism-edition-1">here</a> for some details <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-1'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-2'>Simon L. Altmann, &#8220;Rotations, Quaternions, and Double Groups&#8221;. Oxford University Press 1986 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-2'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-3'>Simon L. Altmann, &#8220;Hamilton, Rodrigues, and the Quaternion Scandal&#8221;. Mathematics Magazine 62 (5): 306, December 1989. JSTOR 2689481. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-3'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-4'>As later proven by Frobenius that the only possible associative division algebras are the real, complex, and quaternion algebras <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-4'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-5'>N. J. Wildberger has a series of video lectures on famous math problems, four of which introduce the rotation problem and Hamilton&#8217;s discovery of quaternions; the series can be found <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uRKZnFAR7yw&amp;list=PLIljB45xT85Bfc-S4WHvTIM7E-ir3nAOf&amp;index=12">here</a>. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-5'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-6'>See this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8CX-Q0gtSp8">intriguing video</a> for a glimpse <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-6'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-7'>For example David Poole, &#8220;Linear Algebra, a Modern Introduction, 4th Edition&#8221;. Cengage Learning 2015 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-7'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-8'>For example Sheldon Axler, &#8220;Linear Algebra Done Right, Third Edition&#8221;. Springer 2015 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-8'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-9'>Israel Kleiner, &#8220;A History of Abstract Algebra&#8221;. Birkhauser Boston 2007 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-9'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-10'>Gottfried Leibniz, letter to Christian Huygens (8 September 1679) &#8220;I believe that, so far as geometry is concerned, we need still another analysis which is distinctly geometrical or linear and which will express situation directly as algebra expresses magnitude directly.&#8221;, in Gottfried Leibniz &#8220;Philosophical Papers and Letters, 2nd Edition&#8221;. Springer 1976 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-10'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-11'>Roger Penrose, &#8220;The Road to Reality: A Complete Guide to the Laws of the Universe&#8221;. Vintage 2007 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-11'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-12'>Gert Schubring (Editor), &#8220;Hermann Günther Graßmann (1809–1877): Visionary Mathematician, Scientist and Neohumanist Scholar, Papers from a Sesquicentennial Conference&#8221;. Springer Netherlands 1996 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-12'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-13'>Hans-Joachim Petsche, Albert C. Lewis, Jörg Liesen, Steve Russ (Editors), &#8220;From Past to Future: Graßmann&#8217;s Work in Context, Graßmann Bicentennial Conference, September 2009&#8221;. Springer Basel 2011 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-13'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-14'>A.N. Kolmogorov and A.P. Yushkevich (Editors), &#8220;Mathematics of the 19th Century, Mathematical Logic Algebra Number Theory Probability Theory&#8221;. Birkhäuser Basel 2001 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-14'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-15'>For a good explanation of the differences between Grassmann algebra and Clifford algebra see Roger Penrose&#8217;s book &#8220;The Road To Reality&#8221; <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-15'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-16'>David Hestenes, &#8220;Oersted Medal Lecture 2002: Reforming the Mathematical Language of Physics&#8221;. American Journal of Physics 71, 104 (2003) <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-16'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-17'>For more very interesting details see Leo Dorst, Daniel Fontijne, and Stephen Mann, &#8220;Geometric Algebra for Computer Science (Revised Edition): An Object-Oriented Approach to Geometry&#8221;. Morgan Kaufmann 2009 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-17'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-270-18'>G. Sommer (Editor), &#8220;Geometric Computing with Clifford Algebra&#8221;. Springer-Verlag Heidelberg 2000 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-270-18'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
</ol>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2015/08/07/history-of-numbers2/">A Functional History of Numbers (2 of 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Functional History of Numbers (1 of 3)</title>
		<link>/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/</link>
		<comments>/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2015 13:00:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ahmad Eid]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[GA History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Algebra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Numbers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://gacomputing.info/?p=251</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>The main goal of this post is to link Geometric Algebra to mathematics on the fundamental level of numbers. Here I briefly describe the history of numbers with emphasis on their functional role in mathematics, science, and engineering to put the computational role GA can play into perspective.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/">A Functional History of Numbers (1 of 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/numbers.png"><img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-286" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/numbers-1024x768.png" alt="Black and white numbers background" width="720" height="540" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/numbers-1024x768.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/numbers-300x225.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/numbers-768x576.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/numbers.png 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 720px) 100vw, 720px" /></a></p>
<blockquote><p>The interest which pupils take in their studies may be greatly increased if the solution of problems and the cold logic of geometrical demonstrations are interspersed with historical remarks and anecdotes. &#8212; Florian Cajori, A History of Mathematics.</p></blockquote>
<span class="dropcap">T</span>en years ago a dear friend of mine gave me a copy of Earl W. Swokowski&#8217;s 6th edition of Calculus (now out of print). The book contains several short historical sketches called &#8220;Mathematicians and Their Times&#8221; attempting to show a more human side of mathematics in a hope that these brief introductions will whet the appetites of readers to explore the fascinating history of mathematics on their own. I really enjoyed reading about:</p>
<ul>
<li>The life, and horrible death, of the first (known) woman mathematician Hypatia,</li>
<li>The dreams of René Descartes who created Analytic Geometry to join algebra and geometry,</li>
<li>The shyness of the great mathematician Pierre de Fermat who didn&#8217;t have a degree in mathematics.</li>
<li>The bitter <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leibniz%E2%80%93Newton_calculus_controversy">controversy</a> that arose concerning the discovery of calculus between Newton and Leibniz that drove a wedge between British and Continental intellectual communities, hampering the development of calculus.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Bernoulli#Private_life">disturbing jealousy</a> in the Bernoulli family of mathematicians leading to name calling between brothers and Johann Bernoulli expelling his own son from home after awarded the French Academy of Sciences prize.</li>
<li>The phenomenal memory of Leonhard Euler and ability to concentrate on difficult problems while surrounded by 13 playing children and being blind for 17 years! He introduced or established the use of many common mathematical notations and discovered the &#8220;mystical formula&#8221; <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">e^{\pi i}+1=0</span> linking the five most significant numbers in mathematics.</li>
</ul>
<p>Since then I use the same technique in lectures I give to my students to catch their attention; that is one goal of this post. However, another important goal is to link Geometric Algebra to mathematics on the fundamental level of numbers. Here I briefly describe the history of numbers with emphasis on their functional role in mathematics, science, and engineering to put the computational role GA can play into perspective.</p>
<h3>How to Count Sheep and Build Pyramids</h3>
<blockquote><p>It is India that gave us the ingenious method of expressing all numbers by means of ten symbols, each symbol receiving a value of position as well as an absolute value; a profound and important idea which appears so simple to us now that we ignore its true merit. &#8212; Pierre Simon Marquis de Laplace.</p></blockquote>
<p>The first functional use of numbers in human history was, naturally, to count and compare items for trading and regularizing society. Creating the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seven_Wonders_of_the_Ancient_World">wonders of the ancient world</a> and accumulating impressively accurate calendars and <a href="http://www.starteachastronomy.com/archaeoastronomy.html">astronomical observations</a> certainly required advanced numerical skills. Some advanced societies in ancient times (the ancient Egyptians, Babylonians, Chinese, and Indians for example) required a symbolic form of numbers that can represent quantities efficiently while doing arithmetic<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-1' id='enref-251-1' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>1</a></sup>.</p>
<div id="attachment_296" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Platonic-Solids1.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-296" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Platonic-Solids1-300x236.jpg" alt="Platonic Solids" width="300" height="236" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Platonic-Solids1-300x236.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Platonic-Solids1-768x603.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Platonic-Solids1-1024x804.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Platonic-Solids1.jpg 1179w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Greeks associated geometry with philosophy (<a href="http://joedubs.com/platonic-solids/">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>Greek mathematics, on the other hand, was founded on geometrical ideas, like lengths, areas, and volumes, that left no room for negative numbers, for example. They didn&#8217;t use anything similar to real numbers in proofs and logical arguments because they represented magnitudes by lines or areas constructed geometrically. They practically avoided irrationals using this technique<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-2' id='enref-251-2' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>2</a></sup>. Irrational numbers appear in even the simplest sorts of measurements, as the Pythagoreans discovered when they found that the diagonal of certain geometric figures may be incommensurable with their sides. This discovery upset the conventional mathematical wisdom of the time, and the penalty was death for those who revealed the secret<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-3' id='enref-251-3' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>3</a></sup>. The Greek were horrified by the implications of this discovery that they took a step backward. Where the Pythagoreans claimed the unity of numbers and geometric extension, the later Greeks denied it. Hence, one could not associate numbers with lengths. This caused an unfortunate split between the disciplines of geometry, which dealt with points and lines (extension), and algebra, which dealt with numbers<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-4' id='enref-251-4' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>4</a></sup>.</p>
<p>The most important advancements of these ancient times, negative numbers, the decimal place-value system, and the use of zero, were made by the Indian mathematicians<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-5' id='enref-251-5' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>5</a></sup> and then translated, used, and spread to renaissance Europe 1000 years later by the Islamic civilization.  A surprising fact I came across is that negative numbers did not begin to appear in Europe until the 15th century when scholars began to study and translate the ancient texts that had been recovered from Islamic and Byzantine sources<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-6' id='enref-251-6' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>6</a></sup>. European mathematicians resisted the concept of negative numbers until the 17th century and some referred to them as “absurd quantities&#8221; <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-7' id='enref-251-7' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>7</a></sup>.</p>
<p>The main point that remains constant when reading the history of numbers is: a number system is advanced by the needs of civilization and, at the same time, civilization is advanced by the development of its number system. The concept of a number is practically the fundamental abstraction of all mathematics and science.</p>
<h3>The Rational Laws of Inheritance</h3>
<blockquote><p>The imam and emir of the believers, al-Ma&#8217;mun, encouraged me to write a concise work on the calculations al-jabr (Calculation by Completion) and al-muqabala (Balancing), confined to a pleasant and interesting art of calculation, which people constantly have need of for their inheritances, their wills, their judgements and their transactions, and in all the things they have to do together, notably, the measurement of land, the digging of canals, geometry and other things of that kind. &#8212; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muḥammad_ibn_Mūsā_al-Khwārizmī">Al-Khwarizmi</a>, The Compendious Book on Calculation by Completion and Balancing <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-8' id='enref-251-8' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>8</a></sup>.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_294" style="width: 222px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/d.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-294" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/d-212x300.jpg" alt="Islamic Inheritance Rules" width="212" height="300" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/d-212x300.jpg 212w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/d-768x1086.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/d-724x1024.jpg 724w" sizes="(max-width: 212px) 100vw, 212px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">One simplified version of Islamic inheritance rules</p></div>
<p>The next important function for numbers in human history was to compare ratios of units. The use of ratios motivated the invention of algebra in the form of equations in one unknown that when found results in a rational number. Historically, the terms <strong>algebra</strong> and <strong>algorithm</strong> originate from the same source: the book &#8220;Kitab al muhtasar fi hisab al-gabr w&#8217;al-muqabalah&#8221; by the Muslim scientist Abu Ja&#8217;far Mohammed ibn Musa al-Khorezmi compiled at the academy of science in Bagdad in the ninth century &#8211; uses &#8220;al-gabr&#8221; and &#8220;muqabalah&#8221; to describe symbolic transformations and term reductions respectively, which are performed to solve algebraic equations<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-9' id='enref-251-9' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>9</a></sup>. Algorithmic manipulation of symbolic algebraic expressions remained to be the major task of algebra about until the end of the nineteenth century. At the beginning of the twentieth century, this method was amended and shadowed by developments in abstract algebra. There, the main interest is focused on formal investigations of algebraic structures derived from axioms. This structural algebraic method has taken over considerable parts of mathematics nowadays<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-10' id='enref-251-10' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>10</a></sup>.</p>
<p>As in the case of the decimal system, zero and other ancient advancements, the Islamic civilization translated, developed, and applied these mathematical concepts for hundreds of years until modern European civilization took place. The foundation and soul of the Islamic civilization is the Revelation in its two forms: Qur&#8217;an and Sunnah. The rules for inheritance<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-11' id='enref-251-11' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>11</a></sup> are accurately specified in the revelation but require some degree of mathematical sophistication to be computed correctly. Such rules were the main reason behind the widespread use of rational numbers and the development of algebra back then<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-12' id='enref-251-12' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>12</a></sup>. As stated in one article<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-13' id='enref-251-13' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>13</a></sup>:</p>
<blockquote><p>Perhaps one of the most significant advances made by Arabic mathematics<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-14' id='enref-251-14' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>14</a></sup> began at this time with the work of al-Khwarizmi, namely the beginnings of algebra. It is important to understand just how significant this new idea was. It was a revolutionary move away from the Greek concept of mathematics which was essentially geometry. Algebra was a unifying theory which allowed rational numbers, irrational numbers, geometrical magnitudes, etc., to all be treated as &#8220;algebraic objects&#8221;. It gave mathematics a whole new development path so much broader in concept to that which had existed before, and provided a vehicle for future development of the subject. Another important aspect of the introduction of algebraic ideas was that it allowed mathematics to be applied to itself in a way which had not happened before.</p></blockquote>
<p>Although Arab mathematicians are most well known for their work on algebra, number theory, and number systems, they also made considerable contributions to geometry, trigonometry, and mathematical astronomy<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-15' id='enref-251-15' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>15</a></sup>. The advancement of the number concept, and mathematics in general, by the Islamic civilization enabled remarkable achievements in all aspects of science and technology and directly affected all the following development of mathematics in the last 400 years<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-16' id='enref-251-16' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>16</a></sup> <sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-17' id='enref-251-17' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>17</a></sup>. A more fundamental influence of the Islamic civilization on the scientific knowledge of the human race is clearly stated by Robert Briffault in his 1919 book “The Making of Humanity” (publicly available for <a href="https://archive.org/details/makingofhumanity00brifrich">download here</a>):</p>
<blockquote><p>The debt of our science to that of the Arabs does not consist in startling discoveries or revolutionary theories; science owes a great deal more to Arab culture, it owes its existence. The ancient world was, as we saw, pre-scientific. The astronomy and mathematics of the Greeks were a foreign importation never thoroughly acclimatized in Greek culture. The Greeks systematized, generalized and theorized, but the patient ways of investigation, the accumulation of positive knowledge, the minute methods of science, detailed and prolonged observation, experimental inquiry, were altogether alien to the Greek temperament. Only in Hellenistic Alexandria was any, approach to scientific work conducted in the ancient classical world. What we call science arose in Europe as a result of a new spirit of inquiry, of new methods of investigation, of the method of experiment, observation, measurement, of the development of mathematics in a form unknown to the Greeks. That spirit and those methods were introduced into the European world by the Arabs.</p></blockquote>
<h3>Caught in the Field</h3>
<blockquote><p>Mathematics is the queen of the sciences and number theory is the queen of mathematics. She often condescends to render service to astronomy and other natural sciences, but in all relations she is entitled to the first rank. &#8212; Carl Friedrich Gauss.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_292" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/dscn7165.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-292" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/dscn7165-300x225.jpg" alt="The fractals of nature are periodic discrete patterns " width="300" height="225" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/dscn7165-300x225.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/dscn7165-768x575.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/dscn7165-1024x767.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/dscn7165.jpg 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The fractals of nature are periodic discrete patterns</p></div>
<p>Any serious study of the universe reveals a fascinating fact: periodic patterns of discrete nature are <a href="http://fractalfoundation.org/category/natural-fractals/">everywhere</a>. Number theory<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-18' id='enref-251-18' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>18</a></sup> has captured the attention of the best mathematical minds of history for centuries. The research done in this area by great mathematicians like Euler, Gauss, and Riemann, has shown that it is not only beautiful and fascinating, but intimately connected with many other mathematical subjects like analysis, algebraic geometry, and topology. Many concepts in group theory and abstract algebra are in fact generalizations of the properties of integers that have originated from the work of 18th and 19th-century mathematicians in number theory<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-19' id='enref-251-19' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>19</a></sup>. Division of integers (resulting in rational numbers) and properties of prime numbers can be studied using the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modular_arithmetic">modulus</a> operation. When you are doing a modulus operation (Mod n), you are basically dealing with a periodic function that goes from 0 to n-1 and then repeats itself all over again. That gave rise to one important abstraction in mathematics: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finite_field#Applications">The Finite Field</a>. In this way, number theory helps us define periodic properties of systems that are concerned with whole or rational numbers. This is directly related to modern applications in cryptography<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-20' id='enref-251-20' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>20</a></sup>, error correcting codes<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-21' id='enref-251-21' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>21</a></sup>, and simulation<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-22' id='enref-251-22' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>22</a></sup>.</p>
<div id="attachment_582" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Fractal_pyramid.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-582" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Fractal_pyramid-300x261.jpg" alt="Fractal_pyramid" width="300" height="261" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Fractal_pyramid-300x261.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Fractal_pyramid.jpg 621w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">A relatively recent approach to understanding the nature of fundamental physics, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P-adic_quantum_mechanics">p-adic quantum mechanics</a>, involves the application of p-adic analysis to quantum mechanics.</p></div>
<p>One of the overriding problems in contemporary computing is the accumulation of rounding errors to such a degree as to make the final result all but useless. The currently dominant computational number system in is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IEEE_floating_point">IEEE Standard for Floating-Point Arithmetic;</a> a very error prone system as we will see in <a href="/index.php/2015/08/14/history-of-numbers3/">part 3</a> of this functional history of numbers. Using finite fields and number theory we can arrive at clever ways for performing fast, error-free digital computations based on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farey_sequence">Farey fractions</a> and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_remainder_theorem">Chinese remainder theorem</a><sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-23' id='enref-251-23' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>23</a></sup>. Another approach is by using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P-adic_number">p-adic Arithmetic</a>, a counter-intuitive arithmetic system<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-24' id='enref-251-24' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>24</a></sup>, as a base for fast error-free computations as a possible alternative for the floating-point numbers<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-25' id='enref-251-25' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>25</a></sup>.</p>
<p>The fact that number theory has few direct applications in engineering is unfortunate but understandable. Number theory is indeed like a queen that seldom interact with the commoners directly, nevertheless influences the whole kingdom by its rulings.</p>
<h3>Continuum: Imagining The Real Numbers</h3>
<blockquote><p>The idea of the continuum seems simple to us. We have somehow lost sight of the difficulties it implies…We are told such a number as the square root of 2 worried Pythagoras and his school almost to exhaustion. Being used to such queer numbers from early childhood, we must be careful not to form a low idea of the mathematical intuition of these ancient sages; their worry was highly credible. &#8212; Erwin Schrödinger.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_290" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/slow_motion_photo_stills-1680x1050.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-290" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/slow_motion_photo_stills-1680x1050-300x188.jpg" alt="the apparent continuity of creation" width="300" height="188" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/slow_motion_photo_stills-1680x1050-300x188.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/slow_motion_photo_stills-1680x1050-768x480.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/slow_motion_photo_stills-1680x1050-1024x640.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">We use Real numbers to model the apparent continuity of creation</p></div>
<p>The set of real numbers rests by all means at the foundation of modern mathematical activity, theoretical and applied. In modern days the word &#8220;number&#8221; is almost equivalent in our minds to &#8220;real number&#8221;. The main function of real numbers is to model the concepts like &#8220;continuum&#8221; and &#8220;continuous motion&#8221; that have always been present in the minds of all mathematicians and scientists, ancient and modern.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m no mathematician, but as an engineer, I&#8217;ve always struggled with irrational and transcendental real numbers. These numbers are &#8220;results of infinite processes&#8221; that can only be expressed symbolically like <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\pi</span>, e, and <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\sqrt{2}</span>, or represented approximately as decimals with finite precision; something is definitely bothering about this class of elusive numbers<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-26' id='enref-251-26' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>26</a></sup>. During high school, to my surprise, I read about paradoxes resulting from the concept of &#8220;continuous real number line&#8221; and &#8220;uncountable infinite sets&#8221; like the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banach%E2%80%93Tarski_paradox">Banach–Tarski paradox</a>. That led me later to some articles questioning the &#8220;<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/math/0411418">reality of real numbers</a>&#8220;; some made by Turing himself<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-27' id='enref-251-27' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>27</a></sup> on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computable_number">computable numbers</a>. Recently I discovered the tangential thoughts of N.J. Wildberger about the <a href="https://njwildberger.com/2012/12/02/difficulties-with-real-numbers/">difficulties with real numbers:</a></p>
<blockquote><p>A hundred years ago, the notion of the “continuum” appeared intuitively straightforward, but it was difficult to pin down precisely. The Greeks had struggled with irrational numbers, but the decimal number approach of Simon Stevin in the 16th century seemed reasonable, especially considering that in practice the further digits beyond the three dots in pi=3.14159263… are hardly of practical significance. Great mathematicians like Newton, Euler, Gauss, Lagrange and others were always interested in a combination of applied questions (physics and astronomy mostly) along with more theoretical questions. In the later part of the nineteenth century an increasing preoccupation with trying to pin down the fundamentals of analysis led to both more careful definitions but also to the realization that the default view of irrational numbers as infinite decimals was shaky.<br />
However with the advent of relativity theory and quantum mechanics, the concept of the continuum again became murky: if time is relative and perhaps finite in extent, and space has an inherent graininess which is not infinitely divisible, then what exactly are we modelling with our notion of the &#8216;infinite number line&#8217;?<br />
While engineers and scientists viewed real numbers primarily as “decimals which go on till we don’t care anymore”, nineteenth century mathematicians introduced the ideas of “equivalence classes of Cauchy sequences of rational numbers”, or as “Dedekind cuts”, or sometimes as “continued fractions”. Each view has different difficulties, but always there is the crucial problem of discussing `infinite objects’ without sufficient regard to how to specify them.</p></blockquote>
<p>Some physicists took some steps to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real_number#In_physics">avoid real numbers</a> in the foundations of physics. As an engineer, I know real numbers are useful and indispensable abstractions, but I realized long ago they are too abstract (i.e. too detached from the physical world) to be taken for granted as completely consistent with applications. As a software developer I know, in agreement with Wildberger&#8217;s view, we need to avoid irrational numbers in our software whenever we can for many practical reasons. If <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\pi</span> appears in an intermediate equation in my model I should rewrite the equations to eliminate <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\pi</span> from the final algorithm to be implemented whenever possible. For real numbers to be functional we, software developers, need to avoid coding most of them!</p>
<h3>Fractions &#8230; To Be Continued</h3>
<blockquote><p>But, surprisingly, one of the most striking and powerful representations of numbers is completely ignored in the mathematics that is taught in schools and it rarely makes an appearance in university courses, unless you take a special option in number theory. Yet continued fractions are one of the most revealing representations of numbers. Numbers whose decimal expansions look unremarkable and featureless are revealed to have extraordinary symmetries and patterns embedded deep within them when unfolded into a continued fraction. &#8212; John D. Barrow, <a href="https://plus.maths.org/content/chaos-numberland-secret-life-continued-fractions">Chaos in Numberland: The secret life of continued fractions</a>.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_567" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/phi-dna.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-567" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/phi-dna-300x278.jpg" alt="phi-dna" width="300" height="278" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/phi-dna-300x278.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/phi-dna.jpg 558w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">The golden ration can be found everywhere in nature even in our DNA (<a href="http://www.interferencetheory.com/Articles/ArticlesGoldenRatio/files/5d222bf41ab67d8a339b4aa3f165c797-4.html">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>Not all irrationals are created equal, some are more irrational than others. The most irrational of all real numbers is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_ratio">Golden Ratio</a> <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\varphi=\frac{1}{2}(1+\sqrt{5})</span>; it&#8217;s the hardest irrational to approximate by any rational number<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-28' id='enref-251-28' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>28</a></sup>. Some of the greatest mathematical minds of all ages have spent endless hours over this simple ratio and its properties. Many books<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-29' id='enref-251-29' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>29</a></sup> have been written specifically for exploring its, often unexpected, appearances in biology, arts, music, history, architecture, and psychology<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-30' id='enref-251-30' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>30</a></sup>. One of the best ways for studying this fascinating number is by its <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continued_fraction">continued fraction</a> representation [1; 1, 1, 1, &#8230;].</p>
<div id="attachment_558" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/continued-fraction-pi.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-558" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/continued-fraction-pi-300x208.png" alt="A continued fraction approximation of Pi: [3; 7, 15, 1, 292, 1, 1, 2, ...] (Source)" width="300" height="208" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/continued-fraction-pi-300x208.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/continued-fraction-pi.png 575w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">A continued fraction approximation of Pi: [3; 7, 15, 1, 292, 1, 1, 2, &#8230;] (<a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/roots-of-unity/don-8217-t-recite-digits-to-celebrate-pi-recite-its-continued-fraction-instead/">Source</a>)</p></div>Continued fractions can be used to reveal many interesting properties of many <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mathematical_constants_by_continued_fraction_representation">interesting numbers</a>; they possess many outstanding properties:</p>
<ul>
<li>Rational numbers have unique finite continued fraction representations; irrational numbers have unique infinite representations. Contrast this property to traditional number systems (for example decimal and binary) that have infinite representations for both rationals and irrationals.</li>
<li>Continued fractions are, in a quantifiable way, the best approximations of numbers. If you truncate the continued fraction expansion of a number q, the rational number that you get is the closest you can get to q without having to resort to a larger denominator.</li>
<li>The continued fraction expansion of the square root of an integer (that isn&#8217;t a perfect square) always repeats. For example the square root of 3 has a representation [1; 1, 2, 1, 2, 1, 2, &#8230;]. Moreover, partial fractions with repeating numbers are exactly the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadratic_irrational">quadratic irrationals</a>.</li>
<li>There is a very high probability that integers appearing in continued fraction representations are of small value; the probability distribution of such integers is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gauss%E2%80%93Kuzmin_distribution">Gauss–Kuzmin distribution</a><sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-31' id='enref-251-31' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>31</a></sup>.</li>
</ul>
<div id="attachment_578" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/elec-ladder.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-578" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/elec-ladder-300x166.png" alt="elec-ladder" width="300" height="166" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/elec-ladder-300x166.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/elec-ladder.png 370w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Electrical ladder network input impedance Z is given by continued fraction. See <a href="https://projecteuclid.org/euclid.bams/1183493356">this paper</a> for detailed analysis</p></div>
<p>Continued fractions appear in the study of many chaotic systems. Numbers whose Continued fractions end in an infinite string of 1&#8217;s, like the golden ratio, are called noble numbers. The golden mean is the &#8220;noblest&#8221; of all because all of its quotients are 1&#8217;s. The designation &#8220;noble numbers&#8221; stem from the fact that in many nonlinear dynamical systems “winding numbers”, the frequency ratios of orbits in phase space, that equal noble numbers are the most resistant against the onset of chaotic motion, which is ubiquitous in nature<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-32' id='enref-251-32' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>32</a></sup>; think of turbulence or the weather, for that matter. The very stability of the entire solar system depends on the nobility of orbital period ratios<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-33' id='enref-251-33' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>33</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Continued fractions have many important geometric interpretations, especially in terms of <a href="http://www.geometrie.tugraz.at/karpenkov/cf2011s.html">integer geometry</a>; the geometry of points that are pairwise integer distances apart<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-34' id='enref-251-34' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>34</a></sup>. In addition, the same idea behind continued fractions can be applied to approximate general functions by rational functions; the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pad%C3%A9_approximant">Padé approximant</a>. The Padé approximant often gives a better approximation of the function than truncating its Taylor series, and it may still work where the Taylor series does not converge. For these reasons Padé approximants are used extensively in computer calculations. I believe that many problems in science and engineering can be approached much effectively using continued fractions and their generalizations; we just need to have a deeper understanding of such problems to detect their &#8220;fractionally continued&#8221; nature.</p>
<h3>The Lateral Unity</h3>
<blockquote><p>I tell you, with complex numbers you can do anything. &#8212; John Derbyshire.</p></blockquote>
<p>Complex numbers are not just another generalization of real numbers on the &#8220;number line&#8221;; they literally introduce a whole new dimension to the &#8220;concept of number&#8221; allowing the symbolic representation and manipulation of geometric entities on a higher level than real numbers do. This is similar in some degree to the use of C instead of Assembly in software development for example. As an electrical engineer, I use complex numbers in many applications in signal processing, electrical circuits, and many others. The most important mathematical function for electrical engineers is the &#8220;vector rotating at frequency <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\omega</span>&#8220;: <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">e^{i\omega t}</span>. The whole of Fourier Transform theory is based on this single complex function with a significant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imaginary_number#Geometric_interpretation">geometric interpretation</a>. Historically the algebraic representation of complex numbers came first in the 16th century when trying to find real algebraic solutions for the roots of cubic and quartic polynomials; hitting the wall of the &#8220;roots of negative numbers&#8221;. The term &#8220;imaginary&#8221; for these quantities was coined by René Descartes, although he was at pains to stress their imaginary nature. It was Gauss who introduced the term &#8220;complex number&#8221; when submitting his ideas to the Royal Society of Gottingen. He provided a geometric representation of this class of numbers<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-35' id='enref-251-35' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>35</a></sup>:</p>
<blockquote><p>If this subject has hitherto been considered from the wrong viewpoint and thus enveloped in mystery and surrounded by darkness, it is largely an unsuitable terminology which should be blamed. Had +1, -1 and <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">\sqrt{-1}</span>, instead of being called positive, negative and imaginary (or worse still, impossible) unity, been given the names say, of direct, inverse and lateral unity, there would hardly have been any scope for such obscurity.</p></blockquote>
<div id="attachment_285" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/ComplexSet-big.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-285" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/ComplexSet-big-300x219.png" alt="Complex Numbers" width="300" height="219" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/ComplexSet-big-300x219.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/ComplexSet-big-768x561.png 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2015/07/ComplexSet-big.png 974w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Complex Numbers (<a href="http://thinkzone.wlonk.com/Numbers/NumberSets.htm">Source</a>)</p></div>
<p>Complex numbers are indispensable for modern science and engineering; mainly because they contain all other commonly used sets of numbers while adding more meaning and power. Nevertheless, the most important function of complex numbers, in my opinion, is generalizing the concept of a number from 1 dimension to 2 dimensions in a geometric manner; logically backed by algebra. The Cartesian form of a complex number <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">x+iy</span> introduced the important idea of &#8220;formal sum&#8221; of algebraic quantities (real <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">x</span> and imaginary <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">iy</span>) to the common math user; including high school students. The polar form of a complex number <span class="wp-katex-eq" data-display="false">re^{i\theta}</span> introduced the geometric meaning of the product operation as a &#8220;scaled rotation transformation&#8221;. Just reading the first chapter of Needham&#8217;s brilliant book &#8220;Visual Complex Analysis&#8221;<sup class='endnote'><a href='#en-251-36' id='enref-251-36' onclick='return hhEndnotes_show(251)'>36</a></sup> can show you the depth of algebraic expressiveness for geometric ideas complex numbers can have. Using the Cartesian and polar forms of  complex numbers one can:</p>
<ul>
<li>Extend the concept of a number from 1 dimension (the number line) to 2 dimensions (the complex plane).</li>
<li>Represent points and vectors in a plane using a single symbolic entity with a full set of operations (i.e. a complex number and its arithmetic).</li>
<li>Represent the operations of translation (using the addition of complex numbers) and scaled rotation (using complex numbers multiplication) in a plane that can act on points and vectors; effectively unifying &#8220;data&#8221; and &#8220;processing&#8221; algebraically using a single algebraic entity, the complex number.</li>
<li>Allowing geometric transformations to be expressed as functions (maps) on the complex plane; a very powerful concept linking geometry to calculus.</li>
</ul>
<p>These ideas are fundamental for the following developments of the concept of a number that we will continue perusing in <a href="/index.php/2015/08/07/history-of-numbers2/">part two</a> of this functional history of numbers.</p>
<p><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/done2.png"><img class="alignright size-full wp-image-298" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/done2.png" alt="done2" width="300" height="40" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<hr />
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class='endnotes' id='hhendnotes-251'>
<ol>
<li id='en-251-1'>Calvin C. Clawson, &#8220;The Mathematical Traveler, Exploring the Grand History of Numbers&#8221;. Springer Science 1994 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-1'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-2'>James Gow, &#8220;A Short History of Greek Mathematics&#8221;, Cambridge University Press 2010 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-2'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-3'>Joseph H. Silverman, &#8220;A Friendly Introduction to Number Theory, 4th Edition&#8221;. Pearson 2012 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-3'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-4'>Calvin C. Clawson, &#8220;The Mathematical Traveler, Exploring the Grand History of Numbers&#8221;. Springer Science 1994 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-4'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-5'>A good online article of two parts giving a summary of the contributions of ancient Indian mathematicians can be found <a href="http://www.vedicsciences.net/articles/history-of-numbers.html">here</a> and <a href="http://www.vedicsciences.net/articles/history-of-numbers-part-2.html">here</a>. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-5'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-6'>J. L. Berggren, &#8220;Episodes in the Mathematics of Medieval Islam&#8221;. Springer 1986 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-6'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-7'>Art Johnson, &#8220;Famous Problems and Their Mathematicians&#8221;. Greenwood Publishing Group 1999 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-7'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-8'>For a very interesting documetary about some of the contrubutions of Al-Khawarizmi see Jim Al-Khalili&#8217;s &#8220;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sAxWF_W6Q9w">Science in a Golden Age &#8211; Al-Khwarizmi: The Father of Algebra</a>&#8221; <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-8'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-9'>This <a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/terry_moore_why_is_x_the_unknown?language=en">TED video</a> explains why is &#8216;x&#8217; the symbol for an unknown relating it to the Arabic word &#8220;Chay&#8217;a&#8221; or &#8220;thing&#8221; <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-9'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-10'>Johannes Grabmeier, Erich Kaltofen, Volker Weispfenning (Editors), &#8220;Computer Algebra Handbook &#8211; Foundations, Applications, Systems&#8221;. Springer 2003 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-10'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-11'>During my research for this post, I found some articles stating a misconception about females having less inheritance than males in Islam. The truth is giving women less inheritance is not a universal law of inheritance in Islam. As clearly explained <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamic_inheritance_jurisprudence#Women_and_inheritance">here</a>:<br />
<blockquote><p>However, this principle is not universally applicable, and there are other circumstances where women might receive equal shares to men. For example, the share of the mother and father of a childless decedent. Also the share of a uterine brother is equal to the share of a uterine sister, as do the shares of their descendants &#8230; Some times women get double the share then that of men, for example if there are only parents and husband, husband will receive half, father gets 1/6 and mother gets 2/6.</p></blockquote>
<p>A good study for the reasons behind giving less inheritance to women in some situations can be found <a href="http://www.kantakji.com/media/3799/4015.pdf">here</a>. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-11'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-12'>Contrast this religion-motivated development of science in the middle ages Islamic lands with the (lack of) development of science in the same period called dark age Europe that lasted until the 12th century, driven by religion and continuous wars in the direction of scientific degeneracy. See <a href="https://www.quora.com/Why-did-science-make-little-real-progress-in-Europe-in-the-Middle-Ages-3?redirected_qid=489923">this article</a> for more interesting details <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-12'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-13'>O&#8217;Connor, John J.; Robertson, Edmund F., &#8220;<a href="http://www-history.mcs.st-and.ac.uk/HistTopics/Arabic_mathematics.html">Arabic mathematics: forgotten brilliance?</a>&#8220;, MacTutor History of Mathematics archive, University of St Andrews. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-13'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-14'>more accurately Islamic mathematics, many Muslim scientists and mathematicians were not of Arab origin <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-14'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-15'>Salim T.S. Al-Hassani, &#8220;1001 Inventions: The Enduring Legacy of Muslim Civilization, 3rd Edition&#8221;. National Geographic 2012. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-15'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-16'>Firas Alkhateeb, &#8220;Lost Islamic History: Reclaiming Muslim Civilization from the Past 1st Edition&#8221;. Hurst 2014. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-16'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-17'>Michael H. Morgan, &#8220;Lost History: The Enduring Legacy of Muslim Scientists, Thinkers, and Artists&#8221;. National Geographic 2008 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-17'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-18'>Joseph H. Silverman, &#8220;A Friendly Introduction to Number Theory, 4th Edition&#8221;. Pearson 2012 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-18'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-19'>Diane L. Herrmann, Paul J. Sally Jr., &#8220;Number, Shape, &amp; Symmetry: An Introduction to Number Theory, Geometry, and Group Theory 1st Edition&#8221;. CRC Press 2012 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-19'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-20'>Jeffrey Hoffstein, Jill Pipher, and Joseph H. Silverman, &#8220;An Introduction to Mathematical Cryptography, 2nd Edition&#8221;. Springer Science 2014 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-20'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-21'>Oliver Pretzel, &#8220;Error-Correcting Codes and Finite Fields&#8221;. Clarendon Press 1992 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-21'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-22'>Stephen Wolfram, &#8220;A New Kind of Science&#8221;, Wolfram Media 2002 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-22'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-23'>See chapter 4 and 16 of M. R. Schroeder, &#8220;Number Theory in Science and Communication, 4th Edition&#8221;. Springer 2006 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-23'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-24'>You can find a very simple and informal introduction by N. J. Wildberger using &#8220;Reversimals&#8221; or 10-adic numbers <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XXRwlo_MHnI&amp;list=PL5A714C94D40392AB&amp;index=65">here</a>, and a tutorial for this system <a href="http://cryptocode.net/docs/r09.pdf">here</a> <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-24'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-25'>R. T. Gregory, E. V. Krishnamurthy, &#8220;Methods and Applications of Error-Free Computation&#8221;. Springer 1984 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-25'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-26'>See for example N.J. Wildberger&#8217;s video &#8220;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=REeaT2mWj6Y">Inconvenient truths about sqrt(2)</a>&#8221; <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-26'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-27'>B. Jack Copeland, &#8220;The Essential Turing&#8221;. Clarendon Press, Oxford 2004. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-27'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-28'>Jay Kappraff, &#8220;Beyond Measure &#8211; A Guided Tour Through Nature, Myth, and Number&#8221;. World Scientific 2002 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-28'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-29'>See for example Livio, Mario, &#8220;The Golden Ratio: The Story of Phi, The World&#8217;s Most Astonishing Number&#8221;. Broadway Books 2002, and H.E. Huntley, &#8220;The Divine Proportion: A Study in Mathematical Beauty&#8221;. Dover Publications 1970 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-29'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-30'><a href="https://www.goldennumber.net/">This site</a> is dedicated to sharing the best information on Phi with insights from dozens of Contributors on a broad range of topics. <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-30'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-31'>This is explained more in John D. Barrow article <a href="https://plus.maths.org/content/chaos-numberland-secret-life-continued-fractions">here</a> <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-31'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-32'>M. R. Schroeder, &#8220;Number Theory in Science and Communication, 4th Edition&#8221;. Springer 2006 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-32'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-33'>See <a href="https://tallbloke.wordpress.com/2013/02/20/a-remarkable-discovery-all-solar-system-periods-fit-the-fibonacci-series-and-the-golden-ratio-why-phi/">this article</a> relating Solar system periods to the Golden Ratio <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-33'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-34'>Oleg Karpenkov, &#8220;Geometry of Continued Fractions&#8221;. Springer 2013 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-34'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-35'>Paul J. Nahin, &#8220;An Imaginary Tale&#8221;. Princeton University Press 1998 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-35'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
<li id='en-251-36'>Tristan Needham, &#8220;Visual Complex Analysis&#8221;. Oxford University Press 2000 <span class='endnotereverse'><a href='#enref-251-36'>&#8617;</a></span></li>
</ol>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/">A Functional History of Numbers (1 of 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Geometric Algebra Explorer</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/index.php/2015/07/24/history-of-numbers1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
